[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "If \\(\\int\\left(e^{2 x}+2 e^{x}-e^{-x}-1\\right) e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)} d x=g(x) e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)}+c\\), where \\(c\\) is a constant of integeration, then \\(g(0)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(e\\)",
            "\\(e^{2}\\)",
            "1",
            "2"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\int\\left(e^{2 x}+2 e^{x}-e^{-x}-1\\right) \\cdot e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(I=\\int\\left(e^{2 x}+e^{x}-1\\right) \\cdot e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)} d x+\\int\\left(e^{x}-e^{-x}\\right) e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int e^{x}\\left(e^{x}+1-e^{-x}\\right) \\cdot e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)} d x+e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)}\\)\n\n\\(=\\int\\left(e^{x}-e^{-x}+1\\right) e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}+x\\right)} d x+e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)}\\)\n\nLet \\(e^{x}+e^{-x}+x=t \\Rightarrow\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}+1\\right) d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(=\\int e^{t} d t+e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)}=e^{t}+e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)}+C\\)\n\n\\(=e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}+x\\right)}+e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)}+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\left(e^{x}+1\\right) \\cdot e^{\\left(e^{x}+e^{-x}\\right)}+C\\)\n\nSo, \\(g(x)=1+e^{x}\\) and \\(g(0)=2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{\\cos \\theta}{5+7 \\sin \\theta-2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta} d \\theta=A \\log _{e}|B(\\theta)|+C\\), where \\(C\\) is a constant of integration, then \\(\\frac{B(\\theta)}{A}\\) can be :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{2 \\sin \\theta+1}{\\sin \\theta+3}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{2 \\sin \\theta+1}{5(\\sin \\theta+3)}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{5(\\sin \\theta+3)}{2 \\sin \\theta+1}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{5(2 \\sin \\theta+1)}{\\sin \\theta+3}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Let \\(\\sin \\theta=t \\Rightarrow \\cos \\theta d \\theta=d t\\)\n\n\n\\(\\int \\frac{\\cos \\theta}{5+7 \\sin \\theta-2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta} d \\theta=\\frac{d t}{5+7 t-2+2 t^{2}}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{1}{2} \\int \\frac{d t}{\\left(t+\\frac{7}{4}\\right)^{2}-\\left(\\frac{5}{4}\\right)^{2}}=\\frac{1}{5} \\ln \\left|\\frac{t+\\frac{1}{2}}{t+3}\\right|+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{5} \\ln \\left|\\frac{2 t+1}{t+3}\\right|+C=\\frac{1}{5} \\ln \\left|\\frac{2 \\sin \\theta+1}{\\sin \\theta+3}\\right|+C\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore B(\\theta)=\\frac{2 \\sin \\theta+1}{2(\\sin \\theta+3)}\\) and \\(A=\\frac{1}{5}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{B(\\theta)}{A}=\\frac{5(2 \\sin \\theta+1)}{(\\sin \\theta+3)}\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int\\left(\\frac{x}{x \\sin x+\\cos x}\\right)^{2} d x\\) is equal to (where \\(C\\) is a constant of integration) :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\tan x-\\frac{x \\sec x}{x \\sin x+\\cos x}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\sec x+\\frac{x \\tan x}{x \\sin x+\\cos x}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\sec x-\\frac{x \\tan x}{x \\sin x+\\cos x}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\tan x+\\frac{x \\sec x}{x \\sin x+\\cos x}+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (a) \\(\\int \\frac{x^{2}}{(x \\sin x+\\cos x)^{2}} d x\\)\n\n\\(\\because \\frac{d}{d x}(x \\sin x+\\cos x)=x \\cos x\\)\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-126}\n\\end{center}\n\n\\(=\\frac{x}{\\cos x}\\left[\\frac{-1}{x \\sin x+\\cos x}\\right]\\)\n\n\\[\n-\\int \\frac{x \\sin x+\\cos x}{\\cos ^{2} x}\\left[\\frac{-1}{x \\sin x+\\cos x}\\right] d x\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\frac{x}{\\cos x}\\left[\\frac{-1}{x \\sin x+\\cos x}\\right]+\\int \\sec ^{2} x d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{-x \\sec x}{x \\sin x+\\cos x}+\\tan x+C\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "Let \\(f(x)=\\int \\frac{\\sqrt{x}}{(1+x)^{2}} d x(x \\geq 0)\\). Then \\(f(3)-f(1)\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(-\\frac{\\pi}{12}+\\frac{1}{2}+\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{6}+\\frac{1}{2}-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{4}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{\\pi}{6}+\\frac{1}{2}+\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{12}+\\frac{1}{2}-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{4}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "(d) \\(\\int \\frac{\\sqrt{x}}{(1+x)^{2}} d x (x>0)\\)\\ Put \\(x=\\tan ^{2} \\theta \\Rightarrow 2 x d x=2 \\tan \\theta \\sec ^{2} \\theta d \\theta\\)\\ \\(I=\\int \\frac{2 \\tan ^{2} \\theta \\cdot \\sec ^{2} \\theta}{\\sec ^{4} \\theta} d \\theta=\\int 2 \\sin ^{2} \\theta d \\theta\\)\\ \\(=\\theta-\\frac{\\sin 2 \\theta}{2}+C\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow f(x)=\\theta-\\frac{1}{2} \\times \\frac{2 \\tan \\theta}{1+\\tan ^{2} \\theta}+C\\)\\ \\(f(x)=\\theta-\\frac{\\tan \\theta}{1+\\tan ^{2} \\theta}+C=\\tan ^{-1} \\sqrt{x}-\\frac{\\sqrt{x}}{1+x}+C\\)\\ Now \\(f(3)-f(1)=\\tan ^{-1}(\\sqrt{3})-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{1+3}-\\tan ^{-1}(1)+\\frac{1}{2}\\)\\ \\[=\\frac{\\pi}{12}+\\frac{1}{2}-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{4}\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\sin ^{-1}\\left(\\sqrt{\\frac{x}{1+x}}\\right) d x=A(x) \\tan ^{-1}(\\sqrt{x})+B(x)+C\\), where \\(C\\) is a constant of integration, then the ordered pair \\((A(x)\\), \\(B(x)\\) ) can be :",
        "options": [
            "\\((x+1,-\\sqrt{x})\\)",
            "\\((x+1, \\sqrt{x})\\)",
            "\\((x-1,-\\sqrt{x})\\)",
            "\\((x-1, \\sqrt{x})\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(I=\\int \\sin ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{x}}{\\sqrt{1+x}}\\right) d x=\\int \\tan ^{-1} \\sqrt{x} \\cdot 1 d x\\)\\\\\n\\(=x \\tan ^{-1} \\sqrt{x}-\\int \\frac{1}{1+x} \\cdot \\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{x}} \\cdot x d x+C\\)\\\\\n\\(=x \\tan ^{-1} \\sqrt{x}-\\frac{1}{2} \\int \\frac{t \\cdot 2 t d t}{1+t^{2}}+C\\)\n\n\n(Put \\(x=t^{2} \\Rightarrow d x=2 t d t\\) )\n\n\\(=x \\tan ^{-1} \\sqrt{x}-\\int \\frac{t^{2}}{1+t^{2}} d t+C\\)\n\n\\(=x \\tan ^{-1} \\sqrt{x}-t+\\tan ^{-1} t+C\\)\n\n\\(=x \\tan ^{-1} \\sqrt{x}-\\sqrt{x}+\\tan ^{-1} \\sqrt{x}+C\\)\n\n\\(=(x+1) \\tan ^{-1} \\sqrt{x}-\\sqrt{x}+C\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow A(x)=x+1 \\Rightarrow B(x)=-\\sqrt{x}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{d x}{(x+4)^{8 / 7}(x-3)^{6 / 7}}\\) is equal to: (where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration)",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\left(\\frac{x-3}{x+4}\\right)^{1 / 7}+C\\)",
            "\\(-\\left(\\frac{x-3}{x+4}\\right)^{-1 / 7}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\frac{x-3}{x+4}\\right)^{3 / 7}+C\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{13}\\left(\\frac{x-3}{x+4}\\right)^{-13 / 7}+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(\\quad I=\\int \\frac{d x}{(x+4)^{8 / 7}(x-3)^{6 / 7}}\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int\\left(\\frac{x-3}{x+4}\\right)^{\\frac{-6}{7}} \\frac{1}{(x+4)^{2}} d x\\)\n\nLet \\(\\frac{x-3}{x+4}=t^{7}\\),\n\nDifferentiate on both sides, we get\n\n\\(\\frac{7}{(x+4)^{2}} d x=7 t^{6} d t\\)\n\nHence, \\(I=\\int t^{-6} t^{6} d t=t+C=\\left(\\frac{x-3}{x+4}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{7}}+C\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{d \\theta}{\\cos ^{2} \\theta(\\tan 2 \\theta+\\sec 2 \\theta)}=\\lambda \\tan \\theta+2 \\log _{\\mathrm{e}}|f(\\theta)|+\\) C where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration, then the ordered pair \\((\\lambda, f(\\theta))\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\((1,1-\\tan \\theta)\\)",
            "\\((-1,1-\\tan \\theta)\\)",
            "\\((-1,1+\\tan \\theta)\\)",
            "\\((1,1+\\tan \\theta)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\int \\frac{d \\theta}{\\cos ^{2} \\theta(\\tan 2 \\theta+\\sec 2 \\theta)}\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\sec ^{2} \\theta}{\\frac{1+\\tan ^{2} \\theta}{1-\\tan ^{2} \\theta}+\\frac{2 \\tan \\theta}{1-\\tan ^{2} \\theta}} d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\sec ^{2} \\theta\\left(1-\\tan ^{2} \\theta\\right)}{(1+\\tan \\theta)^{2}} d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\sec ^{2} \\theta(1-\\tan \\theta)}{1+\\tan \\theta} d \\theta\\)\n\nLet \\(\\tan \\theta=t \\Rightarrow \\sec ^{2} \\theta d \\theta=d t\\), then\n\n\\(I=\\int\\left(\\frac{1-t}{1+t}\\right) d t=\\int\\left(-1+\\frac{2}{1+t}\\right) d t\\)\n\n\\(=-t+2 \\log (1+t)+C\\)\n\n\\(=-\\tan \\theta+2 \\log (1+\\tan \\theta)+C\\)\n\nHence, by comparison \\(\\lambda=-1\\) and \\(f(x)=1+\\tan \\theta\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "If \\(\\frac{\\cos x d x}{\\sin ^{3} x\\left(1+\\sin ^{6} x\\right)^{2 / 3}}=f(x)\\left(1+\\sin ^{6} x\\right)^{1 /}+c\\) where \\(c\\) is a constant of integration, then \\(\\lambda f\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(-\\frac{9}{8}\\)",
            "2",
            "\\(\\frac{9}{8}\\)",
            "-2"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (d) Let \\(I=\\int \\frac{\\cos x d x}{\\sin ^{3} x\\left(1+\\sin ^{6} x\\right)^{2 / 3}}\\)\n\n\\(=f(x)\\left(1+\\sin ^{6} x\\right)^{1 / \\lambda}+\\mathrm{c}\\)\n\nIf \\(\\sin x=t\\)\n\nthen, \\(\\cos x d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int \\frac{d t}{t^{3}\\left(1+t^{6}\\right)^{\\frac{2}{3}}}=\\int \\frac{d t}{t^{7}\\left(1+\\frac{1}{t^{6}}\\right)^{\\frac{2}{3}}}\\)\n\nPut \\(1+\\frac{1}{t^{6}}=r^{3} \\Rightarrow \\frac{d t}{t^{7}}=\\frac{-1}{2} r^{2} d r\\)\n\n\\[\n-\\frac{1}{2} \\int \\frac{r^{2} d r}{r^{2}}=-\\frac{1}{2} r+c\n\\]\n\n\\(=-\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\frac{\\sin ^{6} x+1}{\\sin ^{6} x}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}+c=-\\frac{1}{2 \\sin ^{2} x}\\left(1+\\sin ^{6} x\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}+c\\)\n\n\\(f(x)=-\\frac{1}{2} \\operatorname{cosec}^{2} x\\) and \\(\\lambda=3\\)\n\n[from eqn. (i)]\n\n\\(\\therefore \\lambda f\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)=-2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{2 x^{3}-1}{x^{4}+x} d x\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e} \\frac{\\left|x^{3}+1\\right|}{x^{2}}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e} \\frac{\\left(x^{3}+1\\right)^{2}}{\\left|x^{3}\\right|}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\quad \\log _{e}\\left|\\frac{x^{3}+1}{x}\\right|+C\\)",
            "\\(\\log _{e} \\frac{\\left|x^{3}+1\\right|}{x^{2}}+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Given integral, \\(I=\\int \\frac{\\left(2 x^{3}-1\\right) d x}{x^{4}+x}=\\int \\frac{\\left(2 x-x^{-2}\\right) d x}{x^{2}+x^{-1}}\\)\n\n\nPut \\(x^{2}+x^{-1}=u \\Rightarrow\\left(2 x-x^{-2}\\right) d x=d u\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int \\frac{d u}{u}=\\log |u|+c=\\log \\left|x^{2}+x^{-1}\\right|+c\\)\n\n\\(=\\log \\left|\\frac{x^{3}+1}{x}\\right|+c\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Let \\(\\alpha \\in(0, \\pi / 2)\\) be fixed. If the integral \\(\\int \\frac{\\tan x+\\tan \\alpha}{\\tan x-\\tan \\alpha} d x=\\mathrm{A}(x) \\cos 2 \\alpha+\\mathrm{B}(x) \\sin 2 \\alpha+\\mathrm{C}\\), where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration, then the functions \\(\\mathrm{A}(x)\\) and \\(\\mathrm{B}(x)\\) are respectively :",
        "options": [
            "\\(x+\\alpha\\) and \\(\\log _{e}|\\sin (x+\\alpha)|\\)",
            "\\(x-\\alpha\\) and \\(\\log _{e} \\mid \\sin (x-\\alpha)\\)",
            "\\(x-\\alpha\\) and \\(\\log _{e}|\\cos (x-\\alpha)|\\)",
            "\\(x+\\alpha\\) and \\(\\log _{e}|\\sin (x-\\alpha)|\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) Given integral\n\n\n\\(\\int \\frac{\\tan x+\\tan \\alpha}{\\tan x-\\tan \\alpha} d x=\\int \\frac{\\sin (x+\\alpha)}{\\sin (x-\\alpha)} d x\\)\n\nLet \\(x-\\alpha=t \\Rightarrow d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\sin (t+2 \\alpha)}{\\sin t} d t=\\int[\\cos 2 \\alpha+\\sin 2 \\alpha \\cdot \\cot t] d t\\)\n\n\\(=\\cos 2 \\alpha \\cdot t+\\sin 2 \\alpha \\cdot \\log |\\sin t|+c\\)\n\n\\(=(x-\\alpha) \\cdot \\cos 2 \\alpha+\\sin 2 \\alpha \\cdot \\log |\\sin (x-\\alpha)|+c\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 1
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{d x}{\\left(x^{2}-2 x+10\\right)^{2}}\\) \\(=\\mathrm{A}\\left(\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x-1}{3}\\right)+\\frac{f(x)}{x^{2}-2 x+10}\\right)+\\mathrm{C}\\) where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration, then :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\quad A=\\frac{1}{54}\\) and \\(f(x)=3(x-1)\\)",
            "\\(\\quad A=\\frac{1}{81}\\) and \\(f(x)=3(x-1)\\)",
            "\\(\\quad A=\\frac{1}{27}\\) and \\(f(x)=9(x-1)\\)",
            "\\(A=\\frac{1}{54}\\) and \\(f(x)=9(x-1)^{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let \\(I=\\int \\frac{d x}{\\left(x^{2}-2 x+10\\right)^{2}}=\\int \\frac{d x}{\\left((x-1)^{2}+9\\right)^{2}}\\)\n\n\nLet \\((x-1)^{2}=9 \\tan ^{2} \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\tan \\theta=\\frac{x-1}{3}\\)\n\nAfter differentiating equation ...(i), we get\n\n\\(2(x-1) d x=18 \\tan \\theta \\sec ^{2} \\theta \\mathrm{d} \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I=\\int \\frac{18 \\tan \\theta \\sec ^{2} \\theta d \\theta}{2 \\times 3 \\tan \\theta \\times 81 \\sec ^{4} \\theta}\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{1}{27} \\int \\cos ^{2} \\theta d \\theta=\\frac{1}{27} \\times \\frac{1}{2} \\int(1+\\cos 2 \\theta) d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{1}{54}\\left\\{\\theta+\\frac{\\sin 2 \\theta}{2}\\right\\}+c\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{1}{54}\\left[\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x-1}{3}\\right)+\\frac{1}{2} \\times \\frac{2\\left(\\frac{x-1}{3}\\right)}{1+\\left(\\frac{x-1}{3}\\right)^{2}}\\right]+c\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{1}{54}\\left[\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x-1}{3}\\right)+\\frac{3(x-1)}{x^{2}-2 x+10}\\right]+c\\)\n\nCompare it with \\(\\mathrm{A}\\left[\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x-1}{b}\\right)+\\frac{f(x)}{x^{2}-2 x+10}\\right]+c\\),\n\nwe get: \\(\\mathrm{A}=\\frac{1}{54}\\) and \\(\\mathrm{f}(\\mathrm{x})=3(\\mathrm{x}-1)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "If \\(f(x)\\) is a non-zero polynomial of degree four, having local extreme points at \\(x=-1,0,1\\); then the set \\(S=\\{x \\in R: f(x)=f(0)\\}\\) contains exactly:",
        "options": [
            "four irrational numbers.",
            "four rational numbers.",
            "two irrational and two rational numbers.",
            "two irrational and one rational number."
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Since, function \\(f(x)\\) have local extreem points at \\(x=-1,0,1\\). Then\n\n\n\\(f(x)=K(x+1) x(x-1)\\)\n\n\\(=K\\left(x^{3}-x\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{f}(\\mathrm{x})=K\\left(\\frac{x^{4}}{4}-\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\right)+C\\) (using integration)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{f}(0)=\\mathrm{C}\\)\n\n\\(\\because \\mathrm{f}(\\mathrm{x})=\\mathrm{f}(0) \\Rightarrow K\\left(\\frac{x^{4}}{4}-\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\right)=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}}{2}-1\\right)=0 \\quad \\Rightarrow x=0,0, \\sqrt{2},-\\sqrt{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore S=\\{0,-\\sqrt{2}, \\sqrt{2}\\}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\sec ^{2 / 3} x \\operatorname{cosec}^{4 / 3} x d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(-3 \\tan ^{-1 / 3} \\mathrm{x}+\\mathrm{C}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{3}{4} \\tan ^{-4 / 3} x+C\\)",
            "\\(-3 \\cot ^{-1 / 3} x+C\\)",
            "\\(3 \\tan ^{-1 / 3} x+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(I=\\int \\sec ^{\\frac{2}{3}} x \\cdot \\operatorname{cosec}^{\\frac{4}{3}} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(I=\\int \\frac{\\sec ^{2} x d x}{4}\\)\n\n\\(\\tan ^{3} x\\)\n\nPut \\(\\tan \\mathrm{x}=\\mathrm{z}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\sec ^{2} \\mathrm{xdx}=\\mathrm{dz}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int z^{-\\frac{4}{3}} \\cdot d z=\\frac{z^{\\frac{-1}{3}}}{\\left(\\frac{-1}{3}\\right)}+C \\Rightarrow I=-3(\\tan x)^{\\frac{-1}{3}}+C\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "If \\(\\int e^{\\sec x}\\left(\\sec x \\tan x f(x)+\\left(\\sec x \\tan x+\\sec ^{2} x\\right)\\right) d x\\) \\(=e^{\\sec x} f(x)+\\mathrm{C}\\), then a possible choice of \\(f(x)\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\sec x+\\tan x+\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\sec x-\\tan x-\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\sec x+x \\tan x-\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "\\(x \\sec x+\\tan x+\\frac{1}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "(a) Given,\\ \\(\\int e^{\\sec x}\\left(\\sec x \\tan x f(x)+\\left(\\sec x+\\tan x+\\sec ^{2} x\\right)\\right) d x\\)\\ \\[=e^{\\sec x} f(x)+C\\] \\(\\because \\int e^{g(x)}\\left(\\left(g^{\\prime}(x) f(x)\\right)+f^{\\prime}(x)\\right) d x=e^{g(x)} \\times f(x)+C\\)\\ Our comparing above equation by equation (i),\\ \\(f(x)=\\int\\left((\\sec x \\tan x)+\\sec ^{2} x\\right) d x\\)\\ \\(\\therefore f(x)=\\sec x+\\tan x+C\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "\\(\\int \\frac{\\sin \\frac{5 x}{2}}{\\sin \\frac{x}{2}} d x\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(2 x+\\sin x+2 \\sin 2 x+c\\)",
            "\\(x+2 \\sin x+2 \\sin 2 x+c\\)",
            "\\(x+2 \\sin x+\\sin 2 x+c\\)",
            "\\(2 x+\\sin x+\\sin 2 x+c\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n\\item (c)\n\n\n\\[\n\\int \\frac{\\sin \\left(\\frac{5 x}{2}\\right)}{\\sin \\left(\\frac{x}{2}\\right)} d x=\\int \\frac{2 \\cos \\frac{x}{2} \\cdot \\sin \\frac{5 x}{2}}{2 \\cos \\frac{x}{2} \\cdot \\sin \\frac{x}{2}} d x\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\sin 3 x+\\sin 2 x}{\\sin x} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int\\left(3-4 \\sin ^{2} x+2 \\cos x\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\left[\\because \\sin 2 x=2 \\sin x \\cos x\\right.\\) and \\(\\left.\\sin 3 x=3 \\sin x-4 \\sin ^{3} x\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\int(3-2(1-\\cos 2 x)+2 \\cos x) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int(1+2 \\cos x+2 \\cos 2 x) d x\\)\n\n\\(=x+2 \\sin x+\\sin 2 x+c\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{d x}{x^{3}\\left(1+x^{6}\\right)^{2 / 3}}=x f(x)\\left(1+x^{6}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}+C\\), where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration, then the function \\(f(x)\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{3}{x^{2}}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{6 x^{3}}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{2 x^{2}}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{2 x^{3}}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Let, \\(\\int \\frac{d x}{x^{3}\\left(1+x^{6}\\right)^{\\frac{2}{3}}}=\\int \\frac{d x}{x^{7}\\left(1+x^{-6}\\right)^{\\frac{2}{3}}}\\)\n\n\nPut \\(1+x^{-6}=t^{3} \\Rightarrow-6^{-7} d x=3 t^{2} d t \\Rightarrow \\frac{d x}{x^{7}}=\\left(-\\frac{1}{2}\\right) t^{2} d t\\)\n\nNow, \\(I=\\int\\left(-\\frac{1}{2}\\right) \\frac{t^{2} d t}{t^{2}}=-\\frac{1}{2} t+C\\)\n\n\\(=-\\frac{1}{2}\\left(1+x^{-6}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}+C=-\\frac{1}{2} \\frac{\\left(1+x^{6}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}}{x^{2}}+C\\)\n\n\\(=-\\frac{1}{2 x^{3}} x\\left(1+x^{6}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}+C\\)\n\nHence, \\(f(x)=-\\frac{1}{2 x^{3}}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\cos \\left(\\log _{e} x\\right) d x\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{x}{2}\\left[\\sin \\left(\\log _{e} x\\right)-\\cos \\left(\\log _{e} x\\right)\\right]+C\\)",
            "\\(x\\left[\\cos \\left(\\log _{e} x\\right)+\\sin \\left(\\log _{e} x\\right)\\right]+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{x}{2}\\left[\\cos \\left(\\log _{e} x\\right)+\\sin \\left(\\log _{e} x\\right)\\right]+C\\)",
            "\\(x\\left[\\cos \\left(\\log _{e} x\\right)-\\sin \\left(\\log _{e} x\\right)\\right]+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Let the integral, \\(I=\\int \\cos (\\ln x) d x\\)\n\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\quad I=\\cos (\\ln x) \\cdot x-\\int \\frac{-\\sin (\\ln x)}{x} \\cdot x d x\\)\n\n\\(=x \\cos (\\ln x)+\\int \\sin (\\ln x) d x\\)\n\n\\(=x \\cos (\\ln x)+\\sin (\\ln x) \\cdot x-\\int \\frac{\\cos (\\ln x)}{x} \\cdot x d x\\)\n\n\\(=x \\cos (\\ln x)+\\sin (\\ln x) \\cdot x-I\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 I=x(\\cos (\\ln x)+\\sin (\\ln x))+C\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\frac{x}{2}[\\cos (\\ln x)+\\sin (\\ln x)]+C\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{3 x^{13}+2 x^{11}}{\\left(2 x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1\\right)^{4}} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{x^{4}}{6\\left(2 x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1\\right)^{3}}+\\mathrm{C}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{x^{12}}{6\\left(2 x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1\\right)^{3}}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{x^{4}}{\\left(2 x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1\\right)^{3}}+\\mathrm{C}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{x^{12}}{\\left(2 x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1\\right)^{3}}+\\mathrm{C}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(I=\\int \\frac{3 x^{13}+2 x^{11}}{\\left(2 x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1\\right)^{4}} d x=\\int \\frac{3 x^{13}+2 x^{11}}{x^{16}\\left(2+\\frac{3}{x^{2}}+\\frac{1}{x^{4}}\\right)^{4}} d x\\) \\(I=\\int \\frac{\\frac{3}{x^{3}}+\\frac{2}{x^{5}}}{\\left(2+\\frac{3}{x^{2}}+\\frac{1}{x^{4}}\\right)^{4}} d x\\)\n\n\nLet \\(2+\\frac{3}{x^{2}}+\\frac{1}{x^{4}}=\\mathrm{t},-2\\left(\\frac{3}{x^{3}}+\\frac{2}{x^{5}}\\right) d x=d t\\)\n\nThen, \\(I=\\int \\frac{-\\frac{d t}{2}}{t^{4}}=-\\frac{1}{2} \\frac{t^{-4+1}}{-4+1}+C\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{-1}{2} \\times \\frac{1}{(-3)} \\frac{1}{\\left(2+\\frac{3}{x^{2}}+\\frac{1}{x^{4}}\\right)^{3}}+C\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{1}{6} \\frac{x^{12}}{\\left(2 x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1\\right)^{3}}+C\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{\\sqrt{1-x^{2}}}{x^{4}} d x=A(\\mathrm{x})\\left(\\sqrt{1-x^{2}}\\right)^{m}+C\\), for a suitable chosen integer \\(\\mathrm{m}\\) and a function \\(\\mathrm{A}(\\mathrm{x})\\), where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration, then \\((\\mathrm{A}(\\mathrm{x}))^{\\mathrm{m}}\\) equals :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{-1}{27 x^{9}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{-1}{3 x^{3}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{27 x^{6}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{9 x^{4}}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(A(x)\\left(\\sqrt{1-x^{2}}\\right)^{m}+C=\\int \\frac{\\sqrt{1-x^{2}}}{x^{4}} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\sqrt{\\frac{1}{x^{2}}-1}}{x^{3}} d x\\)\n\nLet \\(\\frac{1}{x^{2}}-1=u^{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow-\\frac{2}{x^{3}}=\\frac{2 u d u}{d x}\\)\n\n\\(\\frac{d x}{x^{3}}=-u d u\\)\n\n\\(A(x)\\left(\\sqrt{1-x^{2}}\\right)^{m}+C=\\int\\left(-u^{2}\\right) d u=-\\frac{u^{3}}{3}+C\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =-\\frac{1}{3}\\left(\\frac{1}{x^{2}}-1\\right)^{\\frac{3}{2}}+C \\\\\n& =-\\frac{1}{3} \\cdot \\frac{1}{x^{3}} \\cdot\\left(1-x^{2}\\right)^{\\frac{3}{2}}+C \\\\\n& =\\frac{-1}{3 x^{3}}\\left(\\sqrt{1-x^{2}}\\right)^{3}+C\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nCompare both sides,\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow A(x)=-\\frac{1}{3 x^{3}}\\) and \\(m=3\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow(A(x))^{3}=\\frac{-1}{27 x^{9}}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{x+1}{\\sqrt{2 x-1}} \\mathrm{~d} x=f(x) \\sqrt{2 x-1}+\\mathrm{C}\\), where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration, then \\(f(x)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{3}(x+1)\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{2}{3}(x+2)\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{2}{3}(x-4)\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{3}(x+4)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Let \\(I=\\int \\frac{x+1}{\\sqrt{2 x-1}} d x\\)\n\n\nPut \\(\\sqrt{2 x-1}=t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore 2 x-1=t^{2} \\Rightarrow d x=t d t\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int \\frac{\\left(t^{2}+3\\right)}{2} d t=\\frac{t^{3}}{6}+\\frac{3 t}{2}+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{(2 x-1)^{\\frac{3}{2}}}{6}+\\frac{3}{2}(2 x-1)^{\\frac{1}{2}}+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\sqrt{2 x-1}\\left(\\frac{x+4}{3}\\right)+C\\)\n\n\\(=f(x) \\cdot \\sqrt{2 x-1}+C\\)\n\nHence, \\(f(x)=\\frac{x+4}{3}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 2
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "Let \\(\\mathrm{n} \\geq 2\\) be a natural number and \\(0<\\theta<\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\) Then \\(\\int \\frac{\\left(\\sin ^{\\mathrm{n}} \\theta+\\sin \\theta\\right)^{\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{n}}} \\cos \\theta}{\\sin ^{\\mathrm{n}+1} \\theta} \\mathrm{d} \\theta\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\mathrm{n}}{\\mathrm{n}^{2}-1}\\left(1-\\frac{1}{\\sin ^{n-1} \\theta}\\right)^{\\frac{\\mathrm{n}+1}{\\mathrm{n}}}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\mathrm{n}}{\\mathrm{n}^{2}+1}\\left(1-\\frac{1}{\\sin ^{\\mathrm{n}-1} \\theta}\\right)^{\\frac{\\mathrm{n}+1}{\\mathrm{n}}}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\mathrm{n}}{\\mathrm{n}^{2}-1}\\left(1+\\frac{1}{\\sin ^{\\mathrm{n}-1} \\theta}\\right)^{\\frac{\\mathrm{n}+1}{\\mathrm{n}}}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\mathrm{n}}{\\mathrm{n}^{2}-1}\\left(1-\\frac{1}{\\sin ^{\\mathrm{n}+1} \\theta}\\right)^{\\frac{\\mathrm{n}+1}{\\mathrm{n}}}+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "(a) Let, \\(I=\\int \\frac{\\left(\\sin ^{n} \\theta-\\sin \\theta\\right)^{\\frac{1}{n}} \\cos \\theta}{\\sin ^{n+1} \\theta} d \\theta\\)\\ \\ Let \\(\\sin \\theta=u\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow \\cos \\theta d \\theta=d u\\)\\ \\(\\therefore \\quad I=\\int \\frac{\\left(u^{n}-u\\right)^{\\frac{1}{n}}}{u^{n+1}} d u\\)\\ \\(=\\int \\frac{\\left(1-\\frac{1}{u^{n-1}}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{n}}}{u^{n}} d u=\\int u^{-n}\\left(1-u^{1-n}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{n}} d u\\)\\ \\ Let \\(1-u^{1-n}=v\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow-(1-n) u^{-n} d u=d v\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow u^{-n} d u=\\frac{d v}{n-1}\\)\\ \\(\\therefore \\quad I=\\int v^{\\frac{1}{n}} \\cdot \\frac{d v}{n-1}=\\frac{1}{n-1} \\cdot \\frac{v^{\\frac{1}{n}}}{\\frac{1}{n}+1}\\)\\ \\(=\\frac{n}{n^{2}-1} v^{\\frac{n+1}{n}}+C=\\frac{n}{n^{2}-1}\\left(1-\\frac{1}{u^{n-1}}\\right)^{\\frac{n+1}{n}}+C\\)\\ \\(=\\frac{n}{n^{2}-1}\\left(1-\\frac{1}{\\sin ^{n-1} \\theta}\\right)^{\\frac{n+1}{n}}+C\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "For \\(x^{2} \\neq \\mathrm{n} \\pi+1, \\mathrm{n} \\in \\mathrm{N}\\) (the set of natural numbers), the integral \\(\\int x \\sqrt{\\frac{2 \\sin \\left(x^{2}-1\\right)-\\sin 2\\left(x^{2}-1\\right)}{2 \\sin \\left(x^{2}-1\\right)+\\sin 2\\left(x^{2}-1\\right)}} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\log _{\\mathrm{e}}\\left|\\frac{1}{2} \\sec ^{2}\\left(x^{2}-1\\right)\\right|+\\mathrm{c}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{\\mathrm{e}}\\left|\\sec \\left(x^{2}-1\\right)\\right|+\\mathrm{c}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{\\mathrm{e}}\\left|\\sec ^{2}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}-1}{2}\\right)\\right|+\\mathrm{c}\\)",
            "\\(\\log _{\\mathrm{e}}\\left|\\sec \\left(\\frac{x^{2}-1}{2}\\right)\\right|+\\mathrm{c}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c, d ) Consider the given integral\n\n\n\\(I=\\int x \\sqrt{\\frac{2 \\sin \\left(x^{2}-1\\right)-2 \\sin \\left(x^{2}-1\\right) \\cos \\left(x^{2}-1\\right)}{2 \\sin \\left(x^{2}-1\\right)+2 \\sin \\left(x^{2}-1\\right) \\cos \\left(x^{2}-1\\right)}} d x\\)\n\n\\((\\therefore \\sin 2 \\theta=2 \\sin \\theta \\cos \\theta)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int x \\sqrt{\\frac{1-\\cos \\left(x^{2}-1\\right)}{1+\\cos \\left(x^{2}-1\\right)}} d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int x\\left|\\tan \\left(\\frac{x^{2}-1}{2}\\right)\\right| d x\\),\n\nNow let \\(\\frac{x^{2}-1}{2}=t \\Rightarrow \\frac{2 x}{2} d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad I=\\int|\\tan (t)| d t=\\ln |\\sec t|+C\\)\n\nor \\(\\quad I=\\ln \\left|\\sec \\left(\\frac{x^{2}-1}{2}\\right)\\right|+c=\\frac{1}{2} \\ln \\left|\\sec ^{2}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}-1}{2}\\right)\\right|+c\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c,d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "If \\(f(x)=\\int \\frac{5 x^{8}+7 x^{6}}{\\left(x^{2}+1+2 x^{7}\\right)^{2}} d x,(x \\geq 0)\\), and \\(f(0)=0\\), then the value of \\(f(1)\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{4}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(f(x)=\\int \\frac{5 x^{8}+7 x^{6}}{\\left(x^{2}+1+2 x^{7}\\right)^{2}} d x, x \\geq 0\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{5 x^{8}+7 x^{6}}{x^{14}\\left(x^{-5}+x^{-7}+2\\right)^{2}} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{5 x^{-6}+7 x^{-8}}{\\left(2+x^{-7}+x^{-5}\\right)^{2}} d x\\)\n\nLet \\(2+x^{-7}+x^{-5}=t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow\\left(-7 x^{-8}-5 x^{-6}\\right) d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(x)=\\int \\frac{-d t}{t^{2}}=\\int-t^{-2} d t=t^{-1}+c\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(x)=\\frac{1}{2+x^{-7}+x^{-5}}+c, f(0)=0 \\Rightarrow c=0\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore f(1)=\\frac{1}{4}\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x \\cos ^{2} x}{\\left(\\sin ^{5} x+\\cos ^{3} x \\sin ^{2} x+\\sin ^{3} x \\cos ^{2} x+\\cos ^{5} x\\right)^{2}} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{-1}{3\\left(1+\\tan ^{3} \\mathrm{x}\\right)}+\\mathrm{C}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{1+\\cot ^{3} \\mathrm{x}}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{-1}{1+\\cot ^{3} \\mathrm{x}}+\\mathrm{C}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{3\\left(1+\\tan ^{3} x\\right)}+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (a) Let I\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\int \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x \\cos ^{2} x}{\\left(\\sin ^{5} x+\\cos ^{3} x \\sin ^{2} x+\\sin ^{3} x \\cos ^{2} x+\\cos ^{5} x\\right)^{2}} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x \\cos ^{2} x}{\\left[\\left(\\sin ^{2} x+\\cos ^{2} x\\right)\\left(\\sin ^{3} x+\\cos ^{3} x\\right)\\right]^{2}} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x \\cos ^{2} x}{\\left(\\sin ^{3} x+\\cos ^{3} x\\right)^{2}} d x=\\int \\frac{\\tan ^{2} x \\cdot \\sec ^{2} x}{\\left(1+\\tan ^{3} x\\right)^{2}} d x \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 3 \\tan ^{2} x \\sec ^{2} x d x=d t \\\\\n& \\therefore \\quad I=\\frac{1}{3} \\int \\frac{d t}{t^{2}}=-\\frac{1}{3 t}+C=\\frac{-1}{3\\left(1+\\tan ^{3} x\\right)}+C\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{\\tan x}{1+\\tan x+\\tan ^{2} x} d x=x-\\frac{K}{\\sqrt{A}} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{K \\tan x+1}{\\sqrt{A}}\\right)+C\\), ( \\(C\\) is a constant of integration), then the ordered pair \\((K, A)\\) is euqal to",
        "options": [
            "\\((2,3)\\)",
            "\\((2,1)\\)",
            "\\((-2,1)\\)",
            "\\((-2,3)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let \\(I=\\int \\frac{\\tan x}{1+\\tan x+\\tan ^{2} x} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int \\frac{\\tan x+1+\\tan ^{2} x}{\\tan x+1+\\tan ^{2} x} d x-\\int \\frac{\\left(1+\\tan ^{2} x\\right)}{1+\\tan x+\\tan ^{2} x}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=x-\\int \\frac{\\sec ^{2} x d x}{1+\\tan x+\\tan ^{2} x}\\)\n\nPut \\(\\tan x=t \\Rightarrow \\sec ^{2} x . d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I=x-\\int \\frac{d t}{t^{2}+t+\\frac{1}{4}+1-\\frac{1}{4}}\\)\n\n\\(=x-\\int \\frac{d t}{\\left(t+\\frac{1}{2}\\right)^{2}+\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\right)^{2}}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=x-\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{3}} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{t+\\frac{1}{2}}{\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}}\\right)+C\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=x-\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{3}} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{2 \\tan x+1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)+C\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore A=3\\) and \\(K=2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "If \\(f\\left(\\frac{x-4}{x+2}\\right)=2 x+1,(x \\in R=\\{1,-2\\})\\), then \\(\\int f(x) d x\\) is equal to (where \\(C\\) is a constant of integration)",
        "options": [
            "\\(12 \\log _{e}|1-x|-3 x+c\\)",
            "\\(-12 \\log _{e}|1-x|-3 x+c\\)",
            "\\(-12 \\log _{e}|1-x|+3 x+c\\)",
            "\\(12 \\log _{e}|1-x|+3 x+c\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) Suppose, \\(\\frac{x-4}{x+2}=y \\Rightarrow x-4=y(x+2)\\)\n\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow x(1-y)=2 y+4 \\Rightarrow x=\\frac{2 y+4}{1-y}\\)\n\nSo, \\(f(y)=2\\left(\\frac{2 y+4}{1-y}\\right)+1\\)\n\nNow, \\(f(x)=2\\left(\\frac{2 x+4}{1-x}\\right)+1=\\frac{3 x+9}{1-x}\\)\\\\\n\\(=\\frac{3(x+3)}{1-x}=\\frac{3(\\mathrm{x}-1+4)}{1-x}=-3+\\frac{12}{1-x}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\int f(x) d x=-12 \\log _{e}|1-x|-3 x+c\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "\\(\\int \\frac{2 x+5}{\\sqrt{7-6 x-x^{2}}} d x=A \\sqrt{7-6 x-x^{2}}+B \\sin ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x+3}{4}\\right)+C\\) (where \\(C\\) is a constant of integration), then the ordered pair \\((A, B)\\) is equal to",
        "options": [
            "\\((-2,-1)\\)",
            "\\((2,-1)\\)",
            "\\((-2,1)\\)",
            "\\((2,1)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(\\because 7-6 x-x^{2}=16-(x+3)^{2}\\)\n\n\nand \\(\\frac{d}{d x}\\left(7-6 x-x^{2}\\right)=-2 x-6\\)\n\nSo, \\(\\int \\frac{2 x+5}{\\sqrt{7-6 x-x^{2}}} d x=\\int \\frac{2 x+6}{\\sqrt{7-6 x-x^{2}}} d x\\)\n\n\\(-\\int \\frac{1}{\\sqrt{16-(x+3)^{2}}} d x\\)\n\n\\(=-2 \\sqrt{7-6 x-x^{2}}-\\sin ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x+3}{4}\\right)+C\\)\n\nTherefore, \\(A=-2, \\& B=-1\\).",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "If \\(f\\left(\\frac{3 x-4}{3 x+4}\\right)=x+2, x \\neq-\\frac{4}{3}\\), and \\(\\int f(x) d x=\\mathrm{A} \\log |1-x|+\\mathrm{B} x+\\mathrm{C}\\), then the ordered pair \\((\\mathrm{A}, \\mathrm{B})\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\left(\\frac{8}{3}, \\frac{2}{3}\\right)\\)",
            "\\(\\left(-\\frac{8}{3}, \\frac{2}{3}\\right)\\)",
            "\\(\\left(-\\frac{8}{3},-\\frac{2}{3}\\right)\\)",
            "\\(\\left(\\frac{8}{3},-\\frac{2}{3}\\right)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(f\\left(\\frac{3 x-4}{3 x+4}\\right)=x+2, x \\neq-\\frac{4}{3}\\)\n\n\nConsider \\(\\frac{3 \\mathrm{x}-4}{3 \\mathrm{x}+4}=\\mathrm{t}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 3 \\mathrm{x}-4=3 \\mathrm{tx}+4 \\mathrm{t}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{x}=\\frac{4 \\mathrm{t}+4}{3-3 \\mathrm{t}}+2\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{f}(\\mathrm{t})=\\frac{10-2 \\mathrm{t}}{3-3 \\mathrm{t}}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{f}(\\mathrm{x})=\\frac{2 \\mathrm{x}-10}{3 \\mathrm{x}-3}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad \\int f(x) d x=\\int \\frac{2 x-10}{3 x-3} d x\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\int \\frac{2 x}{3 x-3} d x-10 \\int \\frac{d x}{3 x-3} \\\\\n& =\\frac{2}{3} \\int \\frac{\\mathrm{x}-1}{\\mathrm{x}-1} \\mathrm{dx}+\\frac{2}{3} \\int \\frac{\\mathrm{dx}}{\\mathrm{x}-1}-\\frac{10}{3} \\int \\frac{\\mathrm{dx}}{\\mathrm{x}-1} \\\\\n& =\\frac{2 \\mathrm{x}}{3}-\\frac{8}{3} \\ln (\\mathrm{x}-1)+\\mathrm{C}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nHere, \\(\\mathrm{A}=-\\frac{8}{3}, \\mathrm{~B}=\\frac{2}{3}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad(\\mathrm{A}, \\mathrm{B})=\\left(-\\frac{8}{3}, \\frac{2}{3}\\right)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\sqrt{1+2 \\cot x(\\operatorname{cosec} x+\\cot x)} d x\\) \\(\\left(0<\\mathrm{x}<\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\right)\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(2 \\log \\left|\\sin \\frac{x}{2}\\right|+C\\)",
            "\\(4 \\log \\left|\\sin \\frac{x}{2}\\right|+C\\)",
            "\\(2 \\log \\left|\\cos \\frac{\\mathrm{x}}{2}\\right|+\\mathrm{C}\\)",
            "\\(4 \\log \\left|\\cos \\frac{x}{2}\\right|+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let, \\(I=\\int \\sqrt{1+2 \\cot x \\operatorname{cosec} x+2 \\cot ^{2} x} \\cdot d x\\)\n\n\n\\[\n\\Rightarrow I=\\int \\sqrt{\\frac{\\sin ^{2} x+2 \\cos x+2 \\cos ^{2} x}{\\sin ^{2} x}} \\cdot d x\n\\]\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int \\sqrt{\\frac{1+2 \\cos x+\\cos ^{2} x}{\\sin x}} \\cdot d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int\\left|\\frac{1+\\cos x}{\\sin x}\\right| \\cdot d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int|\\operatorname{cosec} \\mathrm{x}+\\cot \\mathrm{x}| \\cdot \\mathrm{dx}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I}=\\log |\\operatorname{cosec} \\mathrm{x}-\\cot \\mathrm{x}|+\\log |\\sin \\mathrm{x}|+\\mathrm{C}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\log |1-\\cos x|+C\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\log \\left|2 \\sin ^{2} \\frac{x}{2}\\right|+C\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\log \\left|\\sin ^{2} \\frac{x}{2}\\right|+\\log 2+C\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=2 \\log \\left|\\sin \\frac{x}{2}\\right|+C_{1}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{d x}{\\cos ^{3} \\mathrm{x} \\sqrt{2 \\sin 2 \\mathrm{x}}}=(\\tan \\mathrm{x})^{\\mathrm{A}}+\\mathrm{C}(\\tan \\mathrm{x})^{\\mathrm{B}}+\\mathrm{k}\\), where \\(\\mathrm{k}\\) is a constant of integration, then \\(\\mathrm{A}+\\mathrm{B}+\\mathrm{C}\\) equals :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{16}{5}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{27}{10}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{7}{10}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{21}{5}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(\\int \\frac{d x}{\\cos ^{3} x \\sqrt{4 \\sin x \\cos x}}=\\int \\frac{d x}{2 \\cos ^{4} x \\sqrt{\\tan x}}\\)\n\n\nLet \\(\\tan x=t^{2} \\Rightarrow \\sec ^{2} x=1+t^{4}\\)\n\n\\(\\sec ^{2} x d x=2 t d t\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\sec ^{4} x d x}{2 \\sqrt{\\tan x}}=\\int \\frac{\\sec ^{2} x\\left(\\sec ^{2} x d x\\right)}{2 \\sqrt{\\tan x}}\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\left(1+t^{4}\\right) 2 t d t}{2 t}=\\int\\left(1+t^{4}\\right) d t=t+\\frac{t^{5}}{5}+k\\)\n\n\\(=\\sqrt{\\tan x}+\\frac{1}{5} \\tan ^{5 / 2} x+k[t=\\sqrt{\\tan x}]\\)\n\n\\(A=\\frac{1}{2}, B=\\frac{5}{2}, C=\\frac{1}{5}\\)\n\n\\(A+B+C=\\frac{16}{5}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 3
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{\\log \\left(t+\\sqrt{1+t^{2}}\\right)}{\\sqrt{1+t^{2}}} d t=\\frac{1}{2}(g(t))^{2}+C\\), where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant, then \\(g(b)\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{5}} \\log (2+\\sqrt{5})\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\log (2+\\sqrt{5})\\)",
            "\\(2 \\log (2+\\sqrt{5})\\)",
            "\\(\\log (2+\\sqrt{5})\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int\\left(1+x-\\frac{1}{x}\\right) e^{x+\\frac{1}{x}} d x\\) is equal to",
        "options": [
            "\\((x+1) e^{x+\\frac{1}{x}}+c\\)",
            "\\(-x e^{x+\\frac{1}{x}}+c\\)",
            "\\((x-1) e^{x+\\frac{1}{x}}+c\\)",
            "\\(x e^{x+\\frac{1}{x}}+c\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "No solution provided",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x \\cos ^{2} x}{\\left(\\sin ^{3} x+\\cos ^{3} x\\right)^{2}} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{\\left(1+\\cot ^{3} x\\right)}+c\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{3\\left(1+\\tan ^{3} x\\right)}+c\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\sin ^{3} x}{\\left(1+\\cos ^{3} x\\right)}+c\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{\\cos ^{3} x}{3\\left(1+\\sin ^{3} x\\right)}+c\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "No solution provided",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int x \\cos ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1-x^{2}}{1+x^{2}}\\right) d x(x>0)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(-x+\\left(1+x^{2}\\right) \\tan ^{-1} x+c\\)",
            "\\(x-\\left(1+x^{2}\\right) \\cot ^{-1} x+c\\)",
            "\\(-x+\\left(1+x^{2}\\right) \\cot ^{-1} x+c\\)",
            "\\(x-\\left(1+x^{2}\\right) \\tan ^{-1} x+c\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "No solution provided",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "\\(\\int \\frac{\\sin ^{8} x-\\cos ^{8} x}{\\left(1-2 \\sin ^{2} x \\cos ^{2} x\\right)} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\sin 2 x+c\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{2} \\sin 2 x+c\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{2} \\sin \\mathrm{x}+\\mathrm{c}\\)",
            "\\(-\\sin ^{2} x+c\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "No solution provided",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "If \\(\\int f(x) d x=\\psi(x)\\), then \\(\\int x^{5} f\\left(x^{3}\\right) d x\\) is equal to",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\left[x^{3} \\psi\\left(x^{3}\\right)-\\int x^{2} \\psi\\left(x^{3}\\right) d x\\right]+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{3} x^{3} \\psi\\left(x^{3}\\right)-3 \\int x^{3} \\psi\\left(x^{3}\\right) d x+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{3} x^{3} \\psi\\left(x^{3}\\right)-\\int x^{2} \\psi\\left(x^{3}\\right) d x+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\left[x^{3} \\psi\\left(x^{3}\\right)-\\int x^{3} \\psi\\left(x^{3}\\right) d x\\right]+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "No solution provided",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "If the integral \\(\\int \\frac{\\cos 8 x+1}{\\cot 2 x-\\tan 2 x} d x=A \\cos 8 x+k\\), where \\(k\\) is an arbitrary constant, then \\(\\mathrm{A}\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{16}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{16}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{8}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{8}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int \\frac{\\cos 8 x+1}{\\cot 2 x-\\tan 2 x} d x\\)\n\n\nNow, \\(\\mathrm{D}^{r}=\\cot 2 x-\\tan 2 x=\\frac{\\cos 2 x}{\\sin 2 x}-\\frac{\\sin 2 x}{\\cos 2 x}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\cos ^{2} 2 x-\\sin ^{2} 2 x}{\\sin 2 x \\cos 2 x}=\\frac{2 \\cos 4 x}{\\sin 4 x}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\mathrm{I}=\\int \\frac{2 \\cos ^{2} 4 x}{\\frac{2 \\cos 4 x}{\\sin 4 x}} d x=\\int \\frac{2 \\cos ^{2} 4 x \\cdot \\sin 4 x}{2 \\cos 4 x} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2} \\int \\sin 8 x d x=-\\frac{1}{2} \\frac{\\cos 8 x}{8}+k=-\\frac{1}{16} \\cdot \\cos 8 x+k\\)\n\nNow, \\(-\\frac{1}{16} \\cdot \\cos 8 x+k=\\mathrm{A} \\cos 8 x+k\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{A}=-\\frac{1}{16}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "If the \\(\\int \\frac{5 \\tan \\mathrm{x}}{\\tan \\mathrm{x}-2} \\mathrm{dx}=\\mathrm{x}+\\mathrm{a} \\ln |\\sin \\mathrm{x}-2 \\cos \\mathrm{x}|+\\mathrm{k}\\), then \\(a\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "-1",
            "-2",
            "1",
            "2"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (d) \\(\\int \\frac{5 \\tan x}{\\tan x-2} d x=\\int \\frac{5 \\frac{\\sin x}{\\cos x}}{\\frac{\\sin x}{\\cos x}-2} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int\\left(\\frac{5 \\sin x}{\\cos x} \\times \\frac{\\cos x}{\\sin x-2 \\cos x}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{5 \\sin x d x}{\\sin x-2 \\cos x}\\)\n\n\\(=\\int\\left(\\frac{4 \\sin x+\\sin x+2 \\cos x-2 \\cos x}{\\sin x-2 \\cos x}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{(\\sin x-2 \\cos x)+(4 \\sin x+2 \\cos x)}{\\sin x-2 \\cos x} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{(\\sin x-2 \\cos x)+2(\\cos x+2 \\sin x)}{(\\sin x-2 \\cos x)} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\sin x-2 \\cos x}{\\sin x-2 \\cos x} d x+2 \\int\\left(\\frac{\\cos x+2 \\sin x}{\\sin x-2 \\cos x}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int d x+2 \\int \\frac{\\cos x+2 \\sin x}{\\sin x-2 \\cos x} d x=I_{1}+I_{2}\\)\n\nwhere, \\(I_{1}=\\int d x\\) and \\(I_{2}=2 \\int \\frac{\\cos x+2 \\sin x}{\\sin x-2 \\cos x} d x\\)\n\nLet \\(\\sin x-2 \\cos x=t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow(\\cos x+2 \\sin x) d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I_{2}=2 \\int \\frac{d t}{t}=2 \\ln t+C=2 \\ln (\\sin x-2 \\cos x)+C\\)\n\nHence, \\(I_{1}+I_{2}=\\int d x+2 \\ln (\\sin x-2 \\cos x)+c\\)\n\n\\(=x+2 \\ln |(\\sin x-2 \\cos x)|+k \\Rightarrow a=2\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "If \\(f(x)=\\int\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+\\sin ^{2} x}{1+x^{2}}\\right) \\sec ^{2} x d x\\) and \\(f(0)=0\\), then \\(f(1)\\) equals",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\tan 1-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\tan 1+1\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)",
            "\\(1-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (a) Let \\(f(x)=\\int\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+\\sin ^{2} x}{1+x^{2}}\\right) \\sec ^{2} x d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{x^{2} \\sec ^{2} x+\\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{\\cos ^{2} x}}{1+x^{2}} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{x^{2} \\sec ^{2} x+\\tan ^{2} x}{1+x^{2}} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{x^{2}\\left(1+\\tan ^{2} x\\right)+\\tan ^{2} x}{1+x^{2}} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{x^{2}+\\tan ^{2} x\\left(1+x^{2}\\right)}{1+x^{2}} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{x^{2}}{1+x^{2}} d x+\\int \\tan ^{2} x d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{x^{2}+1-1}{1+x^{2}} d x+\\int\\left(\\sec ^{2} x-1\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int 1 d x-\\int \\frac{d x}{1+x^{2}}+\\int \\sec ^{2} x d x-\\int d x\\)\n\n\\(=-\\tan ^{-1} x+\\tan x+\\mathrm{c}\\)\n\nGiven : \\(f(0)=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(0)=-\\tan ^{-1} 0+\\tan 0+c \\Rightarrow c=0\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore f(x)=-\\tan ^{-1} x+\\tan x\\)\n\nNow, \\(f(1)=-\\tan ^{-1}(1)+\\tan 1=\\tan 1-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "The integral of \\(\\frac{x^{2}-x}{x^{3}-x^{2}+x-1}\\) w.r.t. \\(x\\) is",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\log \\left(x^{2}+1\\right)+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\log \\left|x^{2}-1\\right|+C\\)",
            "\\(\\log \\left(x^{2}+1\\right)+C\\)",
            "\\(\\log \\left|x^{2}-1\\right|+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let \\(I=\\int \\frac{x^{2}-x}{x^{3}-x^{2}+x-1} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{x(x-1)}{x^{2}(x-1)+(x-1)} d x=\\int \\frac{x d x}{x^{2}+1}=\\frac{1}{2} \\int \\frac{2 x d x}{\\left(x^{2}+1\\right)}\\)\n\nLet \\(x^{2}+1=t \\Rightarrow 2 x d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I=\\frac{1}{2} \\int \\frac{d t}{t}=\\frac{1}{2} \\log t+c\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2} \\log \\left(x^{2}+1\\right)+c\\)\n\nwhere ' \\(c\\) ' is the constant of integration.",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 4
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "Let \\(f(x)\\) be an indefinite integral of \\(\\cos ^{3} x\\). Statement 1: \\(f(x)\\) is a periodic function of period \\(\\pi\\). Statement 2: \\(\\cos ^{3} x\\) is a periodic function.",
        "options": [
            "Statement 1 is true, Statement 2 is false",
            "Both the Statements are true, but Statement 2 is not the correct explanation of Statement 1.",
            "Both the Statements are true, and Statement 2 is correct explanation of Statement 1.",
            "Statement 1 is false, Statement 2 is true."
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Statement \\(-2: \\cos ^{3} x\\) is a periodic function.\n\n\nIt is a true statement.\n\nStatement - 1\n\nGiven \\(f(x)=\\int \\cos ^{3} x d x=\\int\\left(\\frac{\\cos 3 x}{4}+\\frac{3 \\cos x}{4}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{4} \\frac{\\sin 3 x}{3}+\\frac{3}{4} \\sin x=\\frac{1}{12} \\sin 3 x+\\frac{3}{4} \\sin x\\)\n\nNow, period of \\(\\frac{1}{12} \\sin 3 x=\\frac{2 \\pi}{3}\\)\n\nPeriod of \\(\\frac{3}{4} \\sin x=2 \\pi\\)\n\nHence period of \\(f(x)=\\frac{\\text { L.C.M. }(2 \\pi, 2 \\pi)}{\\text { HCF of }(1,3)}=\\frac{2 \\pi}{1}=2 \\pi\\)\n\nThus, \\(f(x)\\) is a periodic function of period \\(2 \\pi\\).\n\nHence, Statement - 1 is false.",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\sqrt{2} \\int \\frac{\\sin x d x}{\\sin \\left(x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)}\\) is",
        "options": [
            "\\(x+\\log \\left|\\cos \\left(x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)\\right|+c\\)",
            "\\(x-\\log \\left|\\sin \\left(x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)\\right|+c\\)",
            "\\(x+\\log \\left|\\sin \\left(x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)\\right|+c\\)",
            "\\(x-\\log \\left|\\cos \\left(x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)\\right|+c\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Let \\(I=\\sqrt{2} \\int \\frac{\\sin x d x}{\\sin \\left(x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)}\\)\n\n\nLet \\(x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}=t \\Rightarrow d x=d t\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad I=\\sqrt{2} \\int \\frac{\\sin \\left(t+\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)}{\\sin t} d t=\\frac{\\sqrt{2}}{\\sqrt{2}} \\int\\left(\\frac{\\sin t+\\cos t}{\\sin t}\\right) d t \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad I=\\int(1+\\cot t) d t=t+\\log |\\sin t|+c_{1} \\\\\n& =x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}+\\log \\left|\\sin \\left(x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)\\right|+c_{1} \\\\\n& =x+\\log \\left|\\sin \\left(x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)\\right|+c\\left(\\text { where } c=c_{1}-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "\\(\\int \\frac{d x}{\\cos x+\\sqrt{3} \\sin x}\\) equals",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\log \\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{12}\\right)+C\\)",
            "\\(\\log \\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}-\\frac{\\pi}{12}\\right)+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\log \\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{12}\\right)+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\log \\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}-\\frac{\\pi}{12}\\right)+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\int \\frac{d x}{\\cos x+\\sqrt{3} \\sin x}\\)\n\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int \\frac{d x}{2\\left[\\frac{1}{2} \\cos x+\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2} \\sin x\\right]}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2} \\int \\frac{d x}{\\left[\\sin \\frac{\\pi}{6} \\cos x+\\cos \\frac{\\pi}{6} \\sin x\\right]}=\\frac{1}{2} \\cdot \\int \\frac{d x}{\\sin \\left(x+\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\frac{1}{2} \\cdot \\int \\operatorname{cosec}\\left(x+\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right) d x\\)\n\nWe know that\n\n\\(\\int \\operatorname{cosec} x d x=\\log |(\\tan x / 2)|+C\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad I=\\frac{1}{2} \\cdot \\log \\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{12}\\right)+C\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "\\(\\int \\frac{d x}{\\cos x-\\sin x}\\) is equal to",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\log \\left|\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{3 \\pi}{8}\\right)\\right|+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\log \\left|\\cot \\left(\\frac{x}{2}\\right)\\right|+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\log \\left|\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}-\\frac{3 \\pi}{8}\\right)\\right|+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\log \\left|\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}-\\frac{\\pi}{8}\\right)\\right|+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a)\n\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { (a) } \\int \\frac{d x}{\\cos x-\\sin x}=\\int \\frac{d x}{\\sqrt{2}\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\cos x-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\sin x\\right)} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{d x}{\\sqrt{2} \\cos \\left(x+\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)}=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\int \\sec \\left(x+\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right) d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\log \\left|\\tan \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}+\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{8}\\right)\\right|+C\\)\n\n\\[\n\\left[\\because \\int \\sec x d x=\\log \\left|\\tan \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}+\\frac{x}{2}\\right)\\right|\\right]\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\log \\left|\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{3 \\pi}{8}\\right)\\right|+C\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{\\sin x}{\\sin (x-\\alpha)} d x=A x+B \\log \\sin (x-\\alpha),+C\\), then value of \\((A, B)\\) is",
        "options": [
            "\\((-\\cos \\alpha, \\sin \\alpha)\\)",
            "\\((\\cos \\alpha, \\sin \\alpha)\\)",
            "\\((-\\sin \\alpha, \\cos \\alpha)\\)",
            "\\((\\sin \\alpha, \\cos \\alpha)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(\\int \\frac{\\sin x}{\\sin (x-\\alpha)} d x=\\int \\frac{\\sin (x-\\alpha+\\alpha)}{\\sin (x-\\alpha)} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\sin (x-\\alpha) \\cos \\alpha+\\cos (x-\\alpha) \\sin \\alpha}{\\sin (x-\\alpha)} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int\\{\\cos \\alpha+\\sin \\alpha \\cot (x-\\alpha)\\} d x\\)\n\n\\(=(\\cos \\alpha) x+(\\sin \\alpha) \\log \\sin (x-\\alpha)+C\\)\n\nComparing with \\(A x+B \\log \\sin (x-\\alpha)+\\mathrm{c}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore A=\\cos \\alpha, B=\\sin \\alpha\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "question": "\\(f(x)\\) and \\(g(x)\\) are two differentiable functions on \\([0,2]\\) such that \\(f^{\\prime \\prime}(x)-g^{\\prime \\prime}(x)=0, f^{\\prime}(1)=2 g^{\\prime}(1)=4 f(2)=3 g(2)=9\\) then \\(f(x)-g(x)\\) at \\(x=3 / 2\\) is",
        "options": [
            "0",
            "2",
            "10",
            "5"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\because f^{\\prime \\prime}(x)-g^{\\prime \\prime}(x)=0\\)\n\n\nIntegrating, \\(f^{\\prime}(x)-g^{\\prime}(x)=c\\);\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f^{\\prime}(1)-g^{\\prime}(1)=c \\Rightarrow 4-2=c \\Rightarrow c=2\\).\n\n\\(\\therefore f^{\\prime}(\\mathrm{x})-g^{\\prime}(\\mathrm{x})=2\\);\n\nIntegrating, \\(f(x)-g(x)=2 x+c_{1}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(2)-g(2)=4+c_{1} \\Rightarrow 9-3=4+c_{1}\\);\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow c_{1}=2 \\quad \\therefore f(x)-g(x)=2 x+2\\)\n\nAt \\(x=3 / 2, f(x)-g(x)=3+2=5\\).",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{1}^{2} e^{x} \\cdot x^{x}\\left(2+\\log _{e} x\\right) d x\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "\\(e(4 e+1)\\)",
            "\\(4 e^{2}-1\\)",
            "\\(e(4 e-1)\\)",
            "\\(e(2 e-1)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\int_{1}^{2} e^{x} x^{x}\\left(2+\\log _{e} x\\right) d x\\)\n\n\n\\(I=\\int_{1}^{2} e^{x} x^{x}\\left[1+\\left(1+\\log _{e} x\\right)\\right] d x\\) \\(=\\int_{1}^{2} e^{x}\\left[x^{x}+x^{x}\\left(1+\\log _{e} x\\right)\\right] d x\\)\n\n\\(\\because \\int e^{x}\\left(f(x)+f^{\\prime}(x)\\right) d x=e^{x} f(x)+c\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I=\\left[e^{x} x^{x}\\right]_{1}^{2}\\)\n\n\\(=e^{2} \\times 4-e \\times 1=4 e^{2}-e=e(4 e-1)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "question": "A value of \\(\\alpha\\) such that \\(\\int_{\\alpha}^{\\alpha+1} \\frac{d x}{(x+\\alpha)(x+\\alpha+1)}=\\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{9}{8}\\right)\\) is :",
        "options": [
            "-2",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "2"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(\\int_{\\alpha}^{\\alpha+1} \\frac{d x}{(x+\\alpha)(x+\\alpha+1)}\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{\\alpha}^{\\alpha+1}\\left[\\frac{1}{x+\\alpha}-\\frac{1}{x+\\alpha+1}\\right] d x\\) [Using partial fraction]\n\n\\(=\\left.\\log \\left(\\frac{(x+\\alpha)}{(x+\\alpha+1)}\\right)\\right|_{\\alpha} ^{\\alpha+1}=\\log \\left(\\frac{2 \\alpha+1}{2 \\alpha+2} \\cdot \\frac{2 \\alpha+1}{2 \\alpha}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=\\log \\frac{9}{8}\\) (Given)\n\nSo, \\(\\frac{(2 \\alpha+1)^{2}}{\\alpha(\\alpha+1)}=\\frac{9}{2} \\Rightarrow \\quad 8 \\alpha^{2}+8 \\alpha+2=9 \\alpha^{2}+9 \\alpha\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\alpha^{2}+\\alpha-2=0 \\Rightarrow \\alpha=1,-2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "question": "If \\(\\int x^{5} e^{-x^{2}} d x=g(x) e^{-x^{2}}+c\\), where \\(c\\) is a constant of integration, then \\(g(-1)\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "-1",
            "1",
            "\\(-\\frac{5}{2}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "(c) Let, \\(I=\\int x^{2} \\cdot e^{-x^{2}} d x\\)\\ Put \\(-x^{2}=t \\Rightarrow-2 x d x=d t\\)\\ \\(I=\\int \\frac{t^{2} \\cdot e^{t} d t}{(-2)}=\\frac{-1}{2} e^{t}\\left(t^{2}-2 t+2\\right) + C\\)\\ \\(\\therefore g(x)=\\frac{-1}{2}\\left(x^{4}+2 x^{2}+2\\right) \\Rightarrow g(-1)=\\frac{-5}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "question": "If \\(\\int x^{5} \\mathrm{e}^{-4 x^{3}} d x=\\frac{1}{48} \\mathrm{e}^{-4 x^{3}} f(x)+\\mathrm{C}\\), where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration, then \\(f(x)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(-2 x^{3}-1\\)",
            "\\(-4 x^{3}-1\\)",
            "\\(-2 x^{3}+1\\)",
            "\\(4 x^{3}+1\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "(b) \\(I=\\int x^{5} e^{-4 x^{3}} d x\\)\\ Put \\(-4 x^{3}=\\theta\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow-12 x^{2} d x=d \\theta\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow x^{2} d x=-\\frac{d \\theta}{12}\\)\\ \\(I=\\int \\frac{1}{48} \\theta e^{\\theta} d \\theta=\\frac{1}{48}\\left[\\theta e^{\\theta}-e^{\\theta}\\right]+C\\)\\ \\(I=\\frac{1}{48} e^{-4 x^{3}}\\left(-4 x^{3}-1\\right)+C\\)\\ Then, by comparison\\ \\(f(x)=-4 x^{3}-1\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 5
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{d x}{(1+\\sqrt{\\mathrm{x}}) \\sqrt{\\mathrm{x}-\\mathrm{x}^{2}}}\\) is equal to : (where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration)",
        "options": [
            "\\(-2 \\sqrt{\\frac{1+\\sqrt{\\mathrm{x}}}{1-\\sqrt{\\mathrm{x}}}}+\\mathrm{C}\\)",
            "\\(-\\sqrt{\\frac{1-\\sqrt{\\mathrm{x}}}{1+\\sqrt{\\mathrm{x}}}}+\\mathrm{C}\\)",
            "\\(-2 \\sqrt{\\frac{1-\\sqrt{\\mathrm{x}}}{1+\\sqrt{\\mathrm{x}}}}+\\mathrm{C}\\)",
            "\\(2 \\sqrt{\\frac{1+\\sqrt{\\mathrm{x}}}{1-\\sqrt{\\mathrm{x}}}}+\\mathrm{C}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\int \\frac{d x}{(1+\\sqrt{x}) \\cdot \\sqrt{x} \\sqrt{1-x}}\\)\n\n\nPut \\(1+\\sqrt{x}=t \\Rightarrow \\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{x}} d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\quad 1=\\int \\frac{2 d t}{t \\sqrt{2 t-t^{2}}}\\)\n\nAgain put \\(t=\\frac{1}{z} \\Rightarrow d t=\\frac{-1}{2^{2}} d z\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=2 \\int \\frac{\\frac{-1}{z^{2}} d z}{\\frac{1}{z} \\sqrt{\\frac{2}{z}-\\frac{1}{z^{2}}}}=2 \\int \\frac{-d z}{\\sqrt{2 z-1}}\\)\n\n\\(=-2 \\sqrt{2 z-1}+c=-2 \\sqrt{\\frac{2}{t}-1}+c\\)\n\n\\(=-2 \\sqrt{\\frac{2-t}{t}}+c=-2 \\sqrt{\\frac{1-\\sqrt{x}}{1+\\sqrt{x}}}+c\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 6
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{\\mathrm{dx}}{\\mathrm{x}^{2}\\left(\\mathrm{x}^{4}+1\\right)^{3 / 4}}\\) equals :",
        "options": [
            "\\(-\\left(x^{4}+1\\right)^{\\frac{1}{4}}+c\\)",
            "\\(-\\left(\\frac{x^{4}+1}{x^{4}}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{4}}+c\\)",
            "\\(\\left(\\frac{x^{4}+1}{x^{4}}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{4}}+c\\)",
            "\\(\\left(\\mathrm{x}^{4}+1\\right)^{\\frac{1}{4}}+\\mathrm{c}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int \\frac{\\mathrm{dx}}{\\mathrm{x}^{2}\\left(\\mathrm{x}^{4}+1\\right)^{3 / 4}}=\\int \\frac{\\mathrm{dx}}{\\mathrm{x}^{3}\\left(1+\\mathrm{x}^{-4}\\right)^{3 / 4}}\\)\n\n\nLet \\(\\mathrm{x}^{-4}=\\mathrm{y}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow-4 \\mathrm{x}^{-3} \\mathrm{dx}=\\mathrm{dy} \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{dx}=\\frac{-1}{4} \\mathrm{x}^{3} \\mathrm{dy}\\) \\(\\therefore \\quad I=\\frac{-1}{4} \\int \\frac{x^{3} d y}{x^{3}(1+y)^{3 / 4}}=\\frac{-1}{4} \\int \\frac{d y}{(1+y)^{3 / 4}}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{-1}{4} \\times 4(1+y)^{1 / 4}=-\\left(1+x^{-4}\\right)^{1 / 4}+C\\)\n\n\\(=-\\left(\\frac{x^{4}+1}{x^{4}}\\right)^{1 / 4}+C\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 6
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{\\mathrm{dx}}{(\\mathrm{x}+1)^{\\frac{3}{4}}(\\mathrm{x}-2)^{\\frac{5}{4}}}\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(-\\frac{4}{3}\\left(\\frac{x+1}{x-2}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{4}}+C\\)",
            "\\(4\\left(\\frac{x+1}{x-2}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{4}}+C\\)",
            "\\(4\\left(\\frac{x-2}{x+1}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{4}}+C\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{4}{3}\\left(\\frac{x-2}{x+1}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{4}}+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(\\int \\frac{d x}{(x+1)^{3 / 4}(x-2)^{5 / 4}}\\)\n\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\int \\frac{d x}{\\left(\\frac{x+1}{x-2}\\right)^{3 / 4}(x-2)^{2}}, \\quad \\text { put } \\frac{x+1}{x-2}=t \\\\\n& \\frac{-3}{(x-2)^{2}}=\\frac{d t}{d x} \\\\\n& \\frac{d x}{(x-2)^{2}}=-\\frac{d t}{3}=\\frac{-1}{3} \\int \\frac{d t}{t^{3 / 4}}=-\\frac{1}{3} \\int t \\frac{-3}{4} l t \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{3}\\left[\\frac{t^{\\frac{-3}{4}}+1}{\\frac{-3}{4}}+1\\right]=\\frac{-4}{3}\\left[\\frac{x+1}{x-2}\\right]^{1 / 4}+c\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 6
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "question": "If \\(m\\) is a non-zero number and \\(\\int \\frac{x^{5 m-1}+2 x^{4 m-1}}{\\left(x^{2 m}+x^{m}+1\\right)^{3}} d x=f(x)+c\\), then \\(f(x)\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{x^{5 m}}{2 m\\left(x^{2 m}+x^{m}+1\\right)^{2}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{x^{4 m}}{2 m\\left(x^{2 m}+x^{m}+1\\right)^{2}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{2 m\\left(x^{5 m}+x^{4 m}\\right)}{\\left(x^{2 m}+x^{m}+1\\right)^{2}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\left(x^{5 m}-x^{4 m}\\right)}{2 m\\left(x^{2 m}+x^{m}+1\\right)^{2}}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(\\int \\frac{x^{5 m-1}+2 x^{4 m-1}}{\\left(x^{2 m}+x^{m}+1\\right)^{3}} d x=\\int \\frac{x^{5 m-1}+2 x^{4 m-1}}{x^{6 m}\\left(1+x^{-m}+x^{-2 m}\\right)^{3}} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{x^{-m-1}+2 x^{-2 m-1}}{\\left(1+x^{-m}+x^{-2 m}\\right)^{3}} d x\\)\n\nPut \\(t=1+x^{-m}+x^{-2 m}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\frac{d t}{d x}=-m x^{-m-1}-2 m x^{-2 m-1}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{d t}{-m}=\\left(x^{-m-1}+2 x^{-2 m-1}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\int \\frac{x^{5 m-1}+2 x^{4 m-1}}{\\left(x^{2 m}+x^{m}+1\\right)^{3}} d x=\\frac{1}{-m} \\int t^{-3} d t=\\frac{1}{2 m t^{2}}+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2 m\\left(1+x^{-m}+x^{-2 m}\\right)^{2}}+C\\)\n\n\\[\n=\\frac{x^{4 m}}{2 m\\left(x^{2 m}+x^{m}+1\\right)^{2}}+C\n\\]\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad f(x)=\\frac{x^{4 m}}{2 m\\left(x^{2 m}+x^{m}+1\\right)^{2}}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 6
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{x d x}{2-x^{2}+\\sqrt{2-x^{2}}}\\) equals :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\log \\left|1+\\sqrt{2+x^{2}}\\right|+c\\)",
            "\\(-\\log \\left|1+\\sqrt{2-x^{2}}\\right|+c\\)",
            "\\(-x \\log \\left|1-\\sqrt{2-x^{2}}\\right|+c\\)",
            "\\(x \\log \\left|1-\\sqrt{2+x^{2}}\\right|+c\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int \\frac{x d x}{2-x^{2}+\\sqrt{2-x^{2}}}\\)\n\n\nPut \\(t=\\sqrt{2-x^{2}}, \\frac{d t}{d x}=\\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{2-x^{2}}} \\cdot(-2 x)\\)\\\\\n\\(\\Rightarrow-t d t=x d x\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad \\mathrm{I}=\\int \\frac{(-t) d t}{t^{2}+t}=-\\int \\frac{1}{t+1} d t=-\\log |t+1|\\)\n\n\\[\n=-\\log \\left|\\sqrt{2-x^{2}}+1\\right|+c\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 6
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{x^{2}-x+1}{x^{2}+1} e^{\\cot ^{-1} x} d x=A(x) e^{\\cot ^{-1} x}+C\\), then \\(A(x)\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(-x\\)",
            "\\(x\\)",
            "\\(\\sqrt{1-x}\\)",
            "\\(\\sqrt{1+x}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) Let \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int \\frac{x^{2}-x+1}{x^{2}+1} \\cdot e^{\\cot ^{-1} x} d x\\)\n\n\nPut \\(x=\\cot t \\Rightarrow-\\operatorname{cosec}^{2} t d t=d x\\)\n\nNow, \\(1+\\cot ^{2} t=\\operatorname{cosec}^{2} t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad \\mathrm{I}=\\int \\frac{e^{t}\\left(\\cot ^{2} t-\\cot t+1\\right)}{\\left(1+\\cot ^{2} t\\right)}\\left(-\\operatorname{cosec}^{2} t\\right) d t\\)\n\n\\(=-\\int e^{t}\\left(\\operatorname{cosec}^{2} t-\\cot t\\right) d t\\)\n\n\\(=\\int e^{t}\\left(\\cot t-\\operatorname{cosec}^{2} t\\right) d t=e^{t} \\cot t+\\mathrm{C}\\)\n\n\\(=e^{\\cot ^{-1} x}(x)+\\mathrm{C} \\equiv \\mathrm{A}(x) \\cdot e^{\\cot ^{-1} x}+\\mathrm{C}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{A}(x)=x\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 6
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{d x}{x+x^{7}}=p(x)\\) then, \\(\\int \\frac{x^{6}}{x+x^{7}} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\ln |x|-p(x)+c\\)",
            "\\(\\ln |x|+p(x)+c\\)",
            "\\(x-p(x)+c\\)",
            "\\(x+p(x)+c\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(\\int \\frac{x^{6}}{x+x^{7}} d x=\\int \\frac{x^{6}}{x\\left(1+x^{6}\\right)} d x=\\int \\frac{\\left(1+x^{6}\\right)-1}{x\\left(1+x^{6}\\right)} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{1}{x} d x-\\int \\frac{1}{x+x^{7}} d x=\\ln |x|-p(x)+c\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 6
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "question": "\\(\\int\\left\\{\\frac{(\\log x-1)}{1+(\\log x)^{2}}\\right\\}^{2} d x\\) is equal to",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\log x}{(\\log x)^{2}+1}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{x}{x^{2}+1}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{x e^{x}}{1+x^{2}}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{x}{(\\log x)^{2}+1}+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\int \\frac{(\\log x-1)^{2}}{\\left(1+(\\log x)^{2}\\right)^{2}} d x=\\int \\frac{1+(\\log x)^{2}-2 \\log x}{\\left[1+(\\log x)^{2}\\right]^{2}} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int\\left[\\frac{1}{\\left(1+(\\log x)^{2}\\right)}-\\frac{2 \\log x}{\\left(1+(\\log x)^{2}\\right)^{2}}\\right] d x\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad \\mathrm{I}=\\int\\left[\\frac{e^{t}}{1+t^{2}}-\\frac{2 t e^{t}}{\\left(1+t^{2}\\right)^{2}}\\right] d t\\)\n\n\\(=\\int e^{t}\\left[\\frac{1}{1+t^{2}}-\\frac{2 t}{\\left(1+t^{2}\\right)^{2}}\\right] d t\\)\n\n[Which is of the form \\(\\int e^{x}\\left(f(x)+f^{\\prime}(x)\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\[\n\\left.=f(x) \\cdot e^{x}+c\\right]\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\frac{e^{t}}{1+t^{2}}+c=\\frac{x}{1+(\\log x)^{2}}+c\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 6
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "question": "If \\(\\mathrm{I}_{1}=\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(1-x^{50}\\right)^{100} d x\\) and \\(\\mathrm{I}_{2}=\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(1-x^{50}\\right)^{101} d x\\) such that \\(\\mathrm{I}_{2}=\\alpha \\mathrm{I}_{1}\\) then \\(\\alpha\\) equals to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{5049}{5050}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{5050}{5049}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{5050}{5051}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{5051}{5050}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I_{2}=\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(1-x^{50}\\right)^{101} d x=\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(1-x^{50}\\right)\\left(1-x^{50}\\right)^{100} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(I_{2}=\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(1-x^{50}\\right)^{100} d x-\\int_{0}^{1} x \\underbrace{x^{49}\\left(1-x^{50}\\right)^{100}}_{\\mathrm{II}} d x\\)\n\n\\(I_{2}=I_{1}+\\left[\\frac{x}{5050}\\left(1-x^{50}\\right)^{101}\\right]_{0}^{1}-\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\left(1-x^{50}\\right)^{101}}{5050} d x\\)\n\n\\(I_{2}=I_{1}+0-\\frac{I_{2}}{5050}\\) \\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{5051}{5050} I_{2}=I_{1} \\Rightarrow I_{2}=\\frac{5050}{5051} I_{1}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\alpha=\\frac{5050}{5051}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 6
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{1}{1+e^{\\sin x}} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\pi\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{3 \\pi}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{1}{1+e^{\\sin x}} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{0} \\frac{1}{1+e^{\\sin x}} d x+\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{1}{1+e^{\\sin x}} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2}\\left(\\frac{1}{1+e^{\\sin x}}+\\frac{1}{1+e^{-\\sin x}}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{1+e^{\\sin x}}{1+e^{\\sin x}} d x=\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 6
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "question": "Let \\(f(x)=|x-2|\\) and \\(g(x)=f(f(x)), x \\in[0,4]\\). \\(\\int_{0}^{4} g(x) d x\\) =",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "0",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "(a) \\(f(x)=|x-2|= \\begin{cases}2-x, & x<2 \\\\ x-2, & x \\geq 2\\end{cases}\\)\\ \\(g(x)=f(f(x))= \\begin{cases}2-f(x), & f(x)<2 \\\\ f(x)-2, & f(x) \\geq 2\\end{cases}\\)\\ \\(=\\left\\{\\begin{array}{lll}2-(2-x), & 2-x<2, & x<2 \\\\ (2-x)-2, & 2-x \\geq 2, & x<2 \\\\ 2-(x-2), & x-2<2, & x \\geq 2 \\\\ (x-2)-2, & x-2 \\geq 2, & x \\geq 2\\end{array}\\right.\\)\\ \\(=\\left\\{\\begin{array}{cc}-x & 0<x \\leq 0 \\\\ x & 0<x<2 \\\\ 4-x & 2 \\leq x<4 \\\\ x-4 & x \\geq 4\\end{array}\\right.\\)\\ \\(\\therefore \\int_{0}^{3}[g(x)-f(x)] d x\\)\\ \\(=\\int_{0}^{2} x d x+\\int_{2}^{3}(4-x) d x-\\int_{0}^{3}|x-2| d x=1\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 7
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} \\tan ^{3} x \\cdot \\sin ^{2} 3 x\\left(2 \\sec ^{2} x \\cdot \\sin ^{2} 3 x+3 \\tan x \\cdot \\sin 6 x\\right) d x\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{7}{18}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{9}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{18}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{9}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3}\\left[\\frac{1}{2} \\frac{d\\left(\\tan ^{4} x\\right)}{d x} \\cdot \\sin ^{4} 3 x+\\frac{1}{2} \\tan ^{4} x \\cdot \\frac{d\\left(\\sin ^{4} 3 x\\right)}{d x}\\right] d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} d\\left(\\tan ^{4} x \\cdot \\sin ^{4} 3 x\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\left[\\frac{\\tan ^{4} x \\sin ^{4} 3 x}{2}\\right]_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3}=\\frac{9 \\cdot 0}{2}-\\frac{\\frac{1}{9} \\cdot 1}{2}=\\frac{-1}{18}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 7
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "question": "Let \\(\\{x\\}\\) and \\([x]\\) denote the fractional part of \\(x\\) and the greatest integer \\(\\leq x\\) respectively of a real number \\(x\\). If \\(\\int_{0}^{n}\\{x\\} d x, \\int_{0}^{n}[x] d x\\) and \\(10\\left(n^{2}-n\right),(n \\in \\mathbf{N}, n>1)\\) are three consecutive terms of a G.P., then \\(n\\) is equal to \\(\\qquad\\) .",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (21)\n\n\n\\(\\int_{0}^{n}\\{x\\} d x=n \\int_{0}^{1} x \\cdot d x=\\frac{n}{2}\\)\\\\\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\int_{0}^{n}[x] d x=\\int_{0}^{n}(x-\\{x\\}) d x=\\frac{n^{2}}{2}-\\frac{n}{2}\\)\n\nAccording to the questions,\n\n\\(\\frac{n}{2}, \\frac{n^{2}-n}{2}, 10\\left(n^{2}-n\\right)\\) are in GP\n\n\\(\\therefore\\left(\\frac{n^{2}-n}{2}\\right)^{2}=\\frac{n}{2} \\times 10\\left(n^{2}-n\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow n^{2}=21 n \\Rightarrow n=21\\).",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "21",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 7
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "question": "\\(\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi}|\\pi-| x|| d x\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\sqrt{2} \\pi^{2}\\)",
            "\\(2 \\pi^{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\pi^{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi}|\\pi-| x|| d x \\quad[\\because|\\pi-| x||\\) is even \\(]\\)\n\n\n\\(=2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi}|\\pi-| x|| d x\\)\n\n\\(=2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi}(\\pi-x) d x\\)\n\n\\(=2\\left[\\pi x-\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\right]_{0}^{\\pi}=2\\left(\\pi^{2}-\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{2}\\right)=\\pi^{2}\\).",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 7
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "question": "If the value of the integral \\(\\int_{0}^{1 / 2} \\frac{x^{2}}{\\left(1-x^{2}\\right)^{3 / 2}} d x\\) is \\(\\frac{k}{6}\\), then \\(k\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(2 \\sqrt{3}-\\pi\\)",
            "\\(2 \\sqrt{3}+\\pi\\)",
            "\\(3 \\sqrt{2}+\\pi\\)",
            "\\(3 \\sqrt{2}-\\pi\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(\\frac{k}{6}=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{1}{2}} \\frac{x^{2}}{\\left(1-x^{2}\\right)^{3 / 2}} d x\\)\n\n\nLet \\(x=\\sin \\theta ; d x=\\cos \\theta d \\theta\\),\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { then } \\int_{0}^{\\frac{1}{2}} \\frac{x^{2}}{\\left(1-x^{2}\\right)^{3 / 2}} d x=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{6}} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} \\theta \\cos \\theta}{\\cos ^{3} \\theta} d \\theta \\\\\n& \\therefore \\frac{k}{6}=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{6}} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} \\theta}{\\cos ^{3} \\theta} \\cdot \\cos \\theta d \\theta \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\frac{k}{6}=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{6}} \\tan ^{2} \\theta d \\theta=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{6}}\\left(\\sec ^{2} \\theta-1\\right) d \\theta \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\frac{k}{6}=(\\tan \\theta-\\theta)_{0}^{\\pi / 6}=\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}-\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)=\\frac{2 \\sqrt{3}-x}{6} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow k=2 \\sqrt{3}-\\pi\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 7
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{0}^{2}|| x-1|-x| d x\\) is equal to \\(\\qquad\\) .",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (1.50)\n\n\n\\(\\int_{0}^{2}|| x-1|-x| d x=\\int_{0}^{1}|1-x-x| d x+\\int_{1}^{2}|| x-1-x \\mid d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{1}(1-2 x) d x+\\int_{1 / 2}^{1}(2 x-1) d x+\\int_{1}^{2} d x\\) \\(=\\left[x-x^{2}\\right]_{0}^{\\frac{1}{2}}+\\left[x^{2}-x\\right]_{\\frac{1}{2}}^{1}+[x]_{1}^{2}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2}-\\frac{1}{4}+(1-1)-\\left(\\frac{1}{4}-\\frac{1}{2}\\right)+2-1=\\frac{1}{4}+\\frac{1}{4}+1=\\frac{3}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "1.50",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 7
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "question": "Let \\([t]\\) denote the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(t\\). Then the value of \\(\\int_{1}^{2}|2 x-[3 x]| d x\\) is \\(\\qquad\\) .",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (1)\n\n\n\\(\\int_{1}^{2}|2 x-[3 x]| d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{1}^{2}|3 x-[3 x]-x| d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{1}^{2}|\\{3 x\\}-x| d x=\\int_{1}^{2}(x-\\{3 x\\}) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{1}^{2} x d x-\\int_{1}^{2}\\{3 x\\} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\left[\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\right]_{1}^{2}-3 \\int_{0}^{1 / 3} 3 x d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{(4-1)}{2}-9\\left[\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\right]_{0}^{1 / 3}=\\frac{3}{2}-\\frac{1}{2}=1\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "1",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 7
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "question": "If for all real triplets \\((a, b, c), f(x)=a+b x+c x^{2}\\); then \\(\\int_{0}^{1} f(x) d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(2\\left\\{3 f(1)+2 f\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)\\right\\}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\left\\{f(1)+3 f\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)\\right\\}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\left\\{f(0)+f\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)\\right\\}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{6}\\left\\{f(0)+f(1)+4 f\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)\\right\\}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(a+b x+c x^{2}\\right) d x=a x+\\frac{b x^{2}}{2}+\\left.\\frac{c x^{3}}{3}\\right|_{0} ^{1}=a+\\frac{b}{2}+\\frac{c}{3}\\)\n\n\nNow, \\(f(1)=a+b+c, f(0)=a\\) and \\(f\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)=a+\\frac{b}{2}+\\frac{c}{4}\\)\n\nNow, \\(\\frac{1}{6}\\left(f(1)+f(0)+4 f\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{6}\\left(a+b+c+a+4\\left(a+\\frac{b}{2}+\\frac{c}{4}\\right)\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{6}(6 a+3 b+2 c)=a+\\frac{b}{2}+\\frac{c}{3}\\)\n\nHence, \\(\\int_{0}^{1} f(x)=\\frac{1}{6}\\left\\{f(0)+f(1)+4 f\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)\\right\\}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 7
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{0}^{2 \\pi} \\frac{x \\sin ^{8} x}{\\sin ^{8} x+\\cos ^{8} x} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(2 \\pi\\)",
            "\\(2 \\pi^{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\pi^{2}\\)",
            "\\(4 \\pi\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(\\int_{0}^{2 \\pi} \\frac{x \\sin ^{8} x}{\\sin ^{8} x+\\cos ^{8} x} d x\\)\n\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\int_{0}^{\\pi}\\left[\\frac{x \\sin ^{8} x}{\\sin ^{8} x+\\cos ^{8} x}+\\frac{(2 \\pi-x) \\sin ^{8} x}{\\sin ^{8} x+\\cos ^{8} x}\\right] d x \\\\\n& {\\left[\\because \\int_{0}^{2 a} f(x) d x=\\int_{0}^{a} f(x) d x+\\int_{0}^{a} f(2 a-x) d x\\right]}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\frac{2 \\pi \\sin ^{8} x}{\\sin ^{8} x+\\cos ^{8} x} d x\\)\n\n\\(=2 \\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2}\\left[\\frac{\\sin ^{8} x}{\\sin ^{8} x+\\cos ^{8} x}+\\frac{\\cos ^{8} x}{\\sin ^{8} x+\\cos ^{8} x}\\right] d x\\)\n\n\\(=2 \\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} 1 d x=2 \\pi \\times \\frac{\\pi}{2}=\\pi^{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 7
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "question": "If \\(I=\\int_{1}^{2} \\frac{d x}{\\sqrt{2 x^{3}-9 x^{2}+12 x+4}}\\), then:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{8}<I^{2}<\\frac{1}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{9}<I^{2}<\\frac{1}{8}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{16}<I^{2}<\\frac{1}{9}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{6}<I^{2}<\\frac{1}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(f(x)=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2 x^{3}-9 x^{2}+12 x+4}}\\)\n\n\n\\(f^{\\prime}(x)=\\frac{-1}{2}\\left(\\frac{\\left(6 x^{2}-18 x+12\\right)}{\\left(2 x^{3}-9 x^{2}-12 x+4\\right)^{3 / 2}}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{-6(x-1)(x-2)}{2\\left(2 x^{3}-9 x^{2}+12 x+4\\right)^{3 / 2}}\\)\n\n\\(f(1)=\\frac{1}{3}\\) and \\(f(2)=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{8}}\\)\n\nIt is increasing function\n\n\\(\\frac{1}{3}<I<\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{8}}\\)\n\n\\(\\frac{1}{9}<I^{2}<\\frac{1}{8}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 7
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "question": "If \\(f(a+b+1-x)=f(x)\\), for all \\(x\\), where \\(a\\) and \\(b\\) are fixed positive real numbers, then \\(\\frac{1}{a+b} \\int_{a}^{b} x(f(x)+f(x+1)) d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\int_{a+1}^{b+1} f(x) d x\\)",
            "\\(\\int_{a-1}^{b-1} f(x) d x\\)",
            "\\(\\int_{a-1}^{b-1} f(x+1) d x\\)",
            "\\(\\int_{a+1}^{b+1} f(x+1) d x\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\frac{1}{(a+b)} \\int_{a}^{b} x[f(x)+f(x+1)] d x\\)\n\n\n\\(x \\rightarrow a+b-x\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{1}{(a+b)} \\int_{a}^{b}(a+b-x)[f(a+b-x)+f(a+b+1-x)] d x\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{1}{(a+b)} \\int_{a}^{b}(a+b-x)[f(x+1)+f(x)] d x\\)\n\n\\([\\because\\) put \\(x \\rightarrow x+1\\) in \\(f(a+b+\\)\n\nAdd (i) and (ii)\n\n\\[\n1-x)=f(x)]\n\\]\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{a}^{b}[f(x+1)+f(x)] d x\\)\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{a}^{b} f(x+1) d x+\\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b+1-x) d x+\\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x\\) \\(2 I=2 \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\int_{a-1}^{b-1} f(x+1) d x\\)\n\n\\([\\because\\) Put \\(x \\rightarrow x+1]\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 8
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\alpha\\) for which \\(4 \\alpha \\int_{-1}^{2} e^{-\\alpha|x|} d x=5\\), is :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\log _{e} 2\\)",
            "\\(\\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{3}{2}\\right)\\)",
            "\\(\\log _{e} \\sqrt{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{4}{3}\\right)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(4 \\alpha\\left\\{\\int_{-1}^{0} e^{\\alpha x} d x+\\int_{0}^{2} e^{-\\alpha x} d x\\right\\}=5\\)\n\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 4 \\alpha\\left\\{\\left.\\frac{e^{\\alpha x}}{\\alpha}\\right|_{-1} ^{0}+\\left.\\frac{e^{-\\alpha x}}{-\\alpha}\\right|_{0} ^{2}\\right\\}=5\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 4 \\alpha\\left\\{\\left(\\frac{1-e^{-\\alpha}}{\\alpha}\\right)-\\left(\\frac{e^{-2 \\alpha}-1}{\\alpha}\\right)\\right\\}=5\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 4\\left(2-e^{-\\alpha}-e^{-2 \\alpha}\\right)=5\\)\n\nPut \\(e^{-\\alpha}=t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 4 \\mathrm{t}^{2}+4 \\mathrm{t}-3=0 \\quad \\Rightarrow(2 \\mathrm{t}+3)(2 \\mathrm{t}-1)=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow e^{-\\alpha}=\\frac{1}{2} \\Rightarrow \\alpha=\\log _{e} 2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 8
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "question": "If \\(\\theta_{1}\\) and \\(\\theta_{2}\\) be respectively the smallest and the largest values of \\(\\theta\\) in \\((0,2 \\pi)-\\{\\pi\\}\\) which satisfy the equation, \\(2 \\cot ^{2} \\theta-\\frac{5}{\\sin \\theta}+4=0\\), then \\(\\int_{\\theta_{1}}^{\\theta_{2}} \\cos ^{2} 3 \\theta d \\theta\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{2 \\pi}{3}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{3}+\\frac{1}{6}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{9}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(2 \\cot ^{2} \\theta-\\frac{5}{\\sin \\theta}+4=0\\)\n\n\n\\(\\frac{2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta}{\\sin ^{2} \\theta}-\\frac{5}{\\sin \\theta}+4=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta-5 \\sin \\theta+4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta=0, \\sin \\theta \\neq 0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 \\sin ^{2} \\theta-5 \\sin \\theta+2=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow(2 \\sin \\theta-1)(\\sin \\theta-2)=0\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\sin \\theta=\\frac{1}{2} \\quad \\Rightarrow \\theta=\\frac{\\pi}{6}, \\frac{5 \\pi}{6}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad \\int_{\\pi / 6}^{5 \\pi / 6} \\cos ^{2} 3 \\theta d \\theta=\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{5 \\pi / 6} \\frac{1+\\cos 6 \\theta}{2} d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\theta+\\frac{\\sin 6 \\theta}{6}\\right]_{\\pi / 6}^{5 \\pi / 6}=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\frac{5 \\pi}{6}-\\frac{\\pi}{6}+\\frac{1}{6}(0-0)\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2} \\cdot \\frac{4 \\pi}{6}=\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 8
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "question": "Let \\(f: \\mathrm{R} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{R}\\) be a continuously differentiable function such that \\(f(2)=6\\) and \\(f^{\\'} (2)=\\frac{1}{48}\\). If \\(\\int_{6}^{f(x)} 4 t^{3} d t=(x-2) g(x)\\), then \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 2} g(x)\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "18",
            "24",
            "12",
            "36"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Given, \\(\\int_{6}^{f(x)} 4 t^{3} d t=(x-2) g(x)\\)\n\n\nDifferentiating both sides,\n\n\\(4(f(x))^{3} \\cdot f^{\\prime}(x)=g^{\\prime}(x)(x-2)+g(x)\\)\n\nPutting \\(x=2, \\frac{4(6)^{3} \\cdot 1}{48}=g(2) \\Rightarrow \\lim _{x \\rightarrow 2} g(x)=18\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 8
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "question": "If \\(\\int_{0}^{\\frac{x}{2}} \\frac{\\cot x}{\\cot x+\\operatorname{cosec} x} d x=m(\\pi+n)\\), then m.n is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "1",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "-1"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\cot x d x}{\\cot x+\\operatorname{cosec} x}\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\cot x d x}{1+\\cos x}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2}\\left(1-\\frac{1}{1+\\cos x}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=[x]_{0}^{\\pi / 2}-\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{1}{2 \\cos ^{2} \\frac{x}{2}} d x=\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sec ^{2} \\frac{x}{2} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\left(\\tan \\frac{x}{2}\\right)_{0}^{\\pi / 2}=\\frac{\\pi}{2}-[1]=\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-1\\right)=m \\pi+m n\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore m=, n=-2\\), Hence, \\(m n=-1\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 8
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{0}^{2 \\pi}[\\sin 2 x(1+\\cos 3 x)] d x\\), where \\([t]\\) denotes the greatest integer function, is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\pi\\)",
            "\\(-\\pi\\)",
            "\\(-2 \\pi\\)",
            "\\(2 \\pi\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(I=\\int_{0}^{2 \\pi}[\\sin 2 x(1+\\cos 3 x)] d x\\)\n\n\n\\(\\because \\int_{0}^{a} f(x)=\\int_{0}^{a} f(a-x) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I=\\int_{0}^{2 \\pi}[-\\sin 2 x(1+\\cos 3 \\mathrm{x})] \\mathrm{dx}\\)\n\nFrom (1) \\(+(2)\\), we get;\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{0}^{2 \\pi}(-1) d x \\Rightarrow 2 I=-(x)_{0}^{2 \\pi} \\Rightarrow I=-\\pi\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 8
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} \\sec ^{2 / 3} x \\operatorname{cosec}^{4 / 3} x d x\\) is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "\\(3^{5 / 6}-3^{2 / 3}\\)",
            "\\(3^{4 / 3}-3^{1 / 3}\\)",
            "\\(3^{7 / 6}-3^{5 / 6}\\)",
            "\\(3^{5 / 3}-3^{1 / 3}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Let, \\(I=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{6}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{3}} \\sec ^{\\frac{2}{3}} x \\cdot \\operatorname{cosec}^{\\frac{4}{3}} x d x=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{6} \\cos ^{\\frac{\\pi}{3}} x \\cdot \\sin ^{\\frac{4}{3}} x}^{\\frac{\\pi}{3}}\\) \\(=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{6}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{3}} \\frac{1 d x}{\\cos ^{2} x \\cdot \\tan ^{\\frac{4}{3}} x}=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{6}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{3}} \\frac{\\sec ^{2} x d x}{\\tan ^{\\frac{4}{3}} x}\\)\n\n\nLet \\(\\tan x=u\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int_{\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}}^{\\sqrt{3}} u^{-\\frac{4}{3}} d u=\\frac{3\\left[u^{-\\frac{1}{3}}\\right]}{-1}\\)\n\n\\(=-3\\left[3^{-\\frac{1}{6}}-\\frac{1}{3^{\\frac{-1}{6}}}\\right]=-3\\left(3^{\\frac{-1}{6}}-3^{\\frac{1}{6}}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=3\\left(3^{\\frac{1}{6}}-3^{\\frac{1}{6}}\\right)=\\left(3^{\\frac{7}{6}}-3^{\\frac{5}{6}}\\right)\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 8
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\sin ^{3} x}{\\sin x+\\cos x} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi-2}{8}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi-1}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi-2}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi-1}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (b) Let \\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\sin ^{3} x d x}{\\sin x+\\cos x}\\)\n\nUse the property \\(\\int_{0}^{a} f(x) d x=\\int_{0}^{a} f(a-x) d x\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\cos ^{3} x d x}{\\sin x+\\cos x}\\)\n\nAdding equation (1) and (2), we get\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 I=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2}\\left(1-\\frac{1}{2} \\sin (2 x)\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[x+\\frac{1}{4} \\cos 2 x\\right]_{0}^{\\pi / 2}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\frac{\\pi-1}{4}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 8
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int_{0}^{1} x \\cot ^{-1}\\left(1-x^{2}+x^{4}\\right) d x\\) is",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e} 2\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\log _{e} 2\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\log _{e} 2\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e} 2\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (0) \\(\\int_{0}^{1} x \\cot ^{-1}\\left(1-x^{2}+x^{4}\\right) d x=\\int_{0}^{1} x \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{1+x^{4}-x^{2}}\\right)\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{1} x \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}-\\left(x^{2}-1\\right)}{1+x^{2}\\left(x^{2}-1\\right)}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{1} 1 \\tan ^{-1} t^{2} d t-\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{-1}^{0} 1 \\tan ^{-1} k d k\\)\n\nPut \\(x^{2}=t \\Rightarrow 2 x d x=d t\\) in the first integral\n\nand \\(x^{2}-1=k \\Rightarrow 2 x d x=d k\\) in the second integral.\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{1} 1 \\tan ^{-1} t d t-\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{1} 1 \\tan ^{-1} k d k \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\left.t \\tan ^{-1} t\\right|_{0} ^{1}-\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{t}{1+t^{2}} d t\\right)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{array}{r}\n-\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\left.k \\tan ^{-1} k\\right|_{0} ^{1}-\\int_{-1}^{0} \\frac{k}{1+k^{2}} d k\\right) \\\\\n=\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\left(\\left.\\frac{1}{2} \\ln \\left(1+t^{2}\\right)\\right|_{0} ^{1}\\right)-\\frac{1}{2}\\left(-\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\left(\\left.\\frac{1}{2} \\ln \\left(1+k^{2}\\right)\\right|_{-1} ^{0}\\right)\\right)\\right. \\\\\n=\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{8}-\\frac{1}{4} \\ln 2\\right)-\\left(\\frac{-\\pi}{8}-\\frac{1}{4} 10-\\ln 2\\right)=\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\frac{1}{2} \\ln 2\n\\end{array}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "0",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 8
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "question": "If \\(f: \\mathrm{R} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{R}\\) is a differentiable function and \\(f(2)=6\\), then \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 2} \\int_{6}^{f(x)} \\frac{2 t d t}{(x-2)}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(24 f^{\\prime}(2)\\)",
            "\\(2 f^{\\prime}(2)\\)",
            "0",
            "\\(12 f^{\\prime}(2)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Using L' Hospital rule and Leibnitz theorem, we get\n\n\n\\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 2} \\frac{\\int_{6}^{f(x)} 2 t d t}{(x-2)}=\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 2} \\frac{2 f(x) f^{\\prime}(x)-0}{1}\\)\n\nPutting \\(x=2,2 f(2) f^{\\prime}(2)=12 f^{\\prime}(2) \\quad[\\because f(2)=6]\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 8
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "question": "If \\(f(x)=\\frac{2-x \\cos x}{2+x \\cos x}\\) and \\(g(x)=\\log _{e} x,(\\mathrm{x}>0)\\) then the value of the integral \\(\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} g(f(x)) d x\\) is :",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\log _{\\mathrm{e}} 3\\)",
            "\\(\\log _{\\mathrm{e}} \\mathrm{e}\\)",
            "\\(\\log _{\\mathrm{e}} 2\\)",
            "\\(\\log _{e} 1\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(g(f(x))=\\log \\left(\\frac{2-x \\cos x}{2+x \\cos x}\\right), x>0\\)\n\n\nLet \\(I=\\int_{-\\pi / 4}^{\\pi / 4} \\log \\left(\\frac{2-x \\cos x}{2+x \\cos x}\\right) d x\\)\n\nUse the property \\(\\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\)\n\nThen, equation (i) becomes,\n\n\\(I=\\int_{-\\pi / 4}^{\\pi / 4} \\log \\left(\\frac{2+x \\cos x}{2-x \\cos x}\\right) d x\\)\n\nAdding (i) and (ii)\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{-\\pi / 4}^{\\pi / 4} \\log \\left(\\frac{2-x \\cos x}{2+x \\cos x} \\cdot \\frac{2+x \\cos x}{2-x \\cos x}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\log (1) d x=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=0=\\log 1\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 9
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "question": "Let \\(f(x)=\\int_{0}^{x} g(t) d t\\), where \\(g\\) is a non-zero even function. If \\(f(x+5)=g(x)\\), then \\(\\int_{0}^{x} f(t) d t\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\int_{x+5}^{5} g(t) d t\\)",
            "\\(\\int_{5}^{x+5} g(t) d t\\)",
            "\\(2 \\int_{5}^{x+5} g(t) d t\\)",
            "\\(5 \\int_{x+5}^{5} g(t) d t\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(f(x)=\\int_{0}^{x} g(g) d t\\),\n\n\n\\(\\because g\\) is a non-zero even function.\n\n\\(\\therefore g(-x)=g(x)\\),\n\nGiven, \\(f(x+5)=g(x)\\)\n\nFrom (i) \\(f^{\\prime}(x)=g(x)\\)\n\nLet, \\(I=\\int_{0}^{x} f(t) d t\\),\n\nPut \\(t=\\lambda-5 \\Rightarrow I=\\int_{5}^{x+5} f(\\lambda-5) d \\lambda\\)\n\n\\(\\because f(x+5)=\\mathrm{g}(x)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(-x+5)=g(-x)=g(x)\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int_{5}^{x+5} f(\\lambda-5) d \\lambda\\) \\(f(0)=0, g(x)\\) is even \\(\\Rightarrow f(x)\\) is odd\n\n\\(\\therefore I=\\int_{5}^{x+5}-f(5-\\lambda) d \\lambda\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int_{5}^{x+5} g(\\lambda) d \\lambda=\\int_{x+5}^{5} g(t) d t\\) (from(iv))",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 9
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "question": "Let \\(f\\) and \\(g\\) be continuous functions on \\([0, \\mathrm{a}]\\) such that \\(f(x)=f(a-x)\\) and \\(g(x)+g(a-x)=4\\), then \\(\\int_{0}^{a} f(x) g(x) d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(4 \\int_{0}^{a} f(x) d x\\)",
            "\\(\\int_{0}^{a} f(x) d x\\)",
            "\\(2 \\int_{0}^{a} f(x) d x\\)",
            "\\(-3 \\int_{0}^{a} f(x) d x\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "(c) \\(f(x)=f(a-x)\\)\\ \\(g(x)+g(a-x)=4\\)\\ Let, the integral,\\ \\(I=\\int_{0}^{a} f(x) g(x) d x\\)\\ \\(=\\int_{0}^{a} f(a-x) \\cdot g(a-x) d x\\)\\ \\(\\left[\\because \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\right]\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int_{0}^{a} f(x)[4-g(x)] d x\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int_{0}^{a} 4 f(x) d x-\\int_{0}^{a} f(x) \\cdot g(x) d x\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int_{0}^{a} 4 f(x) d x-I\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow 2 I=\\int_{0}^{a} 4 f(x) d x\\)\\ \\(\\Rightarrow I=2 \\int_{0}^{a} f(x) d x\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 9
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{1}^{e}\\left\\{\\left(\\frac{x}{e}\\right)^{2 x}-\\left(\\frac{e}{x}\\right)^{x}\\right\\} \\log _{e} x d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}-e-\\frac{1}{e^{2}}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{1}{2}+\\frac{1}{e}-\\frac{1}{2 e^{2}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{2}-\\frac{1}{e}-\\frac{1}{2 e^{2}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{2}-e-\\frac{1}{2 e^{2}}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(I=\\int_{1}^{e}\\left\\{\\left(\\frac{x}{e}\\right)^{2 x}-\\left(\\frac{e}{x}\\right)^{x}\\right\\} \\log _{e} x d x\\)\n\n\nLet \\(\\left(\\frac{x}{e}\\right)^{x}=t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\quad x \\ln \\left(\\frac{x}{e}\\right)=\\ln t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow x(\\ln x-1)=\\ln t\\)\n\nOn differentiating both sides w.r. \\(x\\) we get\n\n\\(\\ln x . d x=\\frac{d t}{t}\\)\n\nWhen \\(x=e\\) then \\(t=1\\) and when \\(x=1\\) then \\(t=\\frac{1}{e}\\).\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=\\int_{\\frac{1}{e}}^{1}\\left(t^{2}-\\frac{1}{t}\\right) \\cdot \\frac{d t}{t}=\\int_{\\frac{1}{e}}^{1}\\left(t-\\frac{1}{t^{2}}\\right) d t \\\\\n& =\\left(\\frac{t^{2}}{2}+\\frac{1}{t}\\right)_{\\frac{1}{e}}^{1}=\\left(\\frac{1}{2}+1\\right)-\\left(\\frac{1}{2 e^{2}}+e\\right)=\\frac{3}{2}-e-\\frac{1}{2 e^{2}}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 9
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int_{-2}^{2} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{\\left[\\frac{x}{\\pi}\\right]+\\frac{1}{2}} d x\\) (where \\([\\mathrm{x}]\\) denotes the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(x\\) ) is:",
        "options": [
            "0",
            "\\(\\sin 4\\)",
            "4",
            "\\(4-\\sin 4\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let \\(f(x)=\\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{\\left[\\frac{x}{\\pi}\\right]+\\frac{1}{2}}\\)\n\n\nSo, \\(f(-x)=\\frac{\\sin ^{2}(-x)}{\\left[\\frac{-x}{\\pi}\\right]+\\frac{1}{2}} \\quad \\because[-x]=-1-[x]\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(-x)=\\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{-1-\\left[\\frac{x}{\\pi}\\right]+\\frac{1}{2}}=\\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{-\\frac{1}{2}-\\left[\\frac{x}{\\pi}\\right]}=-f(x)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(x)\\) is odd function\n\nHence, \\(\\int_{-2}^{2} f(x) d x=0\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 9
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 4} \\frac{\\mathrm{d} x}{\\sin 2 x\\left(\\tan ^{5} x+\\cot ^{5} x\\right)}\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{20} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{9 \\sqrt{3}}\\right)\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{10}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{9 \\sqrt{3}}\\right)\\right)\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{40}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{5}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{3 \\sqrt{3}}\\right)\\)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{6}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{d x}{\\sin 2 x\\left(\\tan ^{5} x+\\cot ^{5} x\\right)}\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\pi}{6} \\frac{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}{2 \\frac{\\tan ^{5} x \\cdot \\sec ^{2} x}{\\sin x}\\left(\\left(\\tan ^{5} x\\right)^{2}+1\\right)}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{6}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{\\tan ^{4} x \\cdot \\sec ^{2} x}{\\left(\\tan ^{5} x\\right)^{2}+1} d x\\).\n\nLet \\(\\tan ^{4} x=t\\).\n\n\\(5 \\tan ^{4} x \\cdot \\sec ^{2} x d x=d t\\).\n\nWhen \\(x \\rightarrow \\frac{\\pi}{4}\\) then \\(t \\rightarrow 1\\)\n\nand \\(x \\rightarrow \\frac{\\pi}{6}\\) then \\(t \\rightarrow\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)^{5}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad \\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{10} \\int_{\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)^{5}}^{\\frac{d t}{t^{2}+1}}\\)\n\n\\[\n=\\frac{1}{10}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{9 \\sqrt{3}}\\right)\\right)\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 9
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "question": "Let \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{\\mathrm{a}}^{\\mathrm{b}}\\left(x^{4}-2 x^{2}\\right) \\mathrm{d} x\\). If \\(\\mathrm{I}\\) is minimum then the ordered pair \\((\\mathrm{a}, \\mathrm{b})\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\((0, \\sqrt{2})\\)",
            "\\((\\-\\sqrt{2}, 0)\\)",
            "\\((\\sqrt{2},-\\sqrt{2})\\)",
            "\\((\\-\\sqrt{2}, \\sqrt{2})\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(I=\\int_{a}^{b}\\left(x^{4}-2 x^{2}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{d I}{d x}=x^{4}-2 x^{2}=0\\) (for minimum)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow x=0, \\pm \\sqrt{2}\\)\n\nAlso, \\(I=\\left[\\frac{x^{5}}{5}-\\frac{2 x^{3}}{3}\\right]_{a}^{b}\\)\\\\\nFor \\(\\mathrm{a}=0, \\mathrm{~b}=\\sqrt{2}\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{-8 \\sqrt{2}}{15}\\)\n\nFor \\(\\mathrm{a}=-\\sqrt{2}, \\mathrm{~b}=0\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{-8 \\sqrt{2}}{15}\\).\n\nFor \\(\\mathrm{a}=\\sqrt{2}, \\mathrm{~b}=-\\sqrt{2}\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{16 \\sqrt{2}}{15}\\).\n\nFor \\(\\mathrm{a}=-\\sqrt{2}, \\mathrm{~b}=\\sqrt{2}\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{-16 \\sqrt{2}}{15}\\).\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad I\\) is minimum when \\((a, b)=(-\\sqrt{2}, \\sqrt{2})\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 9
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "question": "If \\(\\int_{0}^{x} f(\\mathrm{t}) \\mathrm{dt}=x^{2}+\\int_{x}^{1} \\mathrm{t}^{2} f(\\mathrm{t}) \\mathrm{dt}\\), then \\(f^{\\prime}(1 / 2)\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{24}{25}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{18}{25}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{4}{5}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{6}{25}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(\\int_{0}^{x} f(t) d t=x^{2}+\\int_{x}^{1} t^{2} f(t) d t\\)\n\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(x)=2 x-x^{2} f(x)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(x)=\\frac{2 x}{1+x^{2}}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f^{\\prime}(x)=\\frac{2\\left(1-x^{2}\\right)}{\\left(1+x^{2}\\right)^{2}}\\)\n\nThen,\n\n\\(f^{\\prime}(1 / 2)=\\frac{2\\left(1-\\frac{1}{4}\\right)}{\\left(1+\\frac{1}{4}\\right)^{2}}=\\frac{3}{2} \\times \\frac{16}{25}=\\frac{24}{25}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 9
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{d x}{[x]+[\\sin x]+4}\\), where \\([t]\\) denotes the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(t\\), is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{12}(7 \\pi+5)\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{12}(7 \\pi-5)\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{20}(4 \\pi-3)\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{10}(4 \\pi-3)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (c) \\(I=\\int_{\\frac{-\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\frac{d x}{[x]+[\\sin x]+4}\\)\n\n\\[\n=\\int_{\\frac{-\\pi}{2}}^{-1} \\frac{d x}{-2-1+4}+\\int_{-1}^{0} \\frac{d x}{-1-1+4}+\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d x}{0+0+4}+\\int_{1}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\frac{d x}{1+0+4}\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\left(-1+\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\right)+\\frac{1}{2}(0+1)+\\frac{1}{4}(1-0)+\\frac{1}{5}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-1\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{3 \\pi}{5}-\\frac{9}{20}=\\frac{3}{20}(4 \\pi-3)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 9
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi}|\\cos x|^{3} \\mathrm{~d} x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "0",
            "\\(\\frac{4}{3}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{2}{3}\\)",
            "\\(-\\frac{4}{3}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}|\\cos x|^{3} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\cos ^{3} x d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{2}{4} \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2}(3 \\cos x+\\cos 3 x) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\left[\\because \\cos 3 \\theta=4 \\cos ^{3} \\theta-3 \\cos \\theta\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[3 \\sin x+\\frac{\\sin 3 x}{3}\\right]_{0}^{\\pi / 2}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2}\\left(3-\\frac{1}{3}\\right)=\\frac{4}{3}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 9
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "question": "Let \\(f\\) be a differentiable function from \\(\\mathbf{R}\\) to \\(\\mathbf{R}\\) such that \\(| f(x) - f(y)|\\leq 2| x- y|^{3 / 2}\\), for all \\(x, y, \\in \\mathbf{R}\\). If \\(f(0)=1\\) then \\(\\int_{0}^{1} f^{2}(x) d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "2",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "0"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(\\because f: R \\rightarrow R\\)\n\n\nand \\(|f(x)-f(y)| \\leq 2 \\cdot|x-y|^{3 / 2}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow\\left|\\frac{f(x)-f(y)}{x-y}\\right| \\leq 2 \\sqrt{x-y}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\lim _{x \\rightarrow y}\\left|\\frac{f(x)-f(y)}{x-y}\\right| \\leq \\lim _{x \\rightarrow y} 2 \\sqrt{x-y}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow\\left|f^{\\prime}(x)\\right|=0\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore f(x)\\) is a constant function.\n\nGiven \\(f(0)=1 \\Rightarrow f(x)=1\\)\n\nHence, the integral\n\n\\(\\int_{0}^{1} f^{2}(x) d x=\\int_{0}^{1} 1 d x=[x]_{0}^{1}=1\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 10
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "question": "If \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{\\tan \\theta}{\\sqrt{2 \\mathrm{ksec} \\theta}} \\mathrm{d} \\theta=1-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}\\), then the value of \\(\\mathrm{k}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "4",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "1",
            "2"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Let, \\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{\\tan \\theta}{\\sqrt{2 k \\sec \\theta}} d \\theta\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2 k}} \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{\\sin \\theta}{\\sqrt{\\cos \\theta}} d \\theta\\)\n\nLet \\(\\cos \\theta=t^{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\sin \\theta d \\theta=-2 t d t\\)\n\nHence, integral becomes,\n\n\\(I=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2 k}} \\int_{1}^{\\sqrt{\\frac{1}{2}}} \\frac{-2 t d t}{t}\\)\n\n\\(=\\sqrt{\\frac{2}{k}} \\frac{\\int_{\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}}^{1} d t}{}\\) \\(=\\sqrt{\\frac{2}{k}}\\left(1-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\sqrt{2}-1}{\\sqrt{k}}\\)\n\n\\(=1-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}\\) (Given)\n\n\\(\\therefore k=2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 10
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{1+2^{x}} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
            "4 \\pi",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{8}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Let, \\(I=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{1+2^{x}} d x\\)\n\n\nUsing, \\(\\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\), we get :\n\n\\(I=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{1+2^{-x}} d x\\)\n\nAdding (i) and (ii), we get;\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& 2 I=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin ^{2} x d x \\Rightarrow 2 I=2 \\cdot \\int_{0}^{x / 2} \\sin ^{2} x d x \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 2 I=2 \\times \\frac{\\pi}{4} \\Rightarrow I=\\frac{\\pi}{4}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 10
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "question": "If \\(f(x)=\\int_{0}^{x} t(\\sin x-\\sin t) d t\\) then:",
        "options": [
            "\\(f^{\\prime \\prime \\prime}(x)+f^{\\prime}(x)=\\cos x-2 x \\sin x\\)",
            "\\(f^{\\prime \\prime \\prime}(x)+f^{\\prime \\prime}(x)-f^{\\prime}(x)=\\cos x\\)",
            "\\(f^{\\prime \\prime \\prime}(x)-f^{\\prime \\prime}(x)=\\cos x-2 x \\sin x\\)",
            "\\(f^{\\prime \\prime \\prime}(x)+f^{\\prime \\prime}(x)=\\sin x\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(f(x)=\\int_{0}^{x} t(\\sin x-\\sin t) \\cdot d t\\)\n\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\sin x \\int_{0}^{x} t \\cdot d t-\\int_{0}^{x} t \\sin t \\cdot d t \\\\\n& =\\frac{x^{2}}{2} \\sin x+[t \\cos t]_{0}^{x}+\\sin x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(x)=\\frac{x^{2}}{2} \\sin x+x \\cos x+\\sin x\\)\n\n\\(f^{\\prime}(x)=\\frac{x^{2}}{2} \\cos x+2 \\cos x\\)\n\n\\(f^{\\prime \\prime}(x)=x \\cos x-\\frac{x^{2}}{2} \\sin x-2 \\sin x\\)\n\n\\(f^{\\prime \\prime \\prime}(x)=\\cos x-2 x \\sin x-\\frac{x^{2}}{2} \\cos x-2 \\cos x\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore f^{\\prime \\prime \\prime}(x)+f^{\\prime}(x)=\\cos x-2 x \\sin x\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 10
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "question": "The value of integral \\(\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}} \\frac{x}{1+\\sin x} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}(\\sqrt{2}+1)\\)",
            "\\(\\pi(\\sqrt{2}-1)\\)",
            "\\(2 \\pi(\\sqrt{2}-1)\\)",
            "\\(\\pi \\sqrt{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let \\(I=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}} \\frac{x}{1+\\sin x} d x\\)\n\n\nalso let \\(K=\\frac{x}{1+\\sin x}\\)\n\nMultiplying numerator and denominator by \\((1-\\sin x)\\), we get;\\\\\n\\(K=\\frac{x(1-\\sin x)}{1-(\\sin x)^{2}}=\\frac{x(1-\\sin x)}{(\\cos x)^{2}}\\)\n\n\\(=x(1-\\sin x) \\sec ^{2} x\\)\n\n\\(=x \\sec ^{2} x-x \\sin x \\sec ^{2} x=x \\sec ^{2} x-x \\tan x \\sec x\\)\n\nNow, \\(I=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}} x \\sec ^{2} x d x-\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}} x \\sec x \\tan x d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\left[x \\tan x-\\int \\frac{d x}{d x} \\tan x d x\\right]_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}}-\\left[x \\sec x-\\int \\frac{d x}{d x} \\sec x d x\\right]_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}}\\)\n\n\\(=[x \\tan x-\\ln |\\sec x|]_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}}\\)\n\n\\(-[x \\sec x-\\ln |\\sec x+\\tan x|]_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}}+c\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\left\\{\\left[\\frac{3 \\pi}{4} \\tan \\frac{3 \\pi}{4}-\\ln \\left|\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}\\right|\\right.\\right.\\)\n\n\\(\\left.-\\left[\\frac{3 \\pi}{4} \\sec \\frac{3 \\pi}{4}-\\ln \\left|\\sec \\frac{3 \\pi}{4}+\\tan \\frac{3 \\pi}{4}\\right|\\right]\\right\\}\\)\n\n\\(-\\left\\{\\left[\\frac{\\pi}{4} \\tan \\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\ln \\left|\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right|\\right.\\right.\\)\n\n\\(\\left.-\\left[\\frac{\\pi}{4} \\sec \\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\ln \\left|\\sec \\frac{\\pi}{4}+\\tan \\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right|\\right]\\right\\}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\pi}{2}(\\sqrt{2}+1)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 10
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "question": "If \\(I_{1}=\\int_{0}^{1} e^{-x} \\cos ^{2} x d x ; I_{2}=\\int_{0}^{1} e^{-x^{2}} \\cos ^{2} x d x\\) and \\(I_{3}=\\int_{0}^{1} e^{-x^{3}} d x\\); then:",
        "options": [
            "\\(I_{2}>I_{3}>I_{1}\\)",
            "\\(I_{3}>I_{1}>I_{2}\\)",
            "\\(I_{2}>I_{1}>I_{3}\\)",
            "\\(I_{3}>I_{2}>I_{1}^{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Given:\n\n\n\\(I_{1}=\\int_{0}^{1} e^{-x} \\cos ^{2} x d x\\)\n\n\\(I_{2}=\\int_{0}^{1} e^{-x^{2}} \\cos ^{2} x d x\\) and\n\n\\(I_{3}=\\int_{0}^{1} e^{-x^{3}} d x\\)\n\nFor \\(x \\in(0,1)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow x>x^{2}\\) or \\(-x<-x^{2}\\)\n\nand \\(x^{2}>x^{3}\\) or \\(-x^{2}<-x^{3}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore e^{-x^{2}}<e^{-x^{3}}\\) and \\(e^{-x}<e^{-x^{2}}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow e^{-x}<e^{-x^{2}}<e^{-x^{3}}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow e^{-x^{3}}>e^{-x^{2}}>e^{-x}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I_{3}>I_{2}>I_{1}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 10
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{4} x\\left(1+\\log \\left(\\frac{2+\\sin x}{2-\\sin x}\\right)\\right) d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{3}{16} \\pi\\)",
            "0",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{8} \\pi\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{4}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Let\n\n\n\\(I=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{4} x\\left(1+\\log \\left(\\frac{2+\\sin x}{2-\\sin x}\\right)\\right) d x\\). \\(\\left.\\Rightarrow I=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{4}(-x)\\right)\\left(1+\\log \\left(\\frac{2+\\sin (-x)}{2-\\sin (-x)}\\right)\\right) \\cdot d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\left[\\because \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) \\cdot d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) \\cdot d x\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}\\left(\\sin ^{4} x\\right)\\left(1+\\log \\left(\\frac{2-\\sin x}{2+\\sin x}\\right)\\right) \\cdot d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{4} x\\left(1-\\log \\left(\\frac{2+\\sin x}{2-\\sin x}\\right)\\right) \\cdot d x\\)\n\nAfter adding equation (1) and (2) we get,\n\n\\(2 I=2 \\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{4} x \\cdot d x\\)\n\n\\(2 I=4 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{4} x \\cdot d x\\)\n\n\\(I=2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{4} x . d x=\\frac{2 \\times \\frac{3}{2} \\times \\frac{1}{2} \\times \\pi}{2 \\times 2}=\\frac{3 \\pi}{8}\\)\n\n[By Gamma function]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 10
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}} \\frac{d x}{1+\\cos x}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "-1",
            "-2",
            "2",
            "4"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}} \\frac{d x}{1+\\cos x}\\)\n\n\n\\(I=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}} \\frac{d x}{1-\\cos x}\\)\n\n\\(\\operatorname{Using} \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\)\n\nAdding (i) and (ii)\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}} \\frac{2}{\\sin ^{2} x} d x ; I=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}} \\operatorname{cosec}^{2} x d x\\)\n\n\\(I=-(\\cot x)_{\\pi / 4}^{3 \\pi / 4}=-\\left[\\cot \\frac{3 \\pi}{4}-\\cot \\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right]=2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 10
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "question": "Let \\(\\mathrm{I}_{n}=\\int \\tan ^{\\mathrm{n}} \\mathrm{xdx},(\\mathrm{n}>1) \\cdot \\mathrm{I}_{4}+\\mathrm{I}_{6}=\\mathrm{a}_{\\tan ^{5} \\mathrm{x}}+\\mathrm{bx}^{5}+\\mathrm{C}\\), where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is constant of integration, then the ordered pair \\((\\mathrm{a}, \\mathrm{b})\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\left(-\\frac{1}{5}, 0\\right)\\)",
            "\\(\\left(-\\frac{1}{5}, 1\\right)\\)",
            "\\(\\left(\\frac{1}{5}, 0\\right)\\)",
            "\\(\\left(\\frac{1}{5},-1\\right)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I_{n}=\\int \\tan ^{n} x d x, n>1\\)\n\n\nLet \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\mathrm{I}_{4}+\\mathrm{I}_{6}\\)\n\n\\(=\\int\\left(\\tan ^{4} x+\\tan ^{6} x\\right) d x=\\int \\tan ^{4} x \\sec ^{2} x d x\\)\n\nLet \\(\\tan x=t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\sec ^{2} \\mathrm{xdx}=\\mathrm{dt}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I=\\int t^{4} d t=\\frac{t^{5}}{5}+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{5} \\tan ^{5} x+C \\Rightarrow\\) On comparing, we have\n\n\\(\\mathrm{a}=\\frac{1}{5}, \\mathrm{~b}=0\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 10
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "question": "If \\(\\int_{1}^{2} \\frac{d x}{\\left(x^{2}-2 x+4\\right)^{\\frac{3}{2}}}=\\frac{k}{k+5}\\) then \\(k\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "2",
            "3",
            "4"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{1}^{2} \\frac{\\mathrm{dx}}{\\left((\\mathrm{x}-1 \\mathrm{a})^{2}+3\\right)^{3 / 2}}\\)\n\n\nLet; \\(\\mathrm{x}-1=\\sqrt{3} \\tan \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{dx}=\\sqrt{3} \\sec ^{2} \\cdot \\mathrm{d} \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 6} \\frac{\\sqrt{3} \\sec ^{2} \\theta \\mathrm{d} \\theta}{\\left((\\sqrt{3} \\tan \\theta)^{2}+(\\sqrt{3})^{2}\\right)^{3 / 2}}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{3} \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 6} \\frac{\\sec ^{2} \\theta}{\\sec ^{3} \\theta} \\mathrm{d} \\theta=\\frac{1}{3} \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 6} \\cos \\theta \\mathrm{d} \\theta\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{3}[\\sin \\theta]_{0}^{\\pi / 6}=\\frac{1}{3} \\times \\frac{1}{2}=\\frac{1}{6}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{6}=\\frac{k}{k+5} \\Rightarrow k+5=6 k\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow k=1\\)\n\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth, center]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-144}\\\\\n\\(=\\frac{1}{4} \\int_{\\pi / 12}^{\\pi / 4} \\sin 4 x \\cdot(1-\\cos 4 x) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{4}\\left[\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{12}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\sin 4 x-\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{12}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\sin 8 x\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{4}\\left[-\\frac{\\cos 4 x}{4}+\\frac{\\cos 8 x}{16}\\right]_{\\pi / 12}^{\\pi / 4}=\\frac{1}{4}\\left[\\frac{15}{32}\\right]=\\frac{15}{128}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 10
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{12}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{8 \\cos 2 x}{(\\tan x+\\cot x)^{3}} d x\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{15}{128}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{15}{64}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{13}{32}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{15}{256}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (a)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 11
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{2 x^{12}+5 x^{9}}{\\left(x^{5}+x^{3}+1\\right)^{3}} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{x^{5}}{2\\left(x^{5}+x^{3}+1\\right)^{2}}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{-x^{10}}{2\\left(x^{5}+x^{3}+1\\right)^{2}}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{-x^{5}}{\\left(x^{5}+x^{3}+1\\right)^{2}}+C\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{x^{10}}{2\\left(x^{5}+x^{3}+1\\right)^{2}}+C\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\int \\frac{2 x^{12}+5 x^{9}}{\\left(x^{5}+x^{3}+1\\right)^{3}} d x\\)\n\n\nDividing by \\(x^{15}\\) in numerator and denominator\n\n\\(\\int \\frac{\\frac{2}{x^{3}}+\\frac{5}{x^{6}} d x}{\\left(1+\\frac{1}{x^{2}}+\\frac{1}{x^{5}}\\right)^{3}}\\)\\\\\nLet \\(1+\\frac{1}{x^{2}}+\\frac{1}{x^{5}}=t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow\\left(\\frac{-2}{x^{3}}-\\frac{5}{x^{6}}\\right) d x=d t \\Rightarrow\\left(\\frac{2}{x^{3}}+\\frac{5}{x^{6}}\\right) d x=-d t\\)\n\nThis gives,\n\n\\(\\int \\frac{\\frac{2}{x^{3}}+\\frac{5}{x^{6}} d x}{\\left(1+\\frac{1}{x^{2}}+\\frac{1}{x^{5}}\\right)^{3}}=\\int \\frac{-d t}{t^{3}}=\\frac{1}{2 t^{2}}+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2\\left(1+\\frac{1}{x^{2}}+\\frac{1}{x^{5}}\\right)^{2}}+C=\\frac{x^{10}}{2\\left(x^{5}+x^{3}+1\\right)^{2}}+C\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "No answer provided",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 11
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "question": "For \\(x \\in R, x \\neq 0\\), if \\(y(x)\\) is a differentiable function such that \\(x \\int_{1}^{x} y(t) d t=(x+1) \\int_{1}^{x} t y(t) d t\\), then \\(y(x)\\) equals: (where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant)",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\mathrm{Cx}^{3} \\mathrm{e}^{\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{x}}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{C}{x^{2}} e^{-\\frac{1}{x}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{C}{x} e^{-\\frac{1}{x}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{C}{x^{3}} e^{-\\frac{1}{x}}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(x \\int_{1}^{x} y(t) d t=x \\int_{1}^{x} t y(t) d t+\\int_{1}^{x} t y(t) d t\\)\n\n\nDifferentiate w.r. to \\(x\\).\n\n\\(\\int_{1}^{x} y(t) d t+x[y(x)-y(1)]\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{1}^{x} t y(t) d t+x[x y(x)-y(1)]+x y(x)-y(1)\\)\n\n\\(\\int_{1}^{x} y(t) d t=\\int_{1}^{x} t y(t) d t+x^{2} y(x)-y(1)\\)\n\nDiff. again w.r. to \\(x\\)\n\n\\(y(x)-y(\\mathrm{a})=x y(x)-y(\\mathrm{a})+2 x y(x)+x^{2} y^{1}(x)\\)\n\n\\((1-3 x) y(x)=x^{2} y^{1}(x)\\)\n\n\\(\\frac{y^{1}(x)}{y(x)}=\\frac{1-3 x}{x^{2}}\\)\n\n\\(\\frac{1 d y}{y d x}=\\frac{1-3 x}{x^{2}} \\Rightarrow \\ln y=-\\frac{1}{x}-3 \\ln x\\)\n\n\\(\\ln \\left(y x^{3}\\right)=-\\frac{1}{x}\\)\n\n\\(y x^{3}=-e^{-1 / x}\\)\n\n\\(y=\\frac{e^{-\\frac{1}{x}}}{x^{3}}\\) or \\(y=\\frac{c e^{-\\frac{1}{x}}}{x^{3}}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 11
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int_{4}^{10} \\frac{\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x}{\\left[x^{2}-28 x+196\\right]+\\left[x^{2}\\right]}\\), where \\([x]\\) denotes the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(x\\), is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)",
            "6",
            "7",
            "3"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(I=\\int_{4}^{10} \\frac{\\left[x^{2}\\right]}{\\left[x^{2}-28 x+196\\right]+\\left[x^{2}\\right]} d x\\)\n\n\nUse \\(\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x\\)\\\\\n\\(I=\\int_{4}^{10} \\frac{\\left[(x-14)^{2}\\right]}{\\left[x^{2}\\right]+\\left[(x-14)^{2}\\right]} d x\\)\n\n(a) + (b)\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{4}^{10} \\frac{\\left[(x-14)^{2}\\right]+\\left[x^{2}\\right]}{\\left[x^{2}\\right]+\\left[(x-14)^{2}\\right]} d x\\)\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{4}^{10} d x \\Rightarrow 2 I=6 \\quad \\Rightarrow I=3\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 11
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "question": "If \\(2 \\int_{0}^{1} \\tan ^{-1} x d x=\\int_{0}^{1} \\cot ^{-1}\\left(1-x+x^{2}\\right) d x\\), then \\(\\int_{0}^{1} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(1-x+x^{2}\\right) d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}+\\log 2\\)",
            "\\(\\log 2\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\log 4\\)",
            "\\(\\log 4\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(2 \\int_{0}^{1} \\tan ^{-1} x d x=\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\tan ^{-1}\\left(1-x+x^{2}\\right)\\right) d x\\)\n\n\n\\(2 \\int_{0}^{1} \\tan ^{-1} x d x=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\pi}{2} d x-\\int_{0}^{1} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(1-x+x^{2}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\int_{0}^{1} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(1-x+x^{2}\\right) d x=\\frac{\\pi}{2}-2 \\int_{0}^{1} \\tan ^{-1} x d x\\)\n\nLet, \\(I_{1}=\\int_{0}^{1} \\tan ^{-1} x d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\left[\\left(\\tan ^{-1} x\\right) x\\right]_{0}^{1}-\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{1}{1+x^{2}} x d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{x}{1+x^{2}} d x=\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\frac{1}{2} \\log 2\\)\n\nBy equation (a)\n\n\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-2\\left[\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\frac{1}{2} \\log 2\\right]=\\log 2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 11
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{2}^{4} \\frac{\\log x^{2}}{\\log x^{2}+\\log \\left(36-12 x+x^{2}\\right)} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "6",
            "2",
            "4"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(I=\\int_{2}^{4} \\frac{\\log x^{2}}{\\log x^{2}+\\log \\left(36-12 x+x^{2}\\right)} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(I=\\int_{2}^{4} \\frac{\\log x^{2}}{\\log x^{2}+\\log (6-x)^{2}} d x\\).\n\n\\(I=\\int_{2}^{4} \\frac{\\log (6-x)^{2}}{\\log (6-x)^{2}+\\log x^{2}} d x\\)\n\nAdding (i) and (ii)\n\n\\(2 \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{2}^{4} \\mathrm{dx}=[\\mathrm{x}]_{2}^{4}=2\\)\n\n\\(I=1\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 11
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "question": "Let \\(\\mathrm{f}: \\mathrm{R} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{R}\\) be a function such that \\(\\mathrm{f}(2-x)=\\mathrm{f}(2+x)\\) and \\(\\mathrm{f}(4-x)=\\mathrm{f}(4+x)\\), for all \\(x \\in \\mathrm{R}\\) and \\(\\int_{0}^{2} f(x) d x=5\\). Then the value of \\(\\int_{10}^{50} f(x) d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "125",
            "80",
            "100",
            "200"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Let \\(f: R \\rightarrow R\\) be a function such that \\(f(2-x)=f(e+\\) \\(x)\\)\n\n\nPut \\(x=2+x\\) we get\n\n\\(f(-x)=f(4+x)=f(4-x)\\) \\(\\Rightarrow f(x)=f(x+4)\\)\n\nHence period is 4\n\nConsider \\(\\int_{10}^{50} f(x) d x=10 \\int_{10}^{14} f(x) d x=10[5+5]=100\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 11
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "question": "Let \\(\\mathrm{f}:(-1,1) \\rightarrow \\mathrm{R}\\) be a continuous function. If \\(\\int_{0}^{\\sin x} f(t) d t=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2} x\\), then \\(f\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\right)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{3}{2}}\\)",
            "\\(\\sqrt{3}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Let \\(\\mathrm{f}:(-1,1) \\rightarrow \\mathrm{R}\\) be a continuous function\n\n\nLet \\(\\int_{0}^{\\sin x} f(t) d t=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2} x\\)\n\n\\(f(\\sin x) \\cdot \\frac{d}{d x}(\\sin x)=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(\\sin x) \\cdot \\cos x=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\)\n\nput \\(\\mathrm{x}=\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{f}\\left(\\sin \\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right) \\cdot \\cos \\frac{\\pi}{3}=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{f}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\right) \\cdot \\frac{1}{2}=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{f}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\right)=\\sqrt{3}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 11
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "question": "For \\(x>0\\), let \\(f(x)=\\int_{1}^{\\mathrm{x}} \\frac{\\log \\mathrm{t}}{1+\\mathrm{t}} \\mathrm{dt}\\). Then \\(f(x)+f\\left(\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{x}}\\right)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{4}(\\log x)^{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\log x\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}(\\log x)^{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{4} \\log \\mathrm{x}^{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(f\\left(\\frac{1}{x}\\right)=\\int_{1}^{1 / x} \\frac{\\ln t}{1+t} d t\\)\n\n\nLet \\(\\mathrm{t}=\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{Z}}\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{dt}=-\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{z}^{2}} \\mathrm{dz}\\)\n\n\\(f(x)=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{\\ln z}{z(z+1)} d z\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{f}(\\mathrm{x})+\\mathrm{f}\\left(\\frac{1}{x}\\right)=\\int_{1}^{\\mathrm{x}} \\frac{\\ln x}{z} d z=\\left[\\frac{(\\ln z)^{2}}{2}\\right]_{1}^{x}=\\frac{(\\ln x)^{2}}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 11
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\sqrt{1+4 \\sin ^{2} \\frac{x}{2}-4 \\sin \\frac{x}{2}} d x\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "\\(4 \\sqrt{3}-4\\)",
            "\\(4 \\sqrt{3}-4-\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\)",
            "\\(\\pi-4\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{2 \\pi}{3}-4-4 \\sqrt{3}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) Let \\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\sqrt{1+4 \\sin ^{2} \\frac{x}{2}-4 \\sin \\frac{x}{2}} d x=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}\\left|2 \\sin \\frac{x}{2}-1\\right| d x\\)\n\n\n\\[\n=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 3}\\left(1-2 \\sin \\frac{x}{2}\\right) d x+\\int_{\\pi / 3}^{\\pi}\\left(2 \\sin \\frac{x}{2}-1\\right) d x\n\\]\n\n\\(\\left[\\because \\sin \\frac{x}{2}=\\frac{1}{2} \\Rightarrow \\frac{x}{2}=\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right.\\)\n\n\\[\n\\left.\\Rightarrow x=\\frac{\\pi}{3}, \\frac{x}{2}=\\frac{5 \\pi}{6} \\Rightarrow x=\\frac{5 \\pi}{3}>\\pi\\right]\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\left[x+4 \\cos \\frac{x}{2}\\right]_{0}^{\\pi / 3}+\\left[-4 \\cos \\frac{x}{2}-x\\right]_{\\pi / 3}^{\\pi} \\\\\n& =\\frac{\\pi}{3}+4 \\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}-4+\\left(0-\\pi+4 \\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right) \\\\\n& =4 \\sqrt{3}-4-\\frac{\\pi}{3}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 11
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "question": "Let function \\(F\\) be defined as \\(F(x)=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{e^{t}}{t} d t, x>0\\) then the value of the integral \\(\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{e^{t}}{t+a} d t\\), where \\(a>0\\), is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\mathrm{e}^{\\mathrm{a}}[\\mathrm{F}(\\mathrm{x})-\\mathrm{F}(1+\\mathrm{a})]\\)",
            "\\(\\mathrm{e}^{-\\mathrm{a}}[\\mathrm{F}(\\mathrm{x}+\\mathrm{a})-\\mathrm{F}(\\mathrm{a})]\\)",
            "\\(\\mathrm{e}^{\\mathrm{a}}[\\mathrm{F}(\\mathrm{x}+\\mathrm{a})-\\mathrm{F}(1+\\mathrm{a})]\\)",
            "\\(\\mathrm{e}^{-\\mathrm{a}}[\\mathrm{F}(\\mathrm{x}+\\mathrm{a})-\\mathrm{F}(1+\\mathrm{a})]\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\mathrm{F}(x)=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{e^{t}}{t} d t, x>0\\)\n\n\nLet \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{e^{t}}{t+a} d t\\)\n\nPut \\(t+a=z \\Rightarrow t=z-a ; d t=d z\\)\n\nfor \\(t=1, z=1+a\\)\n\nfor \\(t=x, z=x+a\\)\n\n\\[\n\\therefore \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{1+a}^{x+a} \\frac{e^{z-a}}{z} d z\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =e^{-a} \\int_{1+a}^{x+a} \\frac{e^{z}}{z} d z \\equiv e^{-a} \\int_{1+a}^{x+a} \\frac{e^{t}}{t} d t \\\\\n& \\mathrm{I}=e^{-a}\\left[\\int_{1+a}^{1} \\frac{e^{t}}{t} d t+\\int_{1}^{x+a} \\frac{e^{t}}{t} d t\\right] \\\\\n& =e^{-a}\\left[-\\int_{1}^{1+a} \\frac{e^{t}}{t} d t+\\int_{1}^{x+a} \\frac{e^{t}}{t} d t\\right] \\\\\n& =e^{-a}[-F(1+a)+F(x+a)]\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n(By the definition of \\(\\mathrm{F}(\\mathrm{x})\\) )\n\n\\(=e^{-a}[F(x+a)-F(1+a)]\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 12
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "question": "If for a continuous function \\(f(x), \\int_{-\\pi}^{t}(f(x)+x) d x=\\pi^{2}-t^{2}\\), for all \\(t \\geq-\\pi\\), then \\(f\\left(-\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\pi\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let \\(\\int_{-\\pi}^{t}(f(x)+x) d x=\\pi^{2}-t^{2}\\)\n\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\Rightarrow \\int_{-\\pi}^{t} f(x) d x+\\int_{-\\pi}^{t} x d x=\\pi^{2}-t^{2} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\int_{-\\pi}^{t} f(x) d x+\\left(\\frac{t^{2}}{2}-\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{2}\\right)=\\pi^{2}-t^{2} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\int_{-\\pi}^{t} f(x) d x=\\frac{3}{2}\\left(\\pi^{2}-t^{2}\\right)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\ndifferentiating with respect to \\(t\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\frac{d}{d t}\\left[\\int_{-\\pi}^{t} f(x) d x\\right]=\\frac{3}{2} \\frac{d}{d t}\\left(\\pi^{2}-t^{2}\\right) \\\\\n& f(t) \\cdot \\frac{d t}{d t}-f(-\\pi) \\frac{d}{d t}(-\\pi)=-3 t \\\\\n& f(t)=-3 t \\\\\n& f\\left(-\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)=-3\\left(-\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)=\\pi\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 12
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "question": "If [ ] denotes the greatest integer function, then the integral \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi}[\\cos x] d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
            "0",
            "-1",
            "\\(-\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Let \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}[\\cos x] d x\\)\n\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}[\\cos (\\pi-x)] d x=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}[-\\cos x] d x\\)\n\nOn adding (1) and (2), we get\n\n\\(2 \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}[\\cos x] d x+\\int_{0}^{\\pi}[-\\cos x] d x\\)\n\n\\(2 \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}[\\cos x]+[-\\cos x] d x\\)\n\n\\(2 \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}-1 d x \\quad(\\because[x]+[-x]=-1 \\quad\\) if \\(x \\notin Z)\\)\n\n\\(2 \\mathrm{I}=-\\left.x\\right|_{0} ^{\\pi}=-\\pi\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I}=\\frac{-\\pi}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 12
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "question": "If for \\(\\mathrm{n} \\geq 1, P_{n}=\\int_{1}^{e}(\\log x)^{n} d x\\), then \\(P_{10}-90 P_{8}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "-9",
            "\\(10 \\mathrm{e}\\)",
            "\\(-9 \\mathrm{e}\\)",
            "10"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(\\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{n}}=\\int_{1}^{e}(\\log x)^{n} d x\\)\n\n\nput \\(\\log x=t\\) then \\(x=e^{t}\\) and \\(d x=e^{t} d t\\)\n\nAlso, when \\(x=1\\), then \\(t=\\log 1=0\\)\n\nand when \\(x=e\\), then \\(t=\\log _{e} e=1\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{n}}=\\int_{0}^{1} t^{n} \\cdot e^{t} d t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\mathrm{P}_{10}=\\int_{0}^{1} t^{10} e^{t} d t\\) and \\(\\mathrm{P}_{8}=\\int_{0}^{1} t^{8} e^{t} d t\\)\n\nNow, \\(\\mathrm{P}_{10}-90 \\mathrm{P}_{8}=\\int_{0}^{1} t_{\\mathrm{I}}^{10} e_{\\text {II }}^{t} d t-90 \\int_{0}^{1} t^{8} e^{t} d t\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{P}_{10}-90 \\mathrm{P}_{8}=\\left[t^{10} e^{t}\\right]_{0}^{1}-10 \\int_{0}^{1} t^{9} e^{t} d t-90 \\int_{0}^{1} t^{8} e^{t} d t\\) \\(\\mathrm{P}_{10}-90 \\mathrm{P}_{8}\\)\n\n\\(=e-10\\left[t^{9} \\int_{0}^{1} e^{t} d t-\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d}{d t}\\left(t^{9}\\right) \\int e^{t} d t\\right]-90 \\int_{0}^{1} t^{8} e^{t} d t\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{P}_{10}-90 \\mathrm{P}_{8}=e-10\\left[e-9 \\int_{0}^{1} t^{8} e^{t} d t\\right]-90 \\int_{0}^{1} t^{8} e^{t} d t\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{P}_{10}-90 \\mathrm{P}_{8}=e-10 e+90 \\int t^{8} \\mathcal{e}^{t} d t-90 \\int_{0}^{1} t^{8} \\mathcal{e}^{t} d t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore P_{10}-90 P_{8}=-9 e\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 12
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{0}^{\\frac{1}{2}} \\frac{\\ln (1+2 x)}{1+4 x^{2}} d x\\), equals:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4} \\ln 2\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{8} \\ln 2\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{16} \\ln 2\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{32} \\ln 2\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Let \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{1 / 2} \\frac{\\ln (1+2 x)}{1+4 x^{2}} d x\\) or \\(\\int_{0}^{1 / 2} \\frac{\\ln (1+2 x)}{1+(2 x)^{2}} d x\\)\n\n\nPut \\(2 x=\\tan \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\frac{2 d x}{d \\theta}=\\sec ^{2} \\theta\\) or \\(d x=\\frac{\\sec ^{2} \\theta d \\theta}{2}\\)\\\\\nalso when \\(x=0 \\Rightarrow \\theta=0\\)\n\nand when \\(x=\\frac{1}{2} \\Rightarrow \\theta=45^{\\circ}\\) or \\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{\\ln (1+\\tan \\theta)}{1+\\tan ^{2} \\theta} \\times \\frac{\\sec ^{2} \\theta d \\theta}{2}\\)\n\n\\(I=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{\\ln (1+\\tan \\theta)}{1+\\tan ^{2} \\theta} \\times \\sec ^{2} \\theta d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\left(\\because 1+\\tan ^{2} \\theta=\\sec ^{2} \\theta\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\ln (1+\\tan \\theta) d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\ln \\left[1+\\tan \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\theta\\right)\\right] d \\theta\\)\n\n(Using the property of definite integral)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\ln \\left[1+\\frac{\\tan \\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\tan \\theta}{1+\\tan \\frac{\\pi}{4} \\times \\tan \\theta}\\right] d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\ln \\left[1+\\frac{1-\\tan \\theta}{1+\\tan \\theta}\\right] d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\ln \\left[\\frac{1+\\tan \\theta+1-\\tan \\theta}{1+\\tan \\theta}\\right] d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\ln \\left[\\frac{2}{1+\\tan \\theta}\\right] d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}[\\ln 2-\\ln (1+\\tan \\theta)] d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\ln 2 . d \\theta-\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\ln (1+\\tan \\theta) d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(I=\\left.\\frac{1}{2} \\ln 2 \\theta\\right|_{0} ^{\\pi / 4}-I\\)\n\n(from eq. (i))\n\n\\(I+I=\\frac{1}{2} \\ln 2\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-0\\right)\\)\n\n\\(2 \\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{2} \\times \\frac{\\pi}{4} \\times \\ln 2\\)\n\n\\(2 \\mathrm{I}=\\frac{\\pi}{8} \\ln 2\\) or \\(I=\\frac{\\pi}{16} \\ln 2\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 12
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "question": "The intercepts on \\(x\\)-axis made by tangents to the curve, \\(y=\\int_{0}^{x}|t| d t, x \\in \\mathrm{R}\\), which are parallel to the line \\(y=2 x\\), are equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\pm 1\\)",
            "\\(\\pm 2\\)",
            "\\(\\pm 3\\)",
            "\\(\\pm 4\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (a) Since, \\(y=\\int_{0}^{x}|t| d t, x \\in R\\)\n\ntherefore \\(\\frac{d y}{d x}=|x|\\)\n\nBut from \\(y=2 x, \\quad \\therefore \\frac{d y}{d x}=2\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow|x|=2 \\quad \\Rightarrow \\quad x= \\pm 2\\)\n\nPoints \\(y=\\int_{0}^{ \\pm 2}|t| d t= \\pm 2\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore\\) Equation of tangent is\n\n\\[\ny-2=2(x-2) \\text { or } y+2=2(x+2)\n\\]\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow x\\)-intercept \\(= \\pm 1\\).",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 12
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "question": "Statement-1 : The value of the integral \\(\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{d x}{1+\\sqrt{\\tan x}} \\text { is equal to } \\pi / 6\\). Statement-2 : \\(\\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\).",
        "options": [
            "Statement-1 is true; Statement-2 is true; Statement-2 is a correct explanation for Statement-1",
            "Statement-1 is true; Statement-2 is true; Statement-2 is not a correct explanation for Statement-1.",
            "Statement-1 is true; Statement-2 is false.",
            "Statement-1 is false; Statement-2 is true."
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Let, \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{d x}{1+\\sqrt{\\tan x}}\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{d x}{1+\\sqrt{\\tan \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-x\\right)}}=\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{\\sqrt{\\tan x} d x}{1+\\sqrt{\\tan x}}\\)\n\nAlso, given\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{\\sqrt{\\tan x} d x}{1+\\sqrt{\\tan x}}\\)\n\nBy adding (i) and (ii), we get\n\n\\(2 \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I}=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\frac{\\pi}{3}-\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right]=\\frac{\\pi}{12}\\),\n\nStatement-1 is false\n\n\\(\\because \\quad \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\)\n\nIt is fundamental property.\n\nStatement -2 is true.",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 12
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "question": "For \\(0 \\leq x \\leq \\frac{\\pi}{2}\\), the value of \\(\\int_{0}^{\\sin ^{2} x} \\sin ^{-1}(\\sqrt{t}) d t+\\int_{0}^{\\cos ^{2} x} \\cos ^{-1}(\\sqrt{t}) d t\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)",
            "0",
            "1",
            "\\(-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Consider\n\n\n\\[\n\\int_{0}^{\\sin ^{2} x} \\sin ^{-1}(\\sqrt{t}) d t+\\int_{0}^{\\cos ^{2} x} \\cos ^{-1}(\\sqrt{t}) d t\n\\]\n\nLet \\(\\mathrm{I}=f(x)\\) after integrating and putting the limits.\n\n\\(f^{\\prime}(x)=\\sin ^{-1} \\sqrt{\\sin ^{2} x}(2 \\sin x \\cos x)-0\\)\n\n\\[\n+\\cos ^{-1} \\sqrt{\\cos ^{2} x}(-2 \\cos x \\sin x)-0\n\\]\n\n\\(\\therefore f^{\\prime}(x)=0 \\Rightarrow f(x)=\\mathrm{C} \\quad\\) (constant)\n\nNow, we find \\(f(x)\\) at \\(x=\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{1 / 2} \\sin ^{-1} \\sqrt{t} d t+\\int_{0}^{1 / 2} \\cos ^{-1} \\sqrt{t} d t\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\quad \\int_{0}^{1 / 2}\\left(\\sin ^{-1} \\sqrt{t}+\\cos ^{-1} \\sqrt{t}\\right) d t=\\int_{0}^{1 / 2} \\frac{\\pi}{2} d t=\\frac{\\pi}{4}=\\mathrm{C} \\\\\n\\therefore & f(x)=\\frac{\\pi}{4} \\\\\n\\therefore & \\text { Required integration }=\\frac{\\pi}{4}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 12
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{1+2^{x}} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\pi\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
            "4 \\pi",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{1+2^{x}} d x\\)\n\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{1+2^{-x}} d x \\text {, by replacing } x \\text { by }\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\frac{\\pi}{2}-x\\right) \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{2^{x} \\cdot \\sin ^{2} x}{1+2^{x}} d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nAdding equations (i) and (ii), we get\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n2 \\mathrm{I} & =\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin ^{2} x d x=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2}(1-\\cos 2 x) d x \\\\\n\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I} & =\\frac{1}{4}\\left[x+\\frac{\\sin 2 x}{2}\\right]_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{4}\\left[\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}+\\frac{\\sin \\pi}{2}\\right)-\\left(-\\frac{\\pi}{2}+\\frac{\\sin (-\\pi)}{2}\\right)\\right] \\\\\n\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I} & =\\frac{1}{4}\\left[\\frac{\\pi}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\right]=\\frac{\\pi}{4}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 12
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int_{7 \\pi / 4}^{7 \\pi / 3} \\sqrt{\\tan ^{2} x} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\log 2 \\sqrt{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\log 2\\)",
            "\\(2 \\log 2\\)",
            "\\(\\log \\sqrt{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Let \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{7 \\pi / 4}^{7 \\pi / 3} \\sqrt{\\tan ^{2} x} d x\\) \\(=\\int_{7 \\pi / 4}^{7 \\pi / 3} \\tan x d x=-\\left.\\log \\cos x\\right|_{7 \\pi / 4} ^{7 \\pi / 3}\\) \\(=-\\left[\\log \\cos \\frac{7 \\pi}{3}-\\log \\cos \\frac{7 \\pi}{4}\\right]\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\log \\cos \\frac{7 \\pi}{4}-\\log \\cos \\frac{7 \\pi}{3}\\)\n\n\\(=\\log \\left[\\frac{\\cos \\frac{7 \\pi}{4}}{\\cos \\frac{7 \\pi}{3}}\\right]=\\log \\left[\\frac{\\cos \\left(2 \\pi-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)}{\\cos \\left(2 \\pi+\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)}\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\log \\left(\\frac{\\cos \\frac{\\pi}{4}}{\\cos \\frac{\\pi}{3}}\\right)=\\log \\left(\\frac{\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}}{\\frac{1}{2}}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=\\log \\left(\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{2}}\\right)=\\log \\sqrt{2}\\).\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 12
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "question": "If \\(x=\\int_{0}^{y} \\frac{d t}{\\sqrt{1+t^{2}}}\\), then \\(\\frac{d^{2} y}{d x^{2}}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(y\\)",
            "\\(\\sqrt{1+y^{2}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{x}{\\sqrt{1+y^{2}}}\\)",
            "\\(y^{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (a) \\(x=\\int_{0}^{y} \\frac{d t}{\\sqrt{1+t^{2}}}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 1=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{1+y^{2}}} \\cdot \\frac{d y}{d x}\\)\n\n\\(\\left[\\because\\right.\\) If \\(\\mathrm{I}(x)=\\int_{\\phi(x)}^{\\psi(x)} f(t) d t\\), then \\(\\frac{d \\mathrm{I}(x)}{d x}=f\\{\\psi(x)\\}\\).\n\n\\[\n\\left.\\left\\{\\frac{d}{d x} \\psi(x)\\right\\}-f\\{\\phi(x)\\} \\cdot\\left\\{\\frac{d}{d x} \\phi(x)\\right\\}\\right]\n\\]\n\n\\(\\frac{d y}{d x}=\\sqrt{1-y^{2}}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{d^{2} y}{d x^{2}}=\\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{1+y^{2}}} \\cdot 2 y \\cdot \\frac{d y}{d x}=\\frac{y}{\\sqrt{1+y^{2}}} \\cdot \\sqrt{1+y^{2}}=y\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "question": "If \\(g(x)=\\int_{0}^{x} \\cos 4 t d t\\), then \\(g(x+\\pi)\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{g(x)}{g(\\pi)}\\)",
            "\\(g(x)+g(\\pi)\\)",
            "\\(\\mathrm{g}(x)-\\mathrm{g}(\\pi)\\)",
            "\\(\\mathrm{g}(x) \\cdot g(\\pi)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b, c) \\(g(x+\\pi)=\\int_{0}^{x+\\pi} \\cos 4 t d t\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{x} \\cos 4 t d t+\\int_{x}^{\\pi+x} \\cos 4 t d t=g(x)+\\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\cos 4 t d t\\)\n\n(it is clear from graph of \\(\\cos 4 t\\) )\n\n\\(\\int_{x}^{\\pi+x} \\cos 4 t d t=\\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\cos 4 t d t=\\mathrm{g}(x)+\\mathrm{g}(\\pi)=\\mathrm{g}(x)-\\mathrm{g}(\\pi)\\)\n\n\\((\\because\\) From graph of \\(\\cos 4 \\mathrm{t}, \\mathrm{g}(\\pi)=0\\) )",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "No answer provided",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "question": "If \\([x]\\) is the greatest integer \\(\\leq x\\), then the value of the integral \\(\\int_{-0.9}^{0.9}\\left(\\left[x^{2}\\right]+\\log \\left(\\frac{2-x}{2+x}\\right)\\right) d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "0.486",
            "0.243",
            "1.8",
            "0"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\int_{-0.9}^{0.9}\\left\\{\\left[x^{2}\\right]+\\log \\left(\\frac{2-x}{2+x}\\right)\\right\\} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{-0.9}^{0.9}\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x+\\int_{-0.9}^{0.9} \\log \\left(\\frac{2-x}{2+x}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=0+\\int_{-0.9}^{0.9} \\log \\left(\\frac{2-x}{2+x}\\right) d x\\)\n\nPut \\(x=-x \\Rightarrow f(x)=\\log \\frac{2-x}{2+x}\\)\n\nand \\(f(-x)=\\log \\frac{2+x}{2-x}=-\\log \\frac{(2-x)}{2+x}=-f(x)\\)\n\nSo, it is an odd function, hence Required integral \\(=0\\).",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int_{0}^{0.9}[x-2[x]] d x\\), where [.] denotes the greatest integer function is:",
        "options": [
            "0.9",
            "1.8",
            "-0.9",
            "0"
        ],
        "solution": "(d) Since \\(\\int_{0}^{a}[x]=0\\) where \\(0 \\leq a \\leq 1\\)\\ \\(\\therefore \\int_{0}^{0.9}[x-2[x]] d x=0\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "question": "If \\(\\frac{d}{d x} G(x)=\\frac{e^{\\tan x}}{x}, x \\in(0, \\pi / 2)\\), then \\(\\int_{1 / 4}^{1 / 2} \\frac{2}{x} \\cdot e^{\\tan \\left(\\pi \\mathrm{x}^{2}\\right)} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(G(\\pi / 4)-G(\\pi / 16)\\)",
            "\\(2[G(\\pi / 4)-G(\\pi / 16)]\\)",
            "\\(\\pi[G(1 / 2)-G(1 / 4)]\\)",
            "\\(G(1 / \\sqrt{2})-G(1 / 2)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let \\(\\frac{d}{d x} G(x)=\\frac{e^{\\tan x}}{x}, x \\in\\left(0, \\frac{\\pi}{2}\\right)\\)\n\n\nNow, \\(I=\\int_{1 / 4}^{1 / 2} \\frac{2}{x} e^{\\tan \\pi x^{2}} \\cdot d x=\\int_{1 / 4}^{1 / 2} \\frac{2 \\pi x}{\\pi x^{2}} e^{\\tan \\pi x^{2}} . d x\\)\n\nLet \\(\\pi x^{2}=t \\Rightarrow 2 \\pi x d x=d t\\)\n\nWhen \\(x=\\frac{1}{2}, t=\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\) and \\(x=\\frac{1}{4}, t=\\frac{\\pi}{16}\\)\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-149}\n\\end{center}",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "question": "If \\(\\int_{e}^{x} t f(t) d t=\\sin x-x \\cos x-\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\), for all \\(x \\in R-\\{0\\}\\), then the value of \\(f\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(1 / 2\\)",
            "1",
            "0",
            "\\(-1 / 2\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Let \\(\\int_{e}^{x} t f(t) d t=\\sin x-x \\cos x-\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\)\n\n\nBy using Leibnitz rule, we get\n\n\\[\n\\frac{d}{d x}\\left[\\int_{e}^{x} t f(t) d t\\right]=\\frac{d}{d x}\\left[\\sin x-x \\cos x-\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\right]\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\Rightarrow x f(x)-e f(e) \\cdot 0=x \\sin x-x\n\\]\n\nNow, put \\(x=\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\), we get\n\n\\(\\frac{\\pi}{6} \\cdot f\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)=\\frac{\\pi}{6} \\cdot \\sin \\frac{\\pi}{6}-\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)=\\sin \\frac{\\pi}{6}-1=\\frac{1}{2}-1=-\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "question": "Let [.] denote the greatest integer function then the value of \\(\\int_{0}^{1.5} x\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "0",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{5}{4}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(\\int_{0}^{1.5} x\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x=\\int_{0}^{1} x\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x+\\int_{1}^{\\sqrt{2}} x\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x+\\int_{\\sqrt{2}}^{1.5} x\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x\\) \\(=\\int_{0}^{1} x .0 d x+\\int_{1}^{\\sqrt{2}} x d x+\\int_{\\sqrt{2}}^{1.5} 2 x d x=0+\\left[\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\right]_{1}^{\\sqrt{2}}+\\left[x^{2}\\right]_{\\sqrt{2}}^{1.5}\\) \\(=\\frac{1}{2}(2-1)+(2.25-2)=\\frac{1}{2}+0.25\\) \\(=\\frac{1}{2}+\\frac{1}{4}=\\frac{3}{4}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{8 \\log (1+x)}{1+x^{2}} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{8} \\log 2\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2} \\log 2\\)",
            "\\(\\log 2\\)",
            "\\(\\pi \\log 2\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (d) \\(I=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{8 \\log (1+x)}{1+x^{2}} d x\\)\n\n\n\nPut \\(x=\\tan \\theta\\),\n\n\\(\\therefore d x=\\sec ^{2} \\theta d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I=8 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 4} \\frac{\\log (1+\\tan \\theta)}{1+\\tan ^{2} \\theta} \\cdot \\sec ^{2} \\theta d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(I=8 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 4} \\log (1+\\tan \\theta) d \\theta\\)\\\\\nApplying \\(\\int_{0}^{a} f(x) d x=\\int_{0}^{a} f(a-x) d x\\)\n\n\\(=8 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 4} \\log \\left[1+\\tan \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\theta\\right)\\right] d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(=8 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 4} \\log \\left[1+\\frac{1-\\tan \\theta}{1+\\tan \\theta}\\right] d \\theta=8 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 4} \\log \\left[\\frac{2}{1+\\tan \\theta}\\right] d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(=8 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 4}[\\log 2-\\log (1+\\tan \\theta)] d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(=8 \\log 2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi 14} 1 d \\theta-8 \\int_{0}^{\\pi 14} \\log (1+\\tan \\theta) \\mathrm{d} \\theta\\)\n\n\\[\n\\mathrm{I}=8 \\cdot(\\log 2)[x]_{0}^{\\pi / 4}-8 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 4} \\log (1+\\tan \\theta) d \\theta\n\\]\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=8 \\cdot \\frac{\\pi}{4} \\cdot \\log 2-\\mathrm{I}\\)\n\n[From equation (i)]\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{I}=2 \\pi \\log 2\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad \\mathrm{I}=\\pi \\log 2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "question": "Let \\(p(x)\\) be a function defined on \\(\\mathbf{R}\\) such that \\(p^{\\prime}(x)=p^{\\prime}(1-x)\\), for all \\(x \\in[0,1], p(0)=1\\) and \\(p(1)=41\\). Then \\(\\int_{0}^{1} p(x) d x\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "21",
            "41",
            "42",
            "\\(\\sqrt{41}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(p^{\\prime}(x)=p^{\\prime}(1-x)\\)\n\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\quad p(x)=-p(1-x)+c\\)\n\nat \\(x=0\\)\n\n\\(p(0)=-p(1)+c \\Rightarrow 42=c\\)\n\nNow, \\(p(x)=-p(1-x)+42\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow p(x)+p(1-x)=42\\)\n\nLet \\(I=\\int_{0}^{1} p(x) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int_{0}^{1} p(1-x) d x\\)\n\nAdding eqn. (i) and (ii),\n\n\\[\n2 I=\\int_{0}^{1}(42) d x \\Rightarrow I=21\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "question": "\\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi} [\\cot x] d x\\), where \\([.]\\) denotes the greatest integer function, is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "-1",
            "\\(-\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Let \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}[\\cot x] d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}[\\cot (\\pi-x)] d x=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}[-\\cot x] d x\\)\n\nAdding eq \\({ }^{\\mathrm{n}} \\mathrm{s}\\) (i) \\& (ii),\n\nWe get\n\n\\(2 \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}([\\cot x]+[-\\cot x]) d x\\) \\(=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}(-1) d x\\)\n\n\\([\\because[x]+[-x]=-1\\), if \\(x \\notin z\\) and \\([x]+[-x]=0\\), if \\(x \\in z]\\)\n\n\\(=[-x]_{0}^{\\pi}=-\\pi \\quad \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I}=-\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 13
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "question": "Let \\(I=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\sin x}{\\sqrt{x}} d x\\) and \\(J=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\cos x}{\\sqrt{x}} d x\\). Then which one of the following is true?",
        "options": [
            "I \\(>\\frac{2}{3}\\) and J \\(>2\\)",
            "I \\(<\\frac{2}{3}\\) and J \\(<2\\)",
            "I \\(<\\frac{2}{3}\\) and J \\(>2\\)",
            "I \\(>\\frac{2}{3}\\) and J \\(<2\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) We know that \\(\\frac{\\sin x}{x}<1\\), for \\(\\mathrm{x} \\in(0,1)\\)\n\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{\\sin x}{\\sqrt{x}}<\\sqrt{x}\\) on \\(\\mathrm{x} \\in(0,1)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\sin x}{\\sqrt{x}} d x<\\int_{0}^{1} \\sqrt{x} d x=\\left[\\frac{2 x^{3 / 2}}{3}\\right]_{0}^{1}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\sin x}{\\sqrt{x}} d x<\\frac{2}{3} \\Rightarrow I<\\frac{2}{3}\\)\n\nAlso \\(\\frac{\\cos x}{\\sqrt{x}}<\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{x}} \\quad\\) for \\(x \\in(0,1)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\cos x}{\\sqrt{x}} d x<\\int_{0}^{1} x^{-1 / 2} d x=[2 \\sqrt{x}]_{0}^{1}=2\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\cos x}{\\sqrt{x}} d x<2 \\Rightarrow J<2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 14
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "question": "The solution for \\(x\\) of the equation \\(\\int_{\\sqrt{2}}^{x} \\frac{d t}{t \\sqrt{t^{2}-1}}=\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\)",
            "\\(2 \\sqrt{2}\\)",
            "2",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\int_{\\sqrt{2}}^{x} \\frac{d t}{t \\sqrt{t^{2}-1}}=\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)\n\n\n\\(\\therefore\\left[\\sec ^{-1} t\\right]_{\\sqrt{2}}^{x}=\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\left[\\because \\int \\frac{d x}{x \\sqrt{x^{2}-1}}=\\sec ^{-1} x\\right]\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\sec ^{-1} x-\\sec ^{-1} \\sqrt{2}=\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\sec ^{-1} x-\\frac{\\pi}{4}=\\frac{\\pi}{2} \\Rightarrow \\sec ^{-1} x=\\frac{\\pi}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\sec ^{-1} x=\\frac{3 \\pi}{4} \\Rightarrow x=\\sec \\frac{3 \\pi}{4}=\\sec \\left(\\pi-\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow x=-\\sec \\frac{\\pi}{4} \\Rightarrow x=-\\sqrt{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 14
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "question": "Let \\(F(x)=f(x)+f\\left(\\frac{1}{x}\\right)\\), where \\(f(x)=\\int_{l}^{x} \\frac{\\log t}{1+t} d t\\), Then \\(F(e)\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "2",
            "\\(1 / 2\\)",
            "0"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) Given that \\(F(x)=f(x)+f\\left(\\frac{1}{x}\\right)\\), where\n\n\n\\(f(x)=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{\\log t}{1+t} d t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore F(e)=f(e)+f\\left(\\frac{1}{e}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow F(e)=\\int_{1}^{e} \\frac{\\log t}{1+t} d t+\\int_{1}^{1 / e} \\frac{\\log t}{1+t} d t\\)\n\nLet \\(I=\\int_{1}^{1 / e} \\frac{\\log t}{1+t} d t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad\\) Put \\(\\frac{1}{t}=z \\Rightarrow-\\frac{1}{t^{2}} d t=d z \\Rightarrow d t=-\\frac{d z}{z^{2}}\\)\n\nwhen \\(t=1 \\Rightarrow z=1\\) and when \\(t=1 / e\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow z=e\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\quad I=\\int_{1}^{e} \\frac{\\log \\left(\\frac{1}{z}\\right)}{1+\\frac{1}{z}}\\left(-\\frac{d z}{z^{2}}\\right)\\) \\(=\\int_{1}^{e} \\frac{(\\log 1-\\log z) \\cdot z}{z+1}\\left(-\\frac{d z}{z^{2}}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{1}^{e}-\\frac{\\log z}{(z+1)}\\left(-\\frac{d z}{z}\\right)\\)\n\n\\([\\because \\log 1=0]\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{1}^{e} \\frac{\\log z}{z(z+1)} d z\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I=\\int_{1}^{e} \\frac{\\log t}{t(t+1)} d t\\)\n\n[By property \\(\\int_{a}^{b} f(t) d t=\\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x\\) ]\n\nNow from eqn. (1)\n\n\\(F(e)=\\int_{1}^{e} \\frac{\\log t}{1+t} d t+\\int_{1}^{e} \\frac{\\log t}{t(1+t)} d t\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{1}^{e} \\frac{t \\cdot \\log t+\\log t}{t(1+t)} d t=\\int_{1}^{e} \\frac{(\\log t)(t+1)}{t(1+t)} d t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow F(e)=\\int_{1}^{e} \\frac{\\log t}{t} d t\\)\n\nLet \\(\\log t=x \\quad \\therefore \\frac{1}{t} d t=d x\\)\n\n[when \\(t=1, x=0\\) and when \\(t=e, x=\\log e=1\\) ]\n\n\\(\\therefore F(e)=\\int_{0}^{1} x d x \\quad F(e)=\\left[\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\right]_{0}^{1}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow F(e)=\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 14
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{1}^{a}[x] f^{\\prime}(x) d x, a>1\\) where \\([x]\\) denotes the greatest integer not exceeding \\(x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(a f(a)-\\{f(1)+f(2)+\\ldots \\ldots \\ldots \\ldots . . . . . . .[a])\\}\\)",
            "\\([a] f(a)-\\{f(1)+f(2)+\\ldots f([a])\\}\\)",
            "\\([a] f([a])-\\{f(1)+f(2)+\\ldots f(a)\\}\\)",
            "\\(a f([a])-\\{f(1)+f(2)+f(a)\\}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) Let \\(a=k+h\\) where \\(\\mathrm{k}\\) is an integer such that and \\(0 \\leq h<1\\)\n\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow[a]=k\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\int_{1}^{a}[x] f^{\\prime}(x) d x=\\int_{1}^{2} 1 f^{\\prime}(x) d x+\\int_{2}^{3} 2 f^{\\prime}(x) d x+\\)\n\n... \\(\\int_{k-1}^{k}(k-1) f^{\\prime}(x) d x+\\int_{k}^{k+h} k f^{\\prime}(x) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\{f(2)-f(1)\\}+2\\{f(3)-f(2)\\}+3\\{f(4)-f(3)\\}\\)\n\n\\(+\\ldots \\ldots . .+(k-1)\\{f(k)-f(k-1)\\}+k\\{f(k+h)-f(k)\\}\\)\n\n\\(=-f(1)-f(2)-f(3) \\ldots \\ldots . .-f(k)+k f(k+h)\\)\n\n\\(=[a] f(a)-\\{f(1)+f(2)+f(3)+\\ldots f([a])\\}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 14
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "question": "\\(\\int_{-\\frac{3 \\pi}{2}}^{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}\\left[(x+\\pi)^{3}+\\cos ^{2}(x+3 \\pi)\\right] d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi^{4}}{32}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi^{4}}{32}+\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-1\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\int_{-\\frac{3 \\pi}{2}}^{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}\\left[(x+\\pi)^{3}+\\cos ^{2}(x+3 \\pi)\\right] d x\\)\n\n\nPut \\(x+\\pi=t\\)\\\\\n\\(I=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}\\left[t^{3}+\\cos ^{2} t\\right] d t=2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\cos ^{2} t d t\\)\n\n[ \\(\\because t^{3}\\) is odd and \\(\\cos ^{2} t\\) is even function]\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}(1+\\cos 2 t) d t=\\frac{\\pi}{2}+0\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 14
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "question": "\\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi} x f(\\sin x) d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi} f(\\cos x) d x\\)",
            "\\(\\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi} f(\\sin x) d x\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} f(\\sin x) d x\\)",
            "\\(\\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} f(\\cos x) d x\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\pi} x f(\\sin x) d x=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}(\\pi-x) f(\\sin x) d x\\) \\(=\\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi} f(\\sin x) d x-I \\Rightarrow 2 I=\\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi} f(\\sin x) d x\\)\n\n\n\\(I=\\frac{\\pi}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\pi} f(\\sin x) d x=\\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} f(\\sin x) d x\\)\n\n\\([\\because \\sin (\\pi-x)=\\sin x]\\)\n\n\\(=\\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} f(\\cos x) d x\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 14
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "question": "The value of the integral in the image is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{2}\\)",
            "2",
            "1"
        ],
        "solution": "(b) \\(I=\\int_{3}^{6} \\frac{\\sqrt{x}}{\\sqrt{9-x}+\\sqrt{x}} d x\\)\\ \\(I=\\int_{3}^{6} \\frac{\\sqrt{9-x}}{\\sqrt{9-x}+\\sqrt{x}} d x\\)\\ \\[\\left[\\because \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\right]\\] Adding equation (1) and (2)\\ \\(2 I=\\int_{3}^{6} d x=[x]_{3}^{6}=3 \\Rightarrow I=\\frac{3}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 14
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi} \\frac{\\cos ^{2} x}{1+a^{x}} d x\\), \\(\\mathrm{a}>0\\), is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\mathrm{a} \\pi\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{\\mathrm{a}}\\)",
            "\\(2 \\pi\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) Let \\(I=\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi} \\frac{\\cos ^{2} x}{1+a^{x}} d x\\)\n\n\n\\[\n=\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi} \\frac{\\cos ^{2}(-x)}{1+a^{-x}} d x\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\left[\\operatorname{Using} \\int_{a}^{\\mathrm{b}} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\right]\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi} \\frac{\\mathrm{a}^{x} \\cos ^{2} x}{1+a^{x}} d x\\)\n\nAdding equations (1) and (2) we get\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi} \\cos ^{2} x\\left(\\frac{1+a^{x}}{1+a^{x}}\\right) d x=\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi} \\cos ^{2} x d x\\)\n\n\\(=2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\cos ^{2} x d x[\\because f(\\pi-x)=f(x)]\\) \\(=2 \\times 2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\cos ^{2} x d x=4 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{2} x d x\\left[\\because f\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-x\\right)=f(x)\\right]\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{2} x d x=2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}\\left(1-\\cos ^{2} x\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} d x-2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\cos ^{2} x d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I+I=2\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\right)=\\pi \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I}=\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 14
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "question": "If \\(I_{1}=\\int_{0}^{1} 2^{x^{2}} d x, I_{2}=\\int_{0}^{1} 2^{x^{3}} d x, I_{3}=\\int_{1}^{2} 2^{x^{2}} d x\\) and \\(I_{4}=\\int_{1}^{2} 2^{x^{3}} d x\\) then:",
        "options": [
            "\\(I_{2}>I_{1}\\)",
            "\\(I_{1}>I_{2}\\)",
            "\\(I_{3}=I_{4}\\)",
            "\\(I_{3}>I_{4}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(I_{1}=\\int_{0}^{1} 2^{x^{2}} d x, I_{2}=\\int_{0}^{1} 2^{x^{3}} d x\\),\n\n\n\\(I_{3}=\\int_{0}^{1} 2^{x^{2}} d x, I_{4}=\\int_{0}^{1} 2^{x^{3}} d x\\)\n\n\\(\\because 2^{x^{3}}<2^{x^{2}}, 0<x<1\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\int_{0}^{1} 2^{x^{2}} d x>\\int_{0}^{1} 2^{x^{3}} d x \\Rightarrow I_{1}>I_{2}\\)\n\nand \\(2^{x^{3}}>2^{x}, x>1\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I}_{4}>\\mathrm{I}_{3}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 14
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "question": "Let \\(f: R \\rightarrow R\\) be a differentiable function having \\(f(2)=6\\), \\(f^{\\prime}(2)=\\left(\\frac{1}{48}\\)\\). Then \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 2} \\int_{6}^{f(x)} \\frac{4 t^{3}}{x-2} d t\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "24",
            "36",
            "12",
            "18"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 2} \\int_{0}^{f(x)} \\frac{4 t^{3}}{x-2} d t=\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0} \\frac{\\int_{0}^{f(x)} 4 t^{3} d t}{x-2}\\)\n\n\nApplying L Hospital rule\n\n\\[\n\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 2} \\frac{\\left[4 f(x)^{3} f^{\\prime}(x)\\right]}{1}=4(f(2))^{3} f\n\\]\n\n\\(=4 \\times 6^{3} \\times \\frac{1}{48}=18\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 14
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "question": "If \\(f(x)=\\frac{e^{x}}{1+e^{x}}, I_{1}=\\int_{f(-a)}^{f(a)} x g\\{x(1-x)\\} d x\\) and \\(I_{2}=\\int_{f(-a)}^{f(a)} g\\{x(1-x)\\} d x\\), then the value of \\(\\frac{I_{2}}{I_{1}}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "-3",
            "-1",
            "2"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(f(x)=\\frac{e^{x}}{1+e^{x}} \\Rightarrow f(-x)=\\frac{e^{-x}}{1+e^{-x}}=\\frac{1}{e^{x}+1}\\)\n\n\n\\(\\therefore f(x)+f(-x)=1 \\forall x \\in R\\)\n\nNow \\(\\quad I_{1}=\\int_{f(-a)}^{f(a)} x g\\{x(1-x)\\} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{f(-a)}^{f(a)}(1-x) g\\{x(1-x)\\} d x\\)\n\n\\[\n\\left[\\operatorname{using} \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x a=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\right]\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\Rightarrow \\int_{f(-a)}^{f(a)} g\\{x(1-x)\\} d x-\\int_{f(-a)}^{f(a)} x g(x(1-x) d x \\\\\n& =I_{2}-I_{1} \\Rightarrow 2 I_{1}=I_{2}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 15
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "question": "If \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi} x f(\\sin x) d x=A \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} f(\\sin x) d x\\), then \\(A\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(2 \\pi\\)",
            "\\(\\pi\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)",
            "0"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) Let \\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\pi} x f(\\sin x) d x\\)\n\n\nWe know that\n\n\\[\n\\int_{0}^{a} f(x) d x=\\int_{0}^{a} f(a-x) d x=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}(\\pi-x) f(\\sin x) d x\n\\]\n\nAdding (i) and (ii)\n\n\\[\n\\therefore 2 I=\\pi \\int_{2}^{\\pi} f(\\sin x) d x=\\pi \\cdot 2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} f(\\sin x) d x\n\\]\n\n\\[\n[\\because \\sin (\\pi-x)=\\sin x]\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\therefore I=\\pi \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} f(\\sin x) d x \\Rightarrow A=\\pi\n\\]\n\nLet \\(\\log x=t \\Rightarrow e^{t}=x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{1}{x} d x=d t \\Rightarrow d x=x d t \\Rightarrow e^{t} d t\\).",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 15
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "question": "The value of \\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{(\\sin x+\\cos x)^{2}}{\\sqrt{1+\\sin 2 x}} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "3",
            "1",
            "2",
            "0"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\frac{(\\sin x+\\cos x)^{2}}{\\sqrt{1+\\sin 2 x}} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{(\\sin x+\\cos x)^{2}}{\\sqrt{(\\sin x+\\cos x)^{2}}}\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\frac{(\\sin x+\\cos x)^{2}}{(\\sin x+\\cos x)} d x=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}(\\sin x+\\cos x) \\mathrm{dx}\\)\n\n\\[\n\\left[\\because \\sin x+\\cos x>0 \\text { if } 0<x<\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\right]\n\\]\n\nor \\(\\quad I=[-\\cos x+\\sin x]_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}=2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 15
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{-2}^{3}\\left|1-x^{2}\\right| d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{14}{3}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{7}{3}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{28}{3}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\int_{-2}^{3}\\left|1-x^{2}\\right| d x=\\int_{-2}^{3}\\left|x^{2}-1\\right| d x\\)\n\n\nNow \\(\\left|x^{2}-1\\right|=\\left\\{\\begin{array}{llc}x^{2}-1 & \\text { if } & x \\leq-1 \\\\ 1-x^{2} & \\text { if } & -1 \\leq x \\leq 1 \\\\ x^{2}-1 & \\text { if } & x \\geq 1\\end{array}\\right.\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore\\) Integral is \\(\\int_{-2}^{-1}\\left(x^{2}-1\\right) d x+\\int_{-1}^{1}\\left(1-x^{2}\\right) d x+\\int_{1}^{3}\\left(x^{2}-1\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\left[\\frac{x^{3}}{3}-x\\right]_{-2}^{-1}+\\left[x-\\frac{x^{3}}{3}\\right]_{-1}^{1}+\\left[\\frac{x^{3}}{3}-x\\right]_{1}^{3} \\\\\n& =\\left(-\\frac{1}{3}+1\\right)-\\left(-\\frac{8}{3}+2\\right)+\\left(2-\\frac{2}{3}\\right)+\\left(\\frac{27}{3}-3\\right)-\\left(\\frac{1}{3}-1\\right) \\\\\n& =\\frac{2}{3}+\\frac{2}{3}+\\frac{4}{3}+6+\\frac{2}{3}=\\frac{28}{3}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 15
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(I=\\int_{0}^{1} x(1-x)^{n} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{n+1}+\\frac{1}{n+2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{n+1}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{n+2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{n+1}-\\frac{1}{n+2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(I=\\int_{0}^{1} x(1-x)^{n} d x=\\int_{0}^{1}(1-x)(1-1+x)^{n} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{1}(1-x) x^{n} d x=\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(x^{n}-x^{n+1}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\left[\\frac{x^{n+1}}{n+1}-\\frac{x^{n+2}}{n+2}\\right]_{0}^{1}=\\frac{1}{n+1}-\\frac{1}{n+2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 15
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "question": "Let \\(f(x)\\) be a function satisfying \\(f^{\\prime}(x)=f(x)\\) with \\(f(0)=1\\) and \\(g(x)\\) be a function that satisfies \\(f(x)+g(x)=x^{2}\\). Then the value of the integral \\(\\int_{0}^{1} f(x) g(x) d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(e+\\frac{e^{2}}{2}+\\frac{5}{2}\\)",
            "\\(e-\\frac{e^{2}}{2}-\\frac{5}{2}\\)",
            "\\(e+\\frac{e^{2}}{2}-\\frac{3}{2}\\)",
            "\\(e-\\frac{e^{2}}{2}-\\frac{3}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Given that \\(f^{\\prime}(x)=f(x) \\Rightarrow \\frac{f^{\\prime}(x)}{f(x)}=1\\)\n\n\nIntegrating both side we get\n\n\\(\\log f(x)=x+c \\Rightarrow f(x)=e^{x+c}\\)\n\n\\(f(0)=1 \\Rightarrow f(x)=e^{x}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore g(x)=x^{2}-f(x)=x^{2}-e^{x}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\int_{0}^{1} f(x) g(x) d x=\\int_{0}^{1} e^{x}\\left(x^{2}-e^{x}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{1} x^{2} e^{x} d x-\\int_{0}^{1} e^{2 x} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\left[x^{2} e^{x}\\right]_{0}^{1}-2\\left[x e^{x}-e^{x}\\right]_{0}^{1}-\\frac{1}{2}\\left[e^{2 x}\\right]_{0}^{1}\\)\n\n\\(=e-\\left[\\frac{e^{2}}{2}-\\frac{1}{2}\\right]-2[e-e+1]=e-\\frac{e^{2}}{2}-\\frac{3}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 15
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "question": "If \\(f(a+b-x)=f(x)\\) then \\(\\int_{a}^{b} x f(x) d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{a+b}{2} \\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b+x) d x\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{a+b}{2} \\int_{a}^{b} f(b-x) d x\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{a+b}{2} \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{b-a}{2} \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(I=\\int_{a}^{b} x f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b}(a+b-x) f(a+b-x) d x\\)\n\n\nWe know that\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\because \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x \\\\\n& =(a+b) \\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x-\\int_{a}^{b} x f(a+b-x) d x \\\\\n& =(a+b) \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x-\\int_{a}^{b} x f(x) d x \\\\\n& {[\\because \\text { Given that } f(a+b-x)=f(x)]}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& 2 I=(a+b) \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad I=\\frac{(a+b)}{2} \\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 15
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0} \\frac{\\int_{0}^{x^{2}} \\sec ^{2} t d t}{x \\sin x}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "0",
            "3",
            "2",
            "1"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0} \\frac{\\frac{d}{d x} \\int_{0}^{x^{2}} \\sec ^{2} t d t}{\\frac{d}{d x}(x \\sin x)}=\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0} \\frac{\\sec ^{2} x^{2} \\cdot 2 x}{\\sin x+x \\cos x}\\)\n\n\n\\[\n\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0} \\frac{2 \\sec ^{2} x^{2}}{\\left(\\frac{\\sin x}{x}+\\cos x\\right)}=\\frac{2 \\times 1}{1+1}=1\n\\]\n\n(by L'Hospital rule)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 15
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "question": "If \\(f(y)=e^{y}, g(y)=y ; y>0\\) and \\(F(t)=\\int_{0}^{t} f(t-y) g(y) d y\\), then:",
        "options": [
            "\\(F(t)=t e^{-t}\\)",
            "\\(F(t)=1-t e^{-t}(1+t)\\)",
            "\\(F(t)=e^{t}-(1+t)\\)",
            "\\(F(t)=t e^{t}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (c) \\(F(t)=\\int_{0}^{t} f(t-y) g(y) d y\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{t} e^{t-y} y d y=e^{t} \\int_{0}^{t} e^{-y} y d y\\)\n\n\\(=e^{t}\\left[-y e^{-y}-e^{-y}\\right]_{0}^{t}=-e^{t}\\left[y e^{-y}+e^{-y}\\right]_{0}^{t}\\)\n\n\\(=-e^{t}\\left[t e^{-t}+e^{-t}-0-1\\right]=-e^{t}\\left[\\frac{t+1-e^{t}}{e^{t}}\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=e^{t}-(1+t)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "c",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 15
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "question": "\\(\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi} \\frac{2 x(1+\\sin x)}{1+\\cos ^{2} x} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\pi^{2}\\)",
            "zero",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi} \\frac{2 x(1+\\sin x)}{1+\\cos ^{2} x} d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi} \\frac{2 x d x}{1+\\cos ^{2} x}+2 \\int_{-\\pi}^{\\pi} \\frac{x \\sin x}{1+\\cos ^{2} x} d x\\)\n\n\\(=0+4 \\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\frac{x \\sin x d x}{1+\\cos ^{2} x}\\);\n\nWe know that\n\n\\(\\because \\int_{-a}^{a} f(\\mathrm{x}) \\mathrm{dx}=0\\), if \\(f(x)\\) is odd.\n\n\\(=2 \\int_{0}^{a} f(x) d x\\), if \\(f(x)\\) is even\n\n\\(I=4 \\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\frac{(\\pi-x) \\sin (\\pi-x)}{1+\\cos ^{2}(\\pi-x)} d x\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{I}=4 \\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\frac{(\\pi-x) \\sin x}{1+\\cos ^{2} x} d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{I}=4 \\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\frac{\\sin x d x}{1+\\cos ^{2} x}-4 \\int \\frac{x \\sin x d x}{1+\\cos ^{2} x}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{I}=4 \\pi \\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\frac{\\sin x}{1+\\cos ^{2} x} d x\\)\n\nput \\(\\cos x=t \\Rightarrow-\\sin x d x=d t\\) when \\(\\mathrm{x}=0, \\mathrm{t}=1\\) and when \\(\\mathrm{x}=\\pi, \\mathrm{t}=-1\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\mathrm{I}=-2 \\pi \\int_{1}^{-1} \\frac{1}{1+t^{2}} d t=2 \\pi \\int_{-1}^{1} \\frac{1}{1+t^{2}} d t\\)\n\n\\(=2 \\pi\\left[\\tan ^{-1} t\\right]_{-1}^{1}=2 \\pi\\left[\\tan ^{-1} 1-\\tan ^{-1}(-1)\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=2 \\pi\\left[\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\left(\\frac{-\\pi}{4}\\right)\\right]=2 \\pi \\cdot \\frac{\\pi}{2}=\\pi^{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 15
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "question": "\\(\\int_{0}^{2}\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(2-\\sqrt{2}\\)",
            "\\(2+\\sqrt{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\sqrt{2}-1\\)",
            "\\(-\\sqrt{2}-\\sqrt{3}+5\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) We know that \\([x]\\) is greatest integer function less than equal to \\(x\\)\n\n\n\\(\\therefore \\int_{0}^{2}\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x=\\int_{0}^{1}\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x+\\int_{1}^{\\sqrt{2}}\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x+\\)\n\n\\[\n\\int_{\\sqrt{2}}^{\\sqrt{3}}\\left[x^{2}\\right]+\\int_{\\sqrt{3}}^{2}\\left[x^{2}\\right] d x\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{1} 0 d x+\\int_{1}^{\\sqrt{2}} 1 d x+\\int_{\\sqrt{2}}^{\\sqrt{3}} 2 d x+\\int_{\\sqrt{3}}^{2} 3 d x\\)\n\n\\(=[x]_{1}^{\\sqrt{2}}+[2 x]_{\\sqrt{2}}^{\\sqrt{3}}+[3 x]_{\\sqrt{3}}^{2}\\)\n\n\\(=\\sqrt{2}-1+2 \\sqrt{3}-2 \\sqrt{2}+6-3 \\sqrt{3}\\)\n\n\\(=5-\\sqrt{3}-\\sqrt{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 16
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "question": "\\(I_{n}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 4} \\tan ^{n} x d x\\) then \\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} n\\left[I_{n}+I_{n+2}\\right]\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "1",
            "\\(\\infty\\)",
            "zero"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(I_{n}+I_{n+2}=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 4} \\tan ^{n} x\\left(1+\\tan ^{2} x\\right) d x\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 4} \\tan ^{n} x \\sec ^{2} x d x=\\left[\\frac{\\tan ^{n+1} x}{n+1}\\right]_{0}^{\\pi / 4}\\)\n\n\\[\n\\left[\\because \\int x^{n} d x=\\frac{x^{n+1}}{n+1}\\right]\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\frac{1-0}{n+1}=\\frac{1}{n+1}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I_{n}+I_{n+2}=\\frac{1}{n+1} \\Rightarrow \\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} n\\left[I_{n}+I_{n+2}\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} n \\cdot \\frac{1}{n+1}=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{n}{n+1}=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{n}{n\\left(1+\\frac{1}{n}\\right)}=1\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 16
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "question": "\\(\\int_{0}^{10 \\pi}|\\sin x| \\mathrm{d} x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "20",
            "8",
            "10",
            "18"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(I=\\int_{0}^{10 \\pi}|\\sin x| d x=10 \\int_{0}^{\\pi}|\\sin x| d x\\)\n\n\n\\([\\because \\sin (10 \\pi-x)=\\sin x]\\)\n\n\\(=10 \\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\sin x d x\\)\n\n\\(\\because \\sin x>0\\), for \\(0<x<\\pi\\).\n\nas \\(\\sin (\\pi-x)=\\sin x\\)\n\n\\(I=20 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin x d x=20[-\\cos x]_{0}^{\\pi / 2}=20\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 16
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "question": "Let a function \\(f:[0,5] \\rightarrow \\mathbf{R}\\) be continuous, \\(f(1)=3\\) and \\(\\mathrm{F}\\) be defined as: \\(\\mathrm{F}(x)=\\int_{1}^{x} t^{2} g(t) d t\\), where \\(g(t)=\\int_{1}^{x} f(u) d u\\). Then for the function \\(\\mathrm{F}\\), the point \\(x=1\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "a point of local minima.",
            "not a critical point.",
            "a point of local maxima.",
            "a point of inflection."
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(F(x)=\\int_{1}^{x} t^{2} g(t) d t\\)\n\n\nDifferentiate by using Leibnitz's rule, we get\n\n\\(F^{\\prime}(x)=x^{2} g(x)=x^{2} \\int_{1}^{x} f(u) d u\\)\n\nAt \\(x=1\\),\n\n\\(F^{\\prime}(1)=1 \\int_{1}^{1} f(u) d u=0\\)\n\nNow, differentiate eqn (i)\n\n\\(F^{\\prime \\prime}(x)=x^{2} f(x)-2 x \\int_{1}^{x} f(u) d u\\)\n\nAt \\(x=1\\),\n\n\\(F^{\\prime \\prime}(1)=1 . f(1)-2 \\times 1 . \\int_{1}^{1} f(u) d u\\)\n\n\\(=f(1)-2 \\times 0=f(1)\\)\n\n\\(F^{\\prime \\prime}(1)=3\\)\n\nThen, for \\(F^{\\prime}(1)=0, F^{\\prime \\prime}(1)=3>0\\)\n\nHence, \\(x=1\\) is a point of local minima.",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 16
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "question": "\\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty}\\left(\\frac{(n+1)^{1 / 3}}{n^{4 / 3}}+\\frac{(n+2)^{1 / 3}}{n^{4 / 3}}+\\ldots \\ldots+\\frac{(2 n)^{1 / 3}}{n^{4 / 3}}\\right)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{3}{4}(2)^{4 / 3}-\\frac{3}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{4}{3}(2)^{4 / 3}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{3}{2}(2)^{4 / 3}-\\frac{4}{3}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{4}{3}(2)^{3 / 4}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(\\lim _{\\mathrm{n} \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{(\\mathrm{n}+1)^{\\frac{1}{3}}+(\\mathrm{n}+2)^{\\frac{1}{3}}+\\ldots+(\\mathrm{n}+\\mathrm{n})^{\\frac{1}{3}}}{n(n)^{\\frac{1}{3}}}\\)\n\n\n\\(=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\sum_{r=1}^{n} \\frac{(n+r)^{\\frac{1}{3}}}{n \\cdot n^{\\frac{1}{3}}}\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{1}(1+\\mathrm{x})^{\\frac{1}{3}} \\mathrm{dx} \\quad\\left[\\because \\frac{\\mathrm{r}}{\\mathrm{n}} \\rightarrow \\mathrm{x}\\right.\\) and \\(\\left.\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{n}} \\rightarrow \\frac{\\mathrm{d}}{\\mathrm{x}}\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\left[\\frac{3}{4}(1+x)^{\\frac{4}{3}}\\right]_{0}^{1}=\\frac{3}{4}(2)^{\\frac{4}{3}}-\\frac{3}{4}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 16
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "question": "\\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty}\\left(\\frac{n}{n^{2}+1^{2}}+\\frac{n}{n^{2}+2^{2}}+\\frac{n}{n^{2}+3^{2}}+\\ldots \\ldots+\\frac{1}{5 n}\\)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)",
            "\\(\\tan ^{-1}(3)\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\tan ^{-1}(2)\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) Let \\(L=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\sum_{r=1}^{2 n} \\frac{n}{n^{2}+r^{2}}=\\int_{0}^{2} \\frac{d x}{1+x^{2}}\\)\n\n\n\\(\\left[\\because \\frac{r}{n} \\rightarrow x, \\frac{1}{r} \\rightarrow d x\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\left[\\tan ^{-1} x\\right]_{0}^{2}\\)\n\n\\(=\\tan ^{-1} 2\\)\\\\",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 16
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "question": "If \\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1^{a}+2^{a}+\\ldots+n^{a}}{(n+1)^{a-1}[(n a+2)+\\ldots+ (n a+n)]}=\\frac{1}{60}\\) for some positive real number \\(a\\), then \\(a\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "7",
            "8",
            "\\(\\frac{15}{2}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{17}{2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\item (a) \\(\\lim _{\\mathrm{n} \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{\\frac{1}{(\\mathrm{a}+1)} \\cdot \\mathrm{n}^{\\mathrm{a}+1}+\\mathrm{a}_{1} \\mathrm{n}^{\\mathrm{a}}+\\mathrm{a}_{2} \\mathrm{n}^{\\mathrm{a}-1}+\\ldots \\ldots .}{(1+1)}=\\frac{1}{60}\\)\n\n\\[\n(\\mathrm{n}+1)^{\\mathrm{a}-1} \\cdot \\mathrm{n}^{2}\\left(\\mathrm{a}+\\frac{1+\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{n}}}{2}\\right)\n\\]\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{\\left(\\frac{1}{n}\\right)^{a}+\\left(\\frac{2}{n}\\right)^{a}+\\ldots \\ldots . .+\\left(\\frac{n}{n}\\right)^{a}}{(n+1)^{a-1}\\left[n^{2} a+\\frac{n(n+1)}{2}\\right]}=\\frac{1}{60}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n} \\sum_{r=1}^{n}\\left(\\frac{r}{n}\\right)^{a}}{\\left(1+\\frac{1}{n}\\right)^{a-1}\\left[a+\\frac{1}{2}\\left(1+\\frac{1}{n}\\right)\\right]}=\\frac{1}{60}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\int_{0}^{1} x^{a} d x}{\\left(a+\\frac{1}{2}\\right)}=\\frac{1}{60}=\\frac{\\frac{1}{a+1}}{a+\\frac{1}{2}}=\\frac{1}{60}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{\\frac{1}{a+1}}{\\left(a+\\frac{1}{2}\\right)}=\\frac{1}{60}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow(a+1)(2 a+1)=120\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 a^{2}+3 a-119=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 a^{2}+17 a-14 a-119=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow(a-7)(2 a+17)=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow a=7,-\\frac{17}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 16
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "question": "\\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty}\\left(\\frac{(n+1)(n+2) \\ldots 3 n}{n^{2 n}}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{n}}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{9}{\\mathrm{e}^{2}}\\)",
            "\\(3 \\log 3-2\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{18}{\\mathrm{e}^{4}}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{27}{\\mathrm{e}^{2}}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(y=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty}\\left(\\frac{(n+1)(n+2) \\ldots 3 n}{n^{2 n}}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{n}}\\)\n\n\n\\(\\ln y=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n} \\ln \\left(1+\\frac{1}{n}\\right)\\left(1+\\frac{2}{n}\\right) \\ldots .\\left(1+\\frac{2 n}{n}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\ln y=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n}\\left[\\ln \\left(1+\\frac{1}{n}\\right)+\\ln \\left(1+\\frac{2}{n}\\right)+\\ldots .+\\ln \\left(1+\\frac{2 n}{n}\\right)\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n} \\sum_{r=1}^{2 n} \\ln \\left(1+\\frac{r}{n}\\right)=\\int_{0}^{2} \\ln (1+x) d x\\)\n\nLet \\(1+x=t \\Rightarrow d x=d t\\)\n\nwhen \\(x=0, t=1\\)\n\n\\(x=2, t=3\\)\n\n\\(\\ln y=\\int_{1}^{3} \\ln t d t=[t \\ln t-t]_{1}^{3}=\\ln \\left(\\frac{3^{3}}{e^{2}}\\right)=\\ln \\left(\\frac{27}{e^{2}}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow y=\\frac{27}{e^{2}}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 16
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "question": "\\(f(x)=\\int \\frac{d x}{\\sin ^{6} x}\\) is a polynomial of degree:",
        "options": [
            "5 in \\(\\cot x\\)",
            "5 in \\(\\tan x\\)",
            "3 in \\(\\tan x\\)",
            "3 in \\(\\cot x\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) Let \\(f(x)=\\int \\frac{d x}{\\sin ^{6} x}\\)\n\n\n\\(f(x)=\\int \\operatorname{cosec}^{6} x d x\\)\n\nFrom reduction formula, we have\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{n}}=\\int \\operatorname{cosec}^{n} x d x=-\\frac{\\operatorname{cosec}^{n-2} x \\cot x}{n-1}+\\frac{n-2}{n-1} \\mathrm{I}_{n-2} \\\\\n& \\therefore f(x)=-\\frac{\\operatorname{cosec}^{4} x \\cot x}{5}+\\frac{4}{5}\\left[\\frac{-\\operatorname{cosec}^{2} x \\cot x}{3}+\\frac{2}{3} \\mathrm{I}_{2}\\right] \\\\\n& =-\\frac{\\operatorname{cosec}^{4} x \\cot x}{5}-\\frac{4}{15} \\operatorname{cosec}^{2} x \\cdot \\cot x+\\frac{8}{15}[-\\cot x] \\\\\n& =\\frac{-\\left(1+\\cot ^{2} x\\right)^{2} \\cdot \\cot x}{5}-\\frac{4}{15}\\left(1+\\cot ^{2} x\\right) \\cot x \\\\\n& =\\frac{-1}{5}\\left[1+\\cot ^{4} x+2 \\cot ^{2} x\\right] \\cot x-\\frac{4}{15}[-\\cot x)\\left(\\because \\operatorname{cosec}^{2} x+\\cot ^{3} x\\right] \\\\\n& =\\frac{-1}{5}\\left[\\cot x+\\cot ^{2} x\\right) \\\\\n& \\left.=\\frac{-15}{15} \\cot x-\\frac{\\cot ^{5} x}{5}-\\frac{10}{15} \\cot ^{3} x\\right] \\\\\n& =\\frac{-\\cot 5}{5} x \\\\\n& 5 \\\\\n& =\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nIt is a polynomial of degree 5 in \\(\\cot x\\).",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 16
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "question": "\\(\\underset{n \\rightarrow \\infty}{\\operatorname{Lim}}\\left[\\frac{1}{n^{2}} \\sec ^{2} \\frac{1}{n^{2}}+\\frac{2}{n^{2}} \\sec ^{2} \\frac{4}{n^{2}} \\ldots \\ldots+\\frac{1}{n} \\sec ^{2} 1\\right]\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\sec 1\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\operatorname{cosec} 1\\)",
            "\\(\\tan 1\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\tan 1\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (d) \\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty}\\left[\\begin{array}{c}\\frac{1}{n^{2}} \\sec ^{2} \\frac{1}{n^{2}}+\\frac{2}{n^{2}} \\sec ^{2} \\frac{4}{n^{2}} \\\\ +\\frac{3}{n^{2}} \\sec ^{2} \\frac{9}{n^{2}}+\\ldots .+\\frac{1}{n} \\sec ^{2} 1\\end{array}\\right]\\) is equal to\n\n\n\\[\n\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{r}{n^{2}} \\sec ^{2} \\frac{r^{2}}{n^{2}}=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n} \\cdot \\frac{r}{n} \\sec ^{2} \\frac{r^{2}}{n^{2}}\n\\]\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow\\) Given limit is equal to value of integral\n\n\\[\n\\int_{0}^{1} x \\sec ^{2} x^{2} d x\n\\]\n\nor \\(\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{1} 2 x \\sec x^{2} d x=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{1} \\sec ^{2} t d t \\quad\\) [put \\(\\left.x^{2}=t\\right]\\)\n\n\\[\n=\\frac{1}{2}(\\tan t)_{0}^{1}=\\frac{1}{2} \\tan 1\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "d",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 16
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "question": "\\(\\operatorname{Lim}_{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\sum_{r=1}^{n} \\frac{1}{n} e^{\\frac{r}{n}}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(e+1\\)",
            "\\(e-1\\)",
            "\\(1-e\\)",
            "\\(e\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (b) \\(\\operatorname{Lim}_{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\sum_{r=1}^{n} \\frac{1}{n} e^{\\frac{r}{n}}\\) [Using definite integrals as limit of sum]\n\n\n\\[\n=\\int_{0}^{1} e^{x} d x=e-1\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "b",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 17
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "question": "\\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1+2^{4}+3^{4}+\\ldots n^{4}}{n^{5}}-\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1+2^{3}+3^{3}+\\ldots n^{3}}{n^{5}}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{5}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{30}\\)",
            "Zero",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{4}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) \\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1^{4}+2^{4}+3^{4}+\\ldots \\ldots . n^{4}}{n^{5}}-\\)\n\n\n\\[\n\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1^{3}+2^{3}+3^{3}+\\ldots \\ldots+n^{3}}{n^{5}}\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n} \\sum_{r=1}^{n}\\left(\\frac{r}{n}\\right)^{4}-\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n} \\cdot \\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n}\\left(\\frac{r}{n}\\right)^{3}\\)\n\n\\[\n=\\int_{0}^{1} x^{4} d x-\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n} \\times \\int_{0}^{1} x^{3} d x=\\left[\\frac{x^{5}}{5}\\right]_{0}^{1}-0=\\frac{1}{5}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 17
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "question": "\\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1^{p}+2^{p}+3^{p}+\\ldots+n^{p}}{n^{p+1}}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\(\\frac{1}{p+1}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{1-p}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{p}-\\frac{1}{p-1}\\)",
            "\\(\\frac{1}{p+2}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "}\n  \\item (a) We have \\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1^{p}+2^{p}+\\ldots .+n^{p}}{n^{p+1}}\\);\n\n\n\\[\n\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\sum_{r=1}^{n} \\frac{r^{p}}{n^{p} \\cdot n}=\\int_{0}^{1} x^{p} d x=\\left[\\frac{x^{p+1}}{p+1}\\right]_{0}^{1}=\\frac{1}{p+1}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "a",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 17
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "question": "Let \\(f(x)=\\int \\frac{d x}{\\left(3+4 x^{2}\\right) \\sqrt{4-3 x^{2}}},|x|<\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{3}}\\). If \\(f(0)=0\\) and \\(f(1)=\\frac{1}{\\alpha \\beta} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\alpha}{\\beta}\\right), \\alpha, \\beta>0\\), then \\(\\alpha^{2}+\\beta^{2}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& f(x)=\\int \\frac{d x}{\\left(3+4 x^{2}\\right) \\sqrt{4-3 x^{2}}} \\\\\n& x=\\frac{1}{t} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{\\frac{-1}{t^{2}} d t}{\\frac{\\left(3 t^{2}+4\\right)}{t^{2}} \\frac{\\sqrt{4 t^{2}-3}}{t}} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{-d t \\cdot t}{\\left(3 t^{2}+4\\right) \\sqrt{4 t^{2}-3}}: \\text { Put } 4 t^{2}-3=z^{2} \\\\\n& =-\\frac{1}{4} \\int \\frac{z d z}{\\left(3\\left(\\frac{z^{2}+3}{4}\\right)+4\\right) z} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{-d z}{3 z^{2}+25}=-\\frac{1}{3} \\int \\frac{\\mathrm{dz}}{\\mathrm{z}^{2}+\\left(\\frac{5}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)^{2}} \\\\\n& =-\\frac{1}{3} \\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{5} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3} z}{5}\\right)+C \\\\\n& =-\\frac{1}{5 \\sqrt{3}} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{5} \\sqrt{4 t^{2}-3}\\right)+C \\\\\n& f(x)=-\\frac{1}{5 \\sqrt{3}} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{5} \\sqrt{\\frac{4-3 \\mathrm{x}^{2}}{x^{2}}}\\right)+C \\\\\n& \\because \\mathrm{f}(0)=0 \\because \\mathrm{c}=\\frac{\\pi}{10 \\sqrt{3}}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\(f(1)=-\\frac{1}{5 \\sqrt{3}} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{5}\\right)+\\frac{\\pi}{10 \\sqrt{3}}\\)\n\n\\(f(1)=\\frac{1}{5 \\sqrt{3}} \\cot ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{5}\\right)=\\frac{1}{5 \\sqrt{3}} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{5}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\alpha=5: \\beta=\\sqrt{3} \\therefore \\alpha^{2}+\\beta^{2}=28\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "28",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 17
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "question": "Let \\(I(x)=\\int \\sqrt{\\frac{x+7}{x}} \\mathrm{~d} x\\) and \\(I(9)=12+7 \\log _{e} 7\\). If \\(I(1)=\\alpha+7 \\log _{e}(1+2 \\sqrt{2})\\), then \\(\\alpha^{4}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "Given integral: \\(\\int \\sqrt{\\frac{x+7}{x}} d x\\)\n\nLet's make the substitution \\(x=t^{2}\\). Then, \\(d x=2 t d t\\).\n\nSubstituting these values, the integral becomes:\n\n\\(\\int 2 \\sqrt{t^{2}+7} d t\\)\n\nNow, let's evaluate this integral :\n\n\\(I(t)=2\\left(\\frac{t}{2} \\sqrt{t^{2}+7}+\\frac{7}{2} \\ln \\left|t+\\sqrt{t^{2}+7}\\right|\\right)+C\\)\n\nSubstituting back \\(t=\\sqrt{x}\\), we have :\n\n\\(I(x)=2\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{x}}{2} \\sqrt{x+7}+\\frac{7}{2} \\ln |\\sqrt{x}+\\sqrt{x+7}|\\right)+C\\)\n\nSimplifying further :\n\n\\(I(x)=\\sqrt{x} \\sqrt{x+7}+7 \\ln |\\sqrt{x}+\\sqrt{x+7}|+C\\)\n\nWe are given that \\(I(9)=12+7 \\ln 7\\).\n\nLet's substitute \\(x=9\\) and solve for the constant \\(C\\) :\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& 12+7 \\ln 7=\\sqrt{9} \\sqrt{9+7}+7 \\ln |\\sqrt{9}+\\sqrt{9+7}|+C \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 12+7 \\ln 7=3 \\sqrt{16}+7 \\ln |\\sqrt{9}+\\sqrt{16}|+C \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 12+7 \\ln 7=3 \\cdot 4+7 \\ln (3+\\sqrt{16})+C \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 12+7 \\ln 7=12+7 \\ln (3+4)+C \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 12+7 \\ln 7=12+7 \\ln 7+C\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nFrom this equation, we can see that \\(C=0\\).\n\nNow, we need to calculate \\(I(1)\\) :\n\n\\(I(1)=\\sqrt{1} \\sqrt{1+7}+7 \\ln |\\sqrt{1}+\\sqrt{1+7}|\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I(1)=1 \\sqrt{8}+7 \\ln (1+\\sqrt{8})\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I(1)=\\sqrt{8}+7 \\ln (1+2 \\sqrt{2})\\)\n\nTherefore, \\(\\alpha=\\sqrt{8}\\).\n\nFinally, to find \\(\\alpha^{4}\\) :\n\n\\(\\alpha^{4}=(\\sqrt{8})^{4}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\alpha^{4}=8^{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\alpha^{4}=64\\)\n\nHence, \\(\\alpha^{4}\\) is equal to 64 .",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "64",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 17
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\sqrt{\\sec 2 x-1} d x=\\alpha \\log _{e}\\left|\\cos 2 x+\\beta+\\sqrt{\\cos 2 x\\left(1+\\cos \\frac{1}{\\beta} x\\right)}\\right|+\\text { constant, then } \\beta-\\alpha\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=\\int \\sqrt{\\sec 2 x-1} d x \\int \\sqrt{\\frac{1-\\cos 2 x}{\\cos 2 x}} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\sqrt{\\frac{2 \\sin ^{2} x}{2 \\cos ^{2} x-1}} d x \\\\\n& \\text { Let } \\sqrt{2 \\cos } x=t-\\sqrt{2} \\sin x d x=d t \\\\\n& I=\\int-\\frac{d t}{\\sqrt{t^{2}-1}}=-\\ln \\left|t+\\sqrt{t^{2}-a^{2}}\\right|+c \\\\\n& =-\\ln \\left|\\sqrt{2} \\cos x+\\sqrt{2 \\cos ^{2}} x-1\\right|+c \\\\\n& =-\\frac{1}{2} \\ln \\left|2 \\cos ^{2} x+\\cos 2 x+2 \\sqrt{2} \\sqrt{\\cos 2 x \\cdot \\cos ^{2} x}\\right|+c \\\\\n& =-\\frac{1}{2} \\ln |2 \\cos 2 x+1+2 \\sqrt{\\cos 2 x(1+\\cos 2 x)}|+c \\\\\n& =-\\frac{1}{2} \\ln \\left|\\cos 2 x+\\frac{1}{2}+\\sqrt{\\cos 2 x(1+\\cos 2 x)}\\right|+c \\\\\n& \\therefore \\alpha=\\frac{-1}{2}, \\beta=\\frac{1}{2} \\\\\n& \\therefore \\beta-\\alpha=1\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "1",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 17
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "question": "For \\(\\alpha, \\beta, \\gamma, \\delta \\in \\mathbb{N}\\), if \\(\\int\\left(\\left(\\frac{x}{e}\\right)^{2 x}+\\left(\\frac{e}{x}\\right)^{2 x}\\right) \\log _{e} x d x=\\frac{1}{\\alpha}\\left(\\frac{x}{e}\\right)^{\\beta x}-\\frac{1}{\\gamma}\\left(\\frac{e}{x}\\right)^{\\delta x}+C\\), where \\(e=\\sum_{n=0}^{\\infty} \\frac{1}{n!}\\) and \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is constant of integration, then \\(\\alpha+2 \\beta+3 \\gamma-4 \\delta\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "-8",
            "-4",
            "1",
            "4"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& f(x)=\\int \\frac{2 x}{\\left(x^{2}+1\\right)\\left(x^{2}+3\\right)} d x \\\\\n& \\text { Put } x^{2}=t \\Rightarrow 2 x d x=d t \\\\\n& f(x)=\\int \\frac{d t}{(t+1)(t+3)}=\\int \\frac{d t}{(t+2)^{2}-1} \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e}\\left|\\frac{t+1}{t+3}\\right|+C \\\\\n& f(x)=\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+1}{x^{2}+3}\\right)+C \\Rightarrow \\\\\n& f(3)=\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{10}{12}\\right)+C \\\\\n& \\because f(3)+\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\log _{e} 5-\\log _{e} 6\\right) \\Rightarrow C=0 \\\\\n& f(x)=\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+1}{x^{2}+3}\\right) \\Rightarrow \\\\\n& f(4)=\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\log _{e} 17-\\log _{e} 19\\right)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 17
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "question": "If \\(I(x)=\\int e^{\\sin ^{2} x}(\\cos x \\sin 2 x-\\sin x) d x\\) and \\(I(0)=1\\), then \\(I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "-e^{\\frac{3}{4}}",
            "-\\frac{1}{2} e^{\\frac{3}{4}}",
            "e^{\\frac{3}{4}}",
            "\\frac{1}{2} e^{\\frac{3}{4}}"
        ],
        "solution": "NULL",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 17
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int\\left(\\left(\\frac{x}{2}\\right)^{x}+\\left(\\frac{2}{x}\\right)^{x}\\right) \\log _{2} x d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\left(\\frac{x}{2}\\right)^{x}+\\left(\\frac{2}{x}\\right)^{x}+C",
            "\\left(\\frac{x}{2}\\right)^{x}-\\left(\\frac{2}{x}\\right)^{x}+C",
            "\\left(\\frac{x}{2}\\right)^{x} \\log _{2}\\left(\\frac{2}{x}\\right)+C",
            "None"
        ],
        "solution": "NULL",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 17
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "question": "Let \\(I(x)=\\int \\frac{(x+1)}{x\\left(1+x e^{x}\\right)^{2}} d x, x>0\\). If \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow \\infty} I(x)=0\\), then \\(I(1)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{e+1}{e+2}-\\log _{e}(e+1)",
            "\\frac{e+1}{e+2}+\\log _{e}(e+1)",
            "\\frac{e+2}{e+1}-\\log _{e}(e+1)",
            "\\frac{e+2}{e+1}+\\log _{e}(e+1)"
        ],
        "solution": "NULL",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 17
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "question": "Let \\(I(x)=\\int \\frac{x^{2}\\left(x \\sec ^{2} x+\\tan x\\right)}{(x \\tan x+1)^{2}} d x\\). If \\(I(0)=0\\), then \\(I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\log _{e} \\frac{(\\pi+4)^{2}}{32}-\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{4(\\pi+4)}",
            "\\log _{e} \\frac{(\\pi+4)^{2}}{16}-\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{4(\\pi+4)}",
            "\\log _{e} \\frac{(\\pi+4)^{2}}{16}+\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{4(\\pi+4)}",
            "\\log _{e} \\frac{(\\pi+4)^{2}}{32}+\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{4(\\pi+4)}"
        ],
        "solution": "NULL",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 18
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "question": "Let \\(f(x)=\\int \\frac{2 x}{\\left(x^{2}+1\\right)\\left(x^{2}+3\\right)} d x\\). If \\(f(3)=\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\log _{e} 5-\\log _{e} 6\\right)\\), then \\(f(4)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\log _{e} 19-\\log _{e} 20",
            "\\log _{e} 17-\\log _{e} 18",
            "\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\log _{e} 19-\\log _{e} 17\\right)",
            "\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\log _{e} 17-\\log _{e} 19\\right)"
        ],
        "solution": "NULL",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 18
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "question": "For \\(I(x)=\\int \\frac{\\sec ^{2} x-2022}{\\sin ^{2022} x} d x\\), if \\(I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)=2^{1011}\\), then:",
        "options": [
            "3^{1010} I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)-I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)=0",
            "3^{1010} I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)-I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)=0",
            "3^{1011} I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)-I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)=0",
            "3^{1011} I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)-I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)=0"
        ],
        "solution": "Given,\n\n\\(I(x)=\\int \\frac{\\sec ^{2} x-2022}{\\sin ^{2022} x} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{\\sec ^{2} x}{\\sin ^{2022} x} d x-\\int \\frac{2022}{\\sin ^{2022} x} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{1}{\\sin ^{2022} x} \\cdot \\sec ^{2} x d x-\\int \\frac{2022}{\\sin ^{2022 x}} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{\\sin ^{2022} x} \\cdot \\tan x-\\int\\left(\\frac{-2022}{\\sin ^{2023} x} \\cdot \\cos x \\cdot \\tan x\\right) d x-\\int \\frac{2022}{\\sin ^{2022} x} d x+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\tan x}{\\sin ^{2222} x}+\\int\\left(\\frac{2022}{\\sin ^{2023} x} \\cdot \\cos x \\cdot \\frac{\\sin x}{\\cos x}\\right) d x-\\int \\frac{2022}{\\sin ^{2022} x} d x+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\tan x}{\\sin ^{2022} x}+\\int \\frac{2022}{\\sin ^{2022} x} d x-\\int \\frac{2022}{\\sin ^{2022} x} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\tan x}{\\sin ^{2022} x}+C\\)\n\nGiven, \\(I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)=2^{1011}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)=\\frac{\\tan \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)}{\\left(\\sin \\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)^{2022}}+C\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\Rightarrow 2^{1011}=\\frac{1}{\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}\\right)^{2022}}+C \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow C=2^{1011}-2^{1011}=0 \\\\\n& \\therefore I(x)=\\frac{\\tan x}{\\sin ^{2022} x} \\\\\n& \\therefore I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)=\\frac{\\tan \\frac{\\pi}{3}}{\\left(\\sin \\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)^{2022}}=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\right)^{2022}} \\\\\n& I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)=\\frac{\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}}{\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)^{2022}}=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}} \\times(2)^{2022}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nFrom option (A),\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& 3^{1010} \\cdot I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)-I\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right) \\\\\n& =3^{1010} \\cdot \\sqrt{3} \\cdot\\left(\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)^{2022}-\\frac{(2)^{2022}}{\\sqrt{3}} \\\\\n& =3^{1010} \\cdot \\sqrt{3} \\times \\frac{2^{2022}}{3^{1011}}-\\frac{2^{2022}}{\\sqrt{3}} \\\\\n& =\\frac{2^{2022}}{\\sqrt{3}}-\\frac{2^{2022}}{\\sqrt{3}}=0\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 18
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{\\left(1-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)(\\cos x-\\sin x)}{\\left(1+\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{3}} \\sin 2 x\\right)} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e}\\left|\\frac{\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{12}\\right)}{\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)}\\right|+C",
            "\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e}\\left|\\frac{\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)}{\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)}\\right|+C",
            "\\log _{e}\\left|\\frac{\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)}{\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{12}\\right)}\\right|+C",
            "\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e}\\left|\\frac{\\tan \\left(\\frac{x}{2}-\\frac{\\pi}{12}\\right)}{\\tan \\left(\\frac{z}{2}-\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)}\\right|+C"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n=\\int \\frac{\\left(1-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)(\\cos x-\\sin x)}{\\left(1+\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{3}} \\sin 2 x\\right)} d x\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\int \\frac{\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}-1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right) \\sqrt{2} \\sin \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-x\\right)}{\\left(\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)\\left(\\sin \\frac{\\pi}{3}+\\sin 2 x\\right)} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{\\frac{(\\sqrt{3}-1)}{\\sqrt{2}} \\sin \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-x\\right)}{\\left(\\sin \\frac{\\pi}{3}+\\sin 2 x\\right)} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{\\frac{\\sqrt{3}-1}{2 \\sqrt{2}} \\sin \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-x\\right)}{\\sin \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}+x\\right) \\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}-x\\right)} d x \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2} \\int \\frac{2 \\sin \\frac{\\pi}{12} \\sin \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-x\\right)}{\\sin \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}+x\\right) \\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}-x\\right)} d x \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2} \\int \\frac{\\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}-x\\right)-\\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}-x\\right)}{\\sin \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}+x\\right) \\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}-x\\right)} d x \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\int \\operatorname{cosec}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}+x\\right) d x-\\int \\sec \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}-x\\right) d x\\right]\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\ln \\left|\\tan \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{12}+\\frac{x}{2}\\right)\\right|-\\int \\operatorname{cosec}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}-x\\right) d x\\right] \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\ln \\left|\\tan \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{12}+\\frac{x}{2}\\right)\\right|-\\ln \\left|\\frac{\\pi}{6}+\\frac{x}{2}\\right|\\right]+C \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2} \\ln \\left|\\frac{\\tan \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}+\\frac{x}{2}\\right)}{\\tan \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}+\\frac{x}{2}\\right)}\\right|+C\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 18
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{\\left(x^{2}+1\\right) e^{x}}{(x+1)^{2}} d x=f(x) e^{x}+C\\), where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant, then \\(\\frac{d^{3} f}{d x^{3}}\\) at \\(\\mathrm{x}=1\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "-\\frac{3}{4}",
            "\\frac{3}{4}",
            "-\\frac{3}{2}",
            "\\frac{3}{2}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\nI=\\int \\frac{e^{x}\\left(x^{2}+1\\right)}{(x+1)^{2}} d x=f(x) e^{x}+c\n\\]\n\n\\[\n=\\int \\frac{e^{x}\\left(x^{2}-1+1+1\\right)}{(x+1)^{2}} d x\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\int e^{x}\\left[\\frac{x-1}{x+1}+\\frac{2}{(x+1)^{2}}\\right] d x\\)\n\n\\(=e^{x}\\left(\\frac{x-1}{x+1}\\right)+c\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore f(x)=\\frac{x-1}{x+1}\\)\n\n\\(f(x)=1-\\frac{2}{x+1}\\)\n\n\\(f^{\\prime}(x)=2\\left(\\frac{1}{x+1}\\right)^{2}\\)\n\n\\(f^{\\prime \\prime}(x)=-4\\left(\\frac{1}{x+1}\\right)^{3}\\)\n\n\\(f^{\\prime \\prime \\prime}(x)=\\frac{12}{(x+1)^{4}}\\)\n\nfor \\(x=1\\)\n\n\\(f^{\\prime \\prime \\prime}(1)=\\frac{12}{2^{4}}=\\frac{12}{16}=\\frac{3}{4}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 18
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{1}{x} \\sqrt{\\frac{1-x}{1+x}} d x=g(x)+c, g(1)=0\\), then \\(g\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}-1}{\\sqrt{3}+1}\\right)+\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\)",
            "\\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}+1}{\\sqrt{3}-1}\\right)+\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\)",
            "\\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}+1}{\\sqrt{3}-1}\\right)-\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\)",
            "\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}-1}{\\sqrt{3}+1}\\right)-\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "Given, \\(\\int \\frac{1}{x} \\sqrt{\\frac{1-x}{1+x}} d x=g(x)+c, g(1)=0\\)\n\nLet \\(\\mathrm{I}=\\int \\frac{1}{x} \\sqrt{\\frac{1-x}{1+x}} d x\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\int \\frac{1}{x} \\sqrt{\\frac{(1-x)(1+x)}{(1+x)(1+x)}} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{1-x}{x \\sqrt{1-x^{2}}} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{1}{x \\sqrt{1-x^{2}}} d x-\\int \\frac{1}{\\sqrt{1-x^{2}}} d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nPut \\(x=\\frac{1}{t}\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& d x=-\\frac{1}{t^{2}} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{\\frac{-1}{t^{2}}}{\\frac{1}{t} \\sqrt{1-\\frac{1}{t^{2}}}} d t-\\sin ^{-1}(x)+C_{1} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{-d t}{\\sqrt{t^{2}-1}}-\\sin ^{-1}(x)+C_{1}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\(=-\\ln \\left|t+\\sqrt{t^{2}-1}\\right|-\\sin ^{-1}(x)+C_{1}\\) [Putting values of \\(t\\) ]\n\n\\(=-\\ln \\left|\\frac{1}{x}+\\sqrt{\\frac{1}{x^{2}}-1}\\right|-\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\cos ^{-1} \\mathrm{x}\\right)+\\mathrm{C}_{1}\\)\n\n\\(=-\\ln \\left|\\frac{1}{x}+\\sqrt{\\frac{1}{x^{2}}-1}\\right|+\\cos ^{-1}(x)-\\frac{\\pi}{2}+C_{1}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore g(x)=\\cos ^{-1}(x)-\\ln \\left|\\frac{1}{x}+\\sqrt{\\frac{1}{x^{2}}-1}\\right|\\)\n\nSo, \\(g(1)=\\cos ^{-1}(1)-\\ell n|1|=0\\)\n\n\\(g\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)=\\cos ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)-\\ell n|2+\\sqrt{3}|\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\pi}{3}+\\ln \\left(\\frac{1}{2+\\sqrt{3}}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{\\pi}{3}+\\ln \\left(\\frac{\\sqrt{3}-1}{\\sqrt{3}+1}\\right)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 18
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{\\sin x}{\\sin ^{3} x+\\cos ^{3} x} d x= \\alpha \\log _{e}|1+\\tan x|+\\beta \\log _{e}\\left|1-\\tan x+\\tan ^{2} x\\right|+\\gamma \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{2 \\tan x-1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)+C\\), when \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is constant of integration, then the value of \\(18\\left(\\alpha+\\beta+\\gamma^{2}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(=\\int \\frac{\\frac{\\sin x}{\\cos ^{3} x}}{1+\\tan ^{3} x} d x=\\int \\frac{\\tan x \\cdot \\sec ^{2} x}{(\\tan x+1)\\left(1+\\tan ^{2} x-\\tan x\\right)} d x\\)\n\nLet \\(\\tan x=t \\Rightarrow \\sec ^{2} x . d x=d t\\)\\\\\n\\(=\\int \\frac{t}{(t+1)\\left(t^{2}-t+1\\right)} d t\\)\n\n\\(=\\int\\left(\\frac{A}{t+1}+\\frac{B(2 t-1)}{t^{2}-t+1}+\\frac{C}{t^{2}-t+1}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow A\\left(t^{2}-t+1\\right)+B(2 t-1)\\left(t^{2}-t+1\\right)+C(t+1)=t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow t^{2}(A+2 B)+t(-A+B+C)+A-B+C=1\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore A+2 B=0 \\ldots\\).\n\n\\(-A+B+C=1 \\ldots\\)\n\n\\(A-B=C=0 .\\).\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow C=\\frac{1}{2} \\Rightarrow A-B=-\\frac{1}{2}\\)\n\n\\(A+2 B=0\\)\n\n\\(A-B=-\\frac{1}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 3 B=\\frac{1}{2} \\Rightarrow B=\\frac{1}{6}\\)\n\n\\(A=-\\frac{1}{3}\\)\n\n\\(I=-\\frac{1}{3} \\int \\frac{d t}{1+t}+\\frac{1}{6} \\int \\frac{2 t-1}{t^{2}-t+1} d t+\\frac{1}{2} \\int \\frac{d t}{t^{2}-t+1}\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =-\\frac{1}{3} \\ln |(1+\\tan x)|+\\frac{1}{6} \\ln \\left|\\tan ^{2} x-\\tan x+1\\right|+\\frac{1}{2} \\cdot \\frac{2}{\\sqrt{3}} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\left(\\tan x-\\frac{1}{2}\\right)}{\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}}\\right) \\\\\n& =-\\frac{1}{3} \\ln |(1+\\tan x)|+\\frac{1}{6} \\ln \\left|\\tan ^{2} x-\\tan x+1\\right|+\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{2 \\tan x-1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)+C \\\\\n& \\alpha=-\\frac{1}{3}, \\beta=\\frac{1}{6}, \\gamma=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}} \\\\\n& 18\\left(\\alpha+\\beta+\\gamma^{2}\\right)=18\\left(-\\frac{1}{3}+\\frac{1}{6}+\\frac{1}{3}\\right)=3\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "3",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 18
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{2 e^{x}+3 e^{-x}}{4 e^{x}+7 e^{-x}} d x=\\frac{1}{14}\\left(u x+v \\log _{e}\\left(4 e^{x}+7 e^{-x}\\right)\\right)+C\\), where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration, then \\(\\mathrm{u}+\\mathrm{v}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& 2 e^{x}+3 e^{-x}=A\\left(4 e^{x}+7 e^{-x}\\right)+B\\left(4 e^{x}-7 e^{-x}\\right)+\\lambda \\\\\n& 2=4 \\mathrm{~A}+4 \\mathrm{~B} ; 3=7 \\mathrm{~A}-7 \\mathrm{~B} ; \\lambda=0 \\\\\n& A+B=\\frac{1}{2} \\\\\n& A-B=\\frac{3}{7} \\\\\n& A=\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\frac{1}{2}+\\frac{3}{7}\\right)=\\frac{7+6}{28}=\\frac{13}{28} \\\\\n& B=A-\\frac{3}{7}=\\frac{13}{28}-\\frac{3}{7}=\\frac{13-12}{28}=\\frac{1}{28} \\\\\n& \\int \\frac{13}{28} d x+\\frac{1}{28} \\int \\frac{4 e^{x}-7 e^{-x}}{4 e^{x}+7 e^{-x}} d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\frac{13}{28} x+\\frac{1}{28} \\ln \\left|4 e^{x}+7 e^{-x}\\right|+C \\\\\n& u=\\frac{13}{2} ; v=\\frac{1}{2} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{u}+\\mathrm{v}=7\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "7",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 18
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{d x}{\\left(x^{2}+x+1\\right)^{2}}=a \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{2 x+1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)+b\\left(\\frac{2 x+1}{x^{2}+x+1}\\right)+C, \\mathrm{x}>0\\) where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is the constant of integration, then the value of \\(9(\\sqrt{3} a+b)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=\\int \\frac{d x}{\\left[\\left(x+\\frac{1}{2}\\right)^{2}+\\frac{3}{4}\\right]^{2}} \\\\\n& \\int \\frac{d t}{\\left(t^{2}+\\frac{3}{4}\\right)^{2}} \\text { put }\\left(x+\\frac{1}{2}=t\\right) \\\\\n& =\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2} \\int \\frac{\\sec ^{2} \\theta d \\theta}{\\frac{9}{16} \\sec ^{4} \\theta} \\text { put }\\left(t=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2} \\tan \\theta\\right) \\\\\n& =\\frac{4 \\sqrt{3}}{9} \\int(1+\\cos 2 \\theta) d \\theta \\\\\n& =\\frac{4 \\sqrt{3}}{9}\\left[\\theta+\\frac{\\sin 2 \\theta}{2}\\right]+c \\\\\n& =\\frac{4 \\sqrt{3}}{9}\\left[\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{2 x+1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)+\\frac{\\sqrt{3}(2 x+1)}{3+(2 x+1)^{2}}\\right]+c \\\\\n& =\\frac{4 \\sqrt{3}}{9} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{2 x+1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)+\\frac{1}{3}\\left(\\frac{2 x+1}{x^{2}+x+1}\\right)+c\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nHence, \\(9(\\sqrt{3} a+b)=15\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "15",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 18
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "question": "If \\(f(x)=\\int \\frac{5 x^{8}+7 x^{6}}{\\left(x^{2}+1+2 x^{7}\\right)^{2}} d x,(x \\geq 0), f(0)=0\\) and \\(f(1)=\\frac{1}{K}\\), then the value of \\(\\mathrm{K}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\int \\frac{5 x^{8}+7 x^{6}}{\\left(2 x^{7}+x^{2}+1\\right)^{2}} d x=\\int \\frac{5 x^{8}+7 x^{6}}{x^{14}\\left(2+\\frac{1}{x^{5}}+\\frac{1}{x^{7}}\\right)^{2}} d x \\\\\n& \\int \\frac{\\frac{5}{x^{6}}+\\frac{7}{x^{8}}}{\\left(2+\\frac{1}{x^{5}}+\\frac{1}{x^{7}}\\right)^{2}} d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nput \\(2+\\frac{1}{x^{5}}+\\frac{1}{x^{7}}=t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow-\\left(\\frac{5}{x^{6}}+\\frac{7}{x^{8}}\\right) d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(\\int \\frac{-d t}{t^{2}}=\\frac{1}{t}+c\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(x)=\\frac{1}{2+\\frac{1}{x^{5}}+\\frac{1}{x^{7}}}+C=\\frac{x^{7}}{2 x^{7}+1+x^{2}}+C\\)\n\n\\(f(0)=0 \\Rightarrow C=0\\)\n\n\\(f(x)=\\frac{1}{4}=\\frac{1}{k}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow k=4\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "4",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 18
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "question": "For real numbers \\(\\alpha, \\beta, \\gamma\\) and \\(\\delta\\), if \\(\\int \\frac{\\left(x^{2}-1\\right)+\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+1}{x}\\right)}{\\left(x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1\\right) \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+1}{x}\\right)} d x =\\alpha \\log _{e}\\left(\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+1}{x}\\right)\\right)+\\beta \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\gamma\\left(x^{2}+1\\right)}{x}\\right)+\\delta \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+1}{x}\\right)+C\\), where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is an arbitrary constant, then the value of \\(10(\\alpha+\\beta \\gamma+\\delta)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\int \\frac{\\left(x^{2}-1\\right)+\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+1}{x}\\right)}{\\left(x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1\\right) \\tan ^^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+1}{x}\\right)} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{x^{2}-1}{\\left(x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1\\right) \\tan ^^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+1}{x}\\right)} d x+\\int \\frac{1}{x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1} d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\text { Let, } I_{1}=\\int \\frac{1-\\frac{1}{x^{2}}}{\\left[\\left(x+\\frac{1}{x}\\right)^{2}+1\\right] \\tan ^^{-1}\\left(x+\\frac{1}{x}\\right)} d x\n\\]\n\nand \\(I_{2}=\\int \\frac{d x}{x^{4}+3 x+1}\\)\n\n\\(\\tan ^{-1}\\left(x+\\frac{1}{x}\\right)=t\\)\n\n\\(I_{1}=\\int \\frac{d t}{t}\\)\n\n\\(I_{1}=\\ln (t)=\\ln \\left|\\tan ^{-1}\\left(x+\\frac{1}{x}\\right)\\right|\\)\n\nNow\n\n\\[\nI_{2}=\\int \\frac{d x}{x^{4}+3 x+1}\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2} \\int \\frac{\\left(x^{2}+1\\right)-\\left(x^{2}-1\\right)}{x^{4}+3 x^{2}+1} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\int \\frac{1+\\frac{1}{x^{2}}}{x^{2}+3+\\frac{1}{x^{2}}} d x-\\int \\frac{\\left(1-\\frac{1}{x^{2}}\\right)}{x^{2}+3+\\frac{1}{x^{2}}} d x\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\int \\frac{1+\\frac{1}{x^{2}}}{\\left[\\left(x-\\frac{1}{x}\\right)^{2}+5\\right]} d x-\\int \\frac{1-\\frac{1}{x^{2}}}{\\left[\\left(x+\\frac{1}{x}\\right)^{2}+1\\right]} d x\\right]\\)\n\nLet \\(x-\\frac{1}{x}=u\\) and \\(x+\\frac{1}{x}=v\\)\\\\\n\\(=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\int \\frac{d u}{u^{2}+(\\sqrt{5})^{2}}-\\int \\frac{d v}{v^{2}+1}\\right]\\)\n\n\\(I_{2}=\\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{5}} \\tan ^^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x-\\frac{1}{x}}{\\sqrt{5}}\\right)-\\frac{1}{2} \\tan ^^{-1}\\left(x+\\frac{1}{x}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(I=I_{1}+I_{2}=\\)\n\n\\(\\ln \\left|\\tan ^^{-1}\\left(x+\\frac{1}{x}\\right)\\right|+\\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{5}} \\ln \\left(\\frac{x^{2}-1}{\\sqrt{5} x}\\right)-\\frac{1}{2} \\tan ^^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x^{2}+1}{x}\\right)+C\\)\n\n\\(\\alpha=1, \\beta=\\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{5}}, \\lambda=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{5}}, \\delta=-\\frac{1}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore 10(\\alpha+\\beta \\lambda+\\delta)=10\\left[1+\\frac{1}{10}-\\frac{1}{2}\\right]\\)\n\n\\(=10\\left(\\frac{1}{10}+\\frac{1}{2}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=1+5=6\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "6",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 19
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{1}{\\sqrt[4]{(x-1)^{3}(x+2)^{5}}} d x\\) is equal to: (where \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is a constant of integration)",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{3}{4}\\left(\\frac{x+2}{x-1}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{4}}+C",
            "\\frac{3}{4}\\left(\\frac{x+2}{x-1}\\right)^{\\frac{5}{4}}+C",
            "\\frac{4}{3}\\left(\\frac{x-1}{x+2}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{4}}+C",
            "\\frac{4}{3}\\left(\\frac{x-1}{x+2}\\right)^{\\frac{5}{4}}+C"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\int \\frac{d x}{(x-1)^{3 / 4}(x+2)^{5 / 4}} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{d x}{\\left(\\frac{x+2}{x-1}\\right)^{5 / 4} \\cdot(x-1)^{2}}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nput \\(\\frac{x+2}{x-1}=t\\)\n\n\\[\n=-\\frac{1}{3} \\int \\frac{d t}{t^{5 / 4}}\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\frac{4}{3} \\cdot \\frac{1}{t^{1 / 4}}+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{4}{3}\\left(\\frac{x-1}{x+2}\\right)^{1 / 4}+C\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 19
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{(2 x-1) \\cos \\sqrt{(2 x-1)^{2}+5}}{\\sqrt{4 x^{2}-4 x+6}} d x\\) is equal to (where \\(\\mathrm{c}\\) is a constant of integration):",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{1}{2} \\sin \\sqrt{(2 x-1)^{2}+5}+c",
            "\\frac{1}{2} \\cos \\sqrt{(2 x+1)^{2}+5}+c",
            "\\frac{1}{2} \\cos \\sqrt{(2 x-1)^{2}+5}+c",
            "\\frac{1}{2} \\sin \\sqrt{(2 x+1)^{2}+5}+c"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(\\int \\frac{(2 x-1) \\cos \\sqrt{(2 x-1)^{2}+5}}{\\sqrt{(2 x-1)^{2}+5}} d x\\)\n\n\\((2 x-1)^{2}+5=t^{2}\\)\n\n\\(2(2 x-1) 2 d x=2 t d t\\)\n\n\\[\n2 \\sqrt{t^{2}-5} d x=t d t\n\\]\n\nSo, \\(\\int \\frac{\\sqrt{t^{2}-5} \\cos t}{2 \\sqrt{t^{2}-5}} d t=\\frac{1}{2} \\sin t+c\\)\n\n\\[\n=\\frac{1}{2} \\sin \\sqrt{(2 x-1)^{2}+5}+c\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 19
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "question": "The integral \\(\\int \\frac{e^{3 \\log _{e} 2 x}+5 e^{2 \\log _{e} 2 x}}{e^{4 \\log _{e} x}+5 e^{3 \\log _{e} x}-7 e^{2 \\log _{e} x}} d x, \\mathrm{x}>0\\), is equal to (where \\(\\mathrm{c}\\) is a constant of integration):",
        "options": [
            "\\log _{e} \\sqrt{x^{2}+5 x-7}+c",
            "4 \\log _{e}\\left|x^{2}+5 x-7\\right|+c",
            "\\frac{1}{4} \\log _{e}\\left|x^{2}+5 x-7\\right|+c",
            "\\log _{e}\\left|x^{2}+5 x-7\\right|+c"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\int \\frac{e^{3 \\log _{e} 2 x}+5 e^{2 \\log _{e} 2 x}}{e^{4 \\log _{e} x}+5 e^{3 \\log _{e} x}-7 e^{2 \\log _{e} x}} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{8 x^{3}+5\\left(4 x^{2}\\right)}{x^{4}+5 x^{3}-7 x^{2}} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{8 x^{3}+20 x^{2}}{x^{4}+5 x^{3}-7 x^{2}} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{8 x+20}{x^{2}+5 x-7} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{4(2 x+5)}{x^{2}+5 x-7}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { Let }\\left\\{\\begin{array}{l}\nx^{2}+5 x-7=t \\\\\n(2 x+5) d x=d t\n\\end{array}\\right\\} \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{4 d t}{t} \\\\\n& =4 \\ln |t|+C \\\\\n& =4 \\ln \\left|\\left(x^{2}+5 x-7\\right)\\right|+C\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nHere \\(\\mathrm{C}\\) is integral constant.",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 19
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int \\frac{\\sin \\theta \\cdot \\sin 2 \\theta\\left(\\sin ^{6} \\theta+\\sin ^{4} \\theta+\\sin ^{2} \\theta\\right) \\sqrt{2 \\sin ^{4} \\theta+3 \\sin ^{2} \\theta+6}}{1-\\cos 2 \\theta} d \\theta\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{1}{18}\\left[9-2 \\cos ^{6} \\theta-3 \\cos ^{4} \\theta-6 \\cos ^{2} \\theta\\right]^{\\frac{3}{2}}+c",
            "\\frac{1}{18}\\left[11-18 \\sin ^{2} \\theta+9 \\sin ^{4} \\theta-2 \\sin ^{6} \\theta\\right]^{\\frac{3}{2}}+c",
            "\\frac{1}{18}\\left[11-18 \\cos ^{2} \\theta+9 \\cos ^{4} \\theta-2 \\cos ^{6} \\theta\\right]^{\\frac{3}{2}}+c",
            "\\frac{1}{18}\\left[9-2 \\sin ^{6} \\theta-3 \\sin ^{4} \\theta-6 \\sin ^{2} \\theta\\right]^{\\frac{3}{2}}+c"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\int \\frac{2 \\sin ^{2} \\theta \\cos \\theta\\left(\\sin ^{6} \\theta+\\sin ^{4} \\theta+\\sin ^{2} \\theta\\right) \\sqrt{2 \\sin ^{4} \\theta+3 \\sin ^{2} \\theta+6}}{2 \\sin ^{2} \\theta} d \\theta \\\\\n& \\text { Let } \\sin \\theta=\\mathrm{t}, \\cos \\theta \\mathrm{d} \\theta=\\mathrm{dt} \\\\\n& =\\int\\left(t^{6}+t^{4}+t^{2}\\right) \\sqrt{2 t^{4}+3 t^{2}+6} d t \\\\\n& =\\int\\left(t^{5}+t^{3}+t\\right) \\sqrt{2 t^{6}+3 t^{4}+6 t^{2}} d t \\\\\n& \\text { Let } 2 t^{6}+3 t^{4}+6 t^{2}=z \\\\\n& 12\\left(t^{5}+t^{3}+t\\right) d t=d z \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{12} \\int \\sqrt{z} d z=\\frac{1}{18} z^{3 / 2}+c \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{18}\\left[\\left(2 \\sin ^{6} \\theta+3 \\sin ^{4} \\theta+6 \\sin ^{2} \\theta\\right)^{3 / 2}+C\\right. \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{18}\\left[\\left(1-\\cos ^{2} \\theta\\right)\\left(2\\left(1-\\cos ^{2} \\theta\\right)^{2}+3-3 \\cos ^{2} \\theta+6\\right)\\right]^{3 / 2}+C \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{18}\\left[\\left(1-\\cos ^{2} \\theta\\right)\\left(2 \\cos ^{4} \\theta-7 \\cos ^{2} \\theta+11\\right)\\right]^{3 / 2}+C \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{18}\\left[-2 \\cos ^{6} \\theta+9 \\cos ^{4} \\theta-18 \\cos ^{2} \\theta+11\\right]^{3 / 2}+C\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 19
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "question": "If \\(\\int \\frac{\\cos x-\\sin x}{\\sqrt{8-\\sin 2 x}} d x=a \\sin ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\sin x+\\cos x}{b}\\right)+c\\), where \\(\\mathrm{c}\\) is a constant of integration, then the ordered pair \\((\\mathrm{a}, \\mathrm{b})\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "(-1,3)",
            "(1,3)",
            "(1,-3)",
            "(3,1)"
        ],
        "solution": "Given \\(\\int \\frac{\\cos x-\\sin x}{\\sqrt{8-\\sin 2 x}} d x\\)\n\nWrite \\(\\sin 2 x=1+\\sin 2 x-1\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\int \\frac{\\cos x-\\sin x}{\\sqrt{8-[1+\\sin 2 x-1]}} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{\\cos x-\\sin x}{\\sqrt{8-\\left[\\sin ^{2} x+\\cos ^{2} x+2 \\sin x \\cos x-1\\right]}} d x \\\\\n& =\\int \\frac{\\cos x-\\sin x}{\\sqrt{9-(\\sin x+\\cos x)^{2}}} d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nput \\(\\sin x+\\cos x=t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow(\\cos x-\\sin x) d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(=\\int \\frac{d t}{\\sqrt{9-(t)^{2}}}\\)\n\n\\(=\\sin ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{t}{3}\\right)+C\\)\n\n\\(=\\sin ^^{-1}\\left(\\frac{\\sin x+\\cos x}{3}\\right)+C\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore a=1\\) and \\(b=3\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 19
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "question": "If the line \\(y=m x\\) bisects the area enclosed by the lines \\(x=0, y=0, x=3 / 2\\) and the curve \\(y=1+4 x-x^{2}\\), then \\(12 \\mathrm{~m}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-035}\n\\end{center}\n\nAccording to the question,\n\n\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{3 / 2}\\left(1+4 x-x^{2}\\right) d x=\\int_{0}^{3 / 2} m x d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\left(x+2 x^{2}-\\frac{x^{3}}{3}\\right)\\right]_{0}^{3 / 2}=\\frac{m}{2}[x]_{0}^{3 / 2} \\Rightarrow \\frac{3}{2}+\\frac{9}{2}-\\frac{9}{8}=\\frac{9 m}{4}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{m}=39 / 18 \\Rightarrow 12 \\mathrm{~m}=26\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "26",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 19
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "question": "If \\(x \\phi(x)=\\int_{5}^{x}\\left(3 t^{2}-2 \\phi^{\\prime}(t)\\right) d t, \\mathrm{x}>-2 \\text {, and } \\phi(0)=4 \\text {, then } \\phi(2) \\text { is }\\):",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& x \\phi(x)=\\int_{5}^{x} 3 t^{2}-2 \\phi^{\\prime}(t) d t \\\\\n& x \\phi(x)=x^{3}-125-2[\\phi(x)-\\phi(5)] \\\\\n& x \\phi(x)=x^{3}-125-2 \\phi(x)-2 \\phi(5) \\\\\n& \\phi(0)=4 \\Rightarrow \\phi(5)=\\frac{133}{2} \\\\\n& \\phi(x)=\\frac{x^{3}+8}{x+2} \\\\\n& \\phi(2)=4\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "4",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 19
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "question": "Let \\([t]\\) denote the greatest integer \\(\\leq \\mathrm{t}\\). Then the value of \\(8 \\int_{-\\frac{1}{2}}^{1}([2 x]+|x|) d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=\\int_{-\\frac{1}{2}}^{1}([2 x]+|x|) d x \\\\\n& =\\int_{-1 / 2}^{1}[2 x] d x+\\int_{-1 / 2}^{1}|x| d x \\\\\n& =0+\\int_{-1 / 2}^{0}(-x) d x+\\int_{0}^{1} x d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\left(-\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\right)_{-1 / 2}^{0}+\\left(\\frac{x^{2}}{2}\\right)_{0}^{1} \\\\\n& =\\left(0+\\frac{1}{8}\\right)+\\frac{1}{2} \\\\\n& =\\frac{5}{8} \\\\\n& \\therefore 81=5\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "5",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 19
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "question": "Let a and \\(b\\) respectively be the points of local maximum and local minimum of the function \\(f(x)=2 x^{3}-3 x^{2}-12 x\\). If \\(A\\) is the total area of the region bounded by \\(y=f(x)\\), the \\(x\\)-axis and the lines \\(x=a\\) and \\(x=b\\), then \\(4 A\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\nf^{\\prime}(x)=6 x^{2}-6 x-12=6(x-2)(x+1)\n\\]\n\nPoint \\(=(2,-20) \\&(-1,7)\\)\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-037}\n\\end{center}\n\n\\(A=\\int_{-1}^{0}\\left(2 x^{3}-3 x^{2}-12 x\\right) d x+\\int_{0}^{2}\\left(12 x+3 x^{2}-2 x^{3}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(A=\\left(\\frac{x^{4}}{2}-x^{3}-6 x^{2}\\right)_{-1}^{0}+\\left(6 x^{2}+x^{3}-\\frac{x^{4}}{2}\\right)_{0}^{2}\\)\n\n\\(4 A=114\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "114",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 19
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "question": "The area of the region \\(S=\\left\\{(x, y): 3 x^{2} \\leq 4 y \\leq 6 x+24\\right\\}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-038}\n\\end{center}\n\nFor \\(A \\& B\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& 3 x^{2}=6 x+24 \\Rightarrow x^{2}-2 x-8=0 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow x=-2,4 \\\\\n& \\text { Area }=\\int_{-2}^{4}\\left(\\frac{3}{2} x+6-\\frac{3}{4} x^{2}\\right) d x \\\\\n& =\\left[\\frac{3 x^{2}}{4}+6 x-\\frac{x^{3}}{4}\\right]_{-2}^{4}=27\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "27",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 20
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "question": "Let the domain of the function \\(f(x)=\\log _{4}\\left(\\log _{5}\\left(\\log _{3}\\left(18 x-x^{2}-77\\right)\\right)\\right)\\) be \\((\\mathrm{a}, \\mathrm{b})\\). Then the value of the integral \\(\\int_{a}^{b} \\frac{\\sin ^{3} x}{\\left(\\sin ^{3} x+\\sin ^{3}(a+b-x)\\right.} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "For domain\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\log _{5}\\left(\\log _{3}\\left(18 x-x^{2}-77\\right)\\right)>0 \\\\\n& \\log _{3}\\left(18 x-x^{2}-77\\right)>1\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& 18 x-x^{2}-77>3 \\\\\n& x^{2}-18 x+80<0 \\\\\n& x \\in(8,10) \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{a}=8 \\text { and } \\mathrm{b}=10 \\\\\n& I=\\int_{a}^{b} \\frac{\\sin ^{3} x}{\\sin ^{3} x+\\sin ^{3}(a+b-x)} d x \\\\\n& I=\\int_{a}^{b} \\frac{\\sin ^{3} x(a+b-x)}{\\sin ^{3} x+\\sin ^{3}(a+b-x)} \\\\\n& 2 I=(b-a) \\Rightarrow I=\\frac{b-a}{2}(\\because \\mathrm{a}=8 \\text { and } \\mathrm{b}=10) \\\\\n& I=\\frac{10-8}{2}=1\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "1",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 20
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "question": "Let a curve \\(y=f(x)\\) pass through the point \\(\\left(2,\\left(\\log _{e} 2\\right)^{2}\\right)\\) and have slope \\(\\frac{2 y}{x \\log _{e} x}\\) for all positive real value of \\(x\\). Then the value of \\(f(e)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& y^{\\prime}=\\frac{2 y}{x \\ln x} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\frac{d y}{y}=\\frac{2 d x}{x \\ln x} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\ln |y|=2 \\ln |\\ln x|+C\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\text { put } x=2, y=(\\ln 2)^{2}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{c}=0 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{y}=(\\ln x)^{2} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{f}(\\mathrm{e})=1\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "1",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 20
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "question": "If \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi}\\left(\\sin ^{3} x\\right) e^{-\\sin ^{2} x} d x=\\alpha-\\frac{\\beta}{e} \\int_{0}^{1} \\sqrt{t} e^{t} d t\\), then \\(\\alpha+\\beta\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin ^{3} x e^{-\\sin ^{2} x} d x \\\\\n& =2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin x e^{-\\sin ^{2} x} d x+\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\underset{I}{\\cos x} \\underbrace{e^{-\\sin ^{2} x}(-\\sin 2 x)}_{I I} d x \\\\\n& =2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin x e^{-\\sin ^{2} x} d x+\\left[\\cos x e^{-\\sin ^{2} x}\\right]_{0}^{\\pi / 2}+\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin x e^{-\\sin ^{2} x} d x \\\\\n& =3 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin x e^{-\\sin ^{2} x} d x-1 \\\\\n& =\\frac{3}{2} \\int_{-1}^{0} \\frac{e^{\\alpha} d \\alpha}{\\sqrt{1+\\alpha}}-1\\left(\\text { Put }-\\sin ^{2} \\mathrm{x}=\\mathrm{t}\\right) \\\\\n& \\left.=\\frac{3}{2 e} \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{e^{x}}{\\sqrt{x}} d x-1 \\text { (put } 1+\\alpha=\\mathrm{x}\\right) \\\\\n& =\\frac{3}{2 e} \\int_{0}^{1} e^{x} \\frac{1}{\\sqrt{x}} d x-1 \\\\\n& =2-\\frac{3}{e} \\int_{0}^{1} e^{x} \\sqrt{x} d x \\\\\n& \\text { Hence, } \\alpha+\\beta=5\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "5",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 20
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "question": "The area (in s units) of the region bounded by the curves \\(x^{2}+2 y-1=0, y^{2}+ 4 x-4=0\\) and \\(y^{2}-4 x-4=0\\), in the upper half plane is:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-041(1)}\n\\end{center}\n\nRequired area (shaded)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =2\\left[\\int_{0}^{2}\\left(\\frac{4-y^{2}}{4}\\right) d y-\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(\\frac{1-x^{2}}{2}\\right) d x\\right] \\\\\n& =2\\left[\\frac{4}{3}-\\frac{1}{3}\\right]=(2)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "2",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 20
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "question": "Let \\(T\\) be the tangent to the ellipse \\(E: x^{2}+4 y^{2}=5\\) at the point \\(P(1,1)\\). If the area of the region bounded by the tangent \\(\\mathrm{T}\\), ellipse \\(\\mathrm{E}\\), lines \\(\\mathrm{x}=1\\) and \\(\\mathrm{x}=\\sqrt{5}\\) is \\(\\alpha \\sqrt{5}+\\beta+\\gamma \\cos ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{5}}\\right)\\), then \\(|\\alpha+\\beta+\\gamma|\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth, center]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-041}\\\\\n\\(E: x^{2}+4 y^{2}=5\\)\n\nTangent at \\(P: x+4 y=5\\)\n\nRequired area\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\int_{1}^{\\sqrt{5}}\\left(\\frac{5-x}{4}-\\frac{\\sqrt{5-x^{2}}}{2}\\right) d x \\\\\n& =\\left[\\frac{5 x}{4}-\\frac{x^{2}}{8}-\\frac{x}{4} \\sqrt{5-x^{2}}-\\frac{5}{2} \\sin ^{-1} \\frac{x}{\\sqrt{5}}\\right]_{1}^{\\sqrt{5}} \\\\\n& =\\frac{5}{4} \\sqrt{5}-\\frac{5}{4}-\\frac{5}{4} \\cos ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{5}}\\right)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nIf we assume \\(\\alpha, \\beta, \\gamma, \\in \\mathrm{Q}\\) (Not given in question) then \\(\\alpha=\\frac{5}{4}, \\beta=-\\frac{5}{4} \\& \\gamma=-\\frac{5}{4}\\)\n\n\\[\n|\\alpha+\\beta+\\gamma|=1.25\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "1.25",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 20
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "question": "Let \\(P(x)\\) be a real polynomial of degree 3 which vanishes at \\(x=-3\\). Let \\(P(x)\\) have local minima at \\(x=1\\), local maxima at \\(\\mathrm{x}=-1\\) and \\(\\int_{-1}^{1} P(x) d x=18\\), then the sum of all the coefficients of the polynomial \\(\\mathrm{P}(\\mathrm{x})\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& P^{\\prime}(x)=a(x+1)(x-1) \\\\\n& \\therefore P(x)=\\frac{a x^{3}}{3}-a x+C \\\\\n& P(-3)=0 \\text { (given) } \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow a(-9+3)+C=0 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 6 a=C \\ldots . . \\text { (i) }\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { Also, } \\int_{-1}^{1} P(x) d x=18 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\int_{-1}^{1}\\left(a\\left(\\frac{x^{3}}{3}-x\\right)+C\\right) d x=18 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 0+2 C=18 \\Rightarrow C=9\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nfrom (i)\n\n\\(a=\\frac{3}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore P(x)=\\frac{x^{3}}{2}-\\frac{3}{2} x+9\\)\n\nSum of co-efficient\n\n\\[\n=\\frac{1}{2}-\\frac{3}{2}+9=-1+9=8\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "8",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 20
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "question": "Let \\(f(x)\\) and \\(g(x)\\) be two functions satisfying \\(f\\left(x^{2}\\right)+g(4-x)=4 x^{3}\\) and \\(g(4-x)+g(x)=0\\), then the value of \\(\\int_{-4}^{4} f(x)^{2} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=2 \\int_{0}^{4} f\\left(x^{2}\\right) d x \\ldots \\ldots \\ldots . . \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow I=2 \\int_{0}^{4} f\\left((4-x)^{2}\\right) d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nAdding equation (1) \\& (2)\n\n\\(2 I=2 \\int_{0}^{4}\\left[f(x)^{2}+f(4-x)^{2}\\right] d x\\)\n\nNow using \\(f\\left(x^{2}\\right)+g(4-x)=4 x^{3}\\)\n\n\\(x \\rightarrow 4-x\\)\n\n\\(f\\left((4-x)^{2}\\right)+g(x)=4(4-x)^{3}\\)\n\nAdding equation (4) \\& (5)\n\n\\(f\\left(x^{2}\\right)+f\\left(4-x^{2}\\right)+g(x)+g(4-x)=4\\left(x^{3}+(4-x)^{3}\\right]\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f\\left(x^{2}\\right)+f\\left(4-x^{2}\\right)=4\\left(x^{3}+(4-x)^{3}\\right]\\)\n\nNow, \\(I=4 \\int_{0}^{4}\\left(x^{3}+(4-x)^{3}\\right) d x=512\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "512",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 20
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "question": "Let \\(\\mathrm{f}:[-3,1] \\rightarrow \\mathrm{R}\\) be given as \\(f(x)=\\left\\{\\begin{array}{l}\\min \\left\\{(x+6), x^{2}\\right\\},-3 \\leq x \\leq 0 \\\\ \\max \\left\\{\\sqrt{x}, x^{2}\\right\\}, 0 \\leq x \\leq 1\\end{array}\\right.\\). If the area bounded by \\(y=f(x)\\) and \\(x\\)-axis is \\(A\\), then the value of \\(6 A\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-044}\n\\end{center}\n\nArea is \\(\\int_{-3}^{-2}(x+6) d x+\\int_{-2}^{0} x^{2} d x+\\int_{0}^{1} \\sqrt{x} d x=A\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{7}{2}+\\left[\\frac{x^{3}}{3}\\right]_{-2}^{0}+\\left[\\frac{2}{3} x^{3 / 2}\\right]_{0}^{1}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{7}{2}+\\frac{8}{3}+\\frac{2}{3}=\\frac{41}{6}\\)\n\nSo, \\(6 A=41\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "41",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 20
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "question": "Let \\(I_{n}=\\int_{1}^{e} x^{19}(\\log |x|)^{n} d x\\), where \\(\\mathrm{n} \\in \\mathrm{N}\\). If \\((20) \\mathrm{I}_{10}=\\alpha \\mathrm{I}_{9}+\\beta \\mathrm{I}_{8}\\), for natural numbers \\(\\alpha\\) and \\(\\beta\\), then \\(\\alpha-\\beta\\) equals to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(I_{n}=2 \\int_{1}^{e} x^{19}(\\ln x)^{n} . d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\left.(\\ln x)^{n} \\cdot \\frac{x^{20}}{20}\\right|_{1} ^{e}-\\int_{1}^{e} n \\frac{(\\ln x)^{n-1}}{x} \\frac{x^{20}}{20} d x\\)\n\n\\(I_{n}=\\frac{e^{20}}{20}-\\frac{n}{20}\\left(I_{n-1}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(20 I_{n}=e^{20}-n I_{n-1}\\)\n\nPutting \\(n=10\\), we get\n\n\\(20 I_{10}=\\left(e^{20}-10 I_{9}\\right) \\ldots \\ldots\\)\n\nPutting \\(n=9\\), we get\n\n\\(20 I_{9}=e^{20}-9 I_{8}\\)\n\nSubtracting (2) from (1), we get\\\\\n\\(20 I_{10}=10 I_{9}+9 I_{8}\\)\n\nBy comparing with \\((20) \\mathrm{I}_{10}=\\alpha \\mathrm{l}_{9}+\\beta \\mathrm{l}_{8}\\), we get\n\n\\(\\alpha=10, \\beta=9 \\Rightarrow \\alpha-\\beta=1\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "1",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 20
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "question": "If the normal to the curve \\(\\mathrm{y}(\\mathrm{x})=\\int_{0}^{x}\\left(2 t^{2}-15 t+10\\right) d t\\) at a point \\(\\mathrm{a}, \\mathrm{b}\\) is parallel to the line \\(\\mathrm{x}+3 \\mathrm{y}=-5, \\mathrm{a}> 1\\), then the value of \\(|a+6 b|\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "Normal to the curve at point \\(P(a, b)\\) is parallel to the line \\(x+3 y=-5\\).\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\mathrm{m}_{\\text {normal }}=-\\frac{1}{3} \\\\\n& \\therefore \\mathrm{m}_{\\text {tangent }}=3=\\frac{d y}{d x} \\\\\n& \\text { Given } \\mathrm{y}(\\mathrm{x})=\\int_{0}^{x}\\left(2 t^{2}-15 t+10\\right) d t \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{y}^{\\prime}(\\mathrm{x})=\\left(2 \\mathrm{x}^{2}-15 \\mathrm{x}+10\\right)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nat point \\(P(a, b)\\)\n\n\\(3=\\left(2 a^{2}-15 a+10\\)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 a^{2}-15 a+7=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{a}^{2}-14 \\mathrm{a}-\\mathrm{a}+7=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 \\mathrm{a}(\\mathrm{a}-7)-1(\\mathrm{a}-7)=0\\)\n\n\\(\\mathrm{a}=\\frac{1}{2}\\) or 7 ,\\\\\ngiven \\(\\mathrm{a}>1 \\therefore \\mathrm{a}=7\\)\n\nAs \\(P(a, b)\\) lies on curve\n\n\\(\\therefore b=\\int_{0}^{a}\\left(2 t^{2}-15 t+10\\right) d t\\)\n\n\\(b=\\int_{0}^{7}\\left(2 t^{2}-15 t+10\\right) d t\\)\n\n\\(6 b=-413\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore|a+6 b|=406\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "406",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 21
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "question": "Let \\(f: R \\rightarrow R\\) be a continuous function such that \\(f(x)+f(x+1)=2\\), for all \\(x \\in R\\). If \\(I_{1}=\\int_{0}^{8} f(x) d x\\) and \\(I_{2}=\\int_{-1}^{3} f(x) d x\\), then the value of \\(\\mathrm{I}_{1}+2 \\mathrm{I}_{2}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(f(x)+f(x+1)=2 \\ldots\\) (i)\n\n\\(x \\rightarrow(x+1)\\)\n\n\\(f(x+1)+f(x+2)=2 \\ldots\\)\n\nby (i) \\& (ii)\n\n\\(f(x)-f(x+2)=0\\)\n\n\\(f(x+2)=f(x)\\)\\\\\n\\(\\therefore f(x)\\) is periodic with \\(T=2\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I_{1}=\\int_{0}^{2 \\times 4} f(x) d x=4 \\int_{0}^{2} f(x) d x \\\\\n& I_{2}=\\int_{-1}^{3} f(x) d x=\\int_{0}^{4} f(x+1) d x=\\int_{0}^{4}(2-f(x)) d x \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow I_{2}=8-2 \\int_{0}^{2} f(x) d x \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow I_{2}=8-\\frac{I_{1}}{2} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow I_{1}+2 I_{2}=16\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "16",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 21
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "question": "Let the curve \\(\\mathrm{y}=\\mathrm{y}(\\mathrm{x})\\) be the solution of the differential equation, \\(\\frac{d y}{d x}=2(\\mathrm{x}+1)\\). If the numerical value of area bounded by the curve \\(y=y(x)\\) and \\(x\\)-axis is \\(\\frac{4 \\sqrt{8}}{3}\\), then the value of \\(y(1)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "Given, \\(\\frac{d y}{d x}=2(x+1)\\)\n\nIntegrating both sides, we get\n\n\\(y=x^{2}+2 x+c\\)\n\nLet the two roots of the quadratic equation \\(\\alpha\\) and \\(\\beta\\)\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-049}\n\\end{center}\n\nAs parabola intercept the \\(x\\) axis so \\(D>0\\)\n\nFrom figure, \\(\\mathrm{AB}=|\\alpha-\\beta|=\\frac{\\sqrt{D}}{|a|}=\\sqrt{D}\\)\n\nand \\(\\mathrm{BC}=-\\frac{D}{4 a}=-\\frac{D}{4}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore\\) Area of rectangle \\((\\mathrm{ABCD})=\\mathrm{AB} \\times \\mathrm{BC}=\\sqrt{D} \\times \\frac{D}{4}\\)\n\nFrom property we know,\n\nArea of parabola with the \\(x\\) axis \\(=\\frac{2}{3}\\) (Area of rectangle)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{4 \\sqrt{8}}{3}=\\frac{2}{3} \\times \\sqrt{D} \\times \\frac{D}{4}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow D \\sqrt{D}=8 \\sqrt{8}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\mathrm{D}=8\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\mathrm{b}^{2}-4 \\mathrm{ac}=8\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 4-4 c=8\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 1-c=2 \\Rightarrow c=-1\\)\n\nEquation of \\(f(x)=x^{2}+2 x-1\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore f(1)=1+2-1=2\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "2",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 21
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "question": "If \\(I_{m, n}=\\int_{0}^{1} x^{m-1}(1-x)^{n-1} d x\\), for \\(\\mathrm{m}, n \\geq 1\\), and \\(\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{x^{m-1}+x^{n-1}}{(1+x)^{m+1}} d x=\\alpha I_{m, n} \\alpha \\in R\\), then \\(\\alpha\\) equals:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\nI_{m, n}=\\int_{0}^{1} x^{m-1} \\cdot(1-x)^{n-1} d x\n\\]\n\nPut \\(x=\\frac{1}{y+1} \\Rightarrow d x=\\frac{-1}{(y+1)^{2}} d y\\)\n\n\\[\n1-x=\\frac{y}{y+1}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\therefore I_{m, n}=\\int_{\\infty}^{0} \\frac{y^{n-1}}{(y+1)^{m+n}}(-1) d y=\\int_{0}^{\\infty} \\frac{y^{n-1}}{(y+1)^{m+n}} d y \\ldots . . \\text { (i) }\n\\]\n\nSimilarly, \\(I_{m, n}=\\int_{0}^{1} x^{n-1} \\cdot(1-x)^{m-1} d x\\)\n\n\\[\n\\Rightarrow I_{m, n}=\\int_{0}^{\\infty} \\frac{y^{m-1}}{(y+1)^{m+n}} d y \\ldots . . \\text { (ii) }\n\\]\n\nFrom (i) \\& (ii)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& 2 I_{m, n}=\\int_{0}^{\\infty} \\frac{y^{m+1}+y^{n-1}}{(y+1)^{m+n}} d y \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 2 I_{m, n}=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{y^{m+1}+y^{n-1}}{(y+1)^{m+n}} d y+\\int_{0}^{\\infty} \\frac{y^{m+1}+y^{n-1}}{(y+1)^{m+n}} d y=I_{1}+I_{2}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nPut \\(y=\\frac{1}{z}\\) in \\(I_{2}\\)\n\n\\[\nd y=-\\frac{1}{z^{2}} d z\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\Rightarrow 2 I_{m, n}=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{y^{m+1}+y^{n-1}}{(y+1)^{m+n}} d y+\\int_{1}^{0} \\frac{z^{m+1}+z^{n-1}}{(z+1)^{m+n}}(-d z) \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow I_{m, n}=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{y^{m+1}+y^{n-1}}{(y+1)^{m+n}} d y \\Rightarrow \\alpha=1\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "1",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 21
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "question": "Let the normals at all the points on a given curve pass through a fixed point \\((\\mathrm{a}, b)\\). If the curve passes through \\((3,-3)\\) and \\((4,-2 \\sqrt{2})\\), and given that \\(a-2 \\sqrt{2} b=3\\), then \\(\\left(\\mathrm{a}^{2}+\\mathrm{b}^{2}+\\mathrm{ab}\\right)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "Let the equation of normal is \\(\\mathrm{Y}-\\mathrm{y}=-\\frac{1}{m}(X-x)\\), where, \\(\\mathrm{m}=\\frac{d y}{d x}\\)\n\nAs it passes through \\((a, b)\\)\n\n\\(b-y=-\\frac{1}{m}(a-x)=-\\frac{d x}{d y}(a-x)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow(b-y) d y=(x-a) d x\\)\n\nby \\(-\\frac{y^{2}}{2}=\\frac{x^{2}}{2}-a x+c \\ldots\\).\n\nIt passes through \\((3,-3) \\&(4,-2 \\sqrt{2})\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore-3 b-\\frac{9}{2}=\\frac{9}{2}-3 a+c\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow-6 b-9=9-6 a+2 c\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 6 a-6 b-2 c=18\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 3 a-3 b-c=9 \\ldots\\)\n\nAlso,\\\\\n\\(-2 \\sqrt{2} b-4=8-4 a+c\\)\n\n\\(4 a-2 \\sqrt{2} b-c=12 \\ldots .\\). (iii)\n\nAlso, \\(a-2 \\sqrt{2} b=3 \\ldots\\) (iv) (given)\n\n\\((i i)-(i i i) \\Rightarrow-a+(2 \\sqrt{2}-3) b=-3 \\ldots(\\mathrm{v})\\)\n\n\\((i v)+(v) \\Rightarrow b=0, a=3\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore a^{2}+b^{2}+a b=9\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "9",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 21
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "question": "The area bounded by the lines \\(y=|| x-1|-2|\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "Question is incomplete it should be area bounded by \\(y=\\| x-1|-2|\\) and \\(y\\) \\(=2\\).",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "8",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 21
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int_{0}^{\\pi}\\left|\\sin ^{2} 2 x\\right| d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\pi}|\\sin 2 x| d x\\)\n\n\\(I=2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2}|\\sin 2 x| d x=2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin 2 x d x\\)\n\n\\(I=2\\left[\\frac{-\\cos (2 x)}{2}\\right]_{0}^{\\pi / 2}=2\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "2",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 21
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{-2}^{2}\\left|3 x^{2}-3 x-6\\right| d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(23 x^{2}-x-2=(x-2)(x+1)\\)\n\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\int_{-2}^{2} 3\\left|x^{2}-x-2\\right| d x \\\\\n& =3 \\int_{-2}^{2}\\left|x^{2}-x-2\\right| d x \\\\\n& =3\\left[\\int_{-2}^{-1}\\left(x^{2}-x-2\\right) d x+\\int_{-1}^{2}-\\left(x^{2}-x-2\\right) d x\\right] \\\\\n& =3\\left[\\left.\\left(\\frac{x^{3}}{3}-\\frac{x^{2}}{2}-2 x\\right)\\right|_{-2} ^{-1}-\\left(\\frac{x^{3}}{3}-\\frac{x^{2}}{2}-2 x\\right)_{-1}^{2}\\right] \\\\\n& =3\\left[7-\\frac{2}{3}\\right] \\\\\n& =19\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "19",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 21
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "question": "The graphs of sine and cosine functions, intersect each other at a number of points and between two consecutive points of intersection, the two graphs enclose the same area \\(\\mathrm{A}\\). Then \\(\\mathrm{A}^{4}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& A=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{5 \\pi}{4}}(\\sin x-\\cos x) d x \\\\\n& =[-\\cos x-\\sin x]_{\\pi / 4}^{5 \\pi / 4} \\\\\n& =-\\left[\\left(\\cos \\frac{5 \\pi}{4}+\\sin \\frac{5 \\pi}{4}\\right)-\\left(\\cos \\frac{\\pi}{4}+\\sin \\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)\\right]\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =-\\left[\\left(-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}\\right)-\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}+\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}\\right)\\right] \\\\\n& =\\frac{4}{\\sqrt{2}}=2 \\sqrt{2} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow A^{4}=(2 \\sqrt{2})^{4}=64\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "64",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 21
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "question": "If \\(\\int_{-a}^{a}(|x|+|x-2|) d x=22, (\\mathrm{a}>2)\\) and \\([\\mathrm{x}]\\) denotes the greatest integer \\(\\leq \\mathrm{x}\\), then \\(\\int_{-a}^{a}(x+[x]) d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "N",
            "U",
            "L",
            "L"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(\\int_{-a}^{a}(|x|+|x-2|) d x=22\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\int_{-a}^{0}(-2 x+2) d x+\\int_{0}^{2}(x+2-x) d x+\\int_{2}^{a}(2 x-2) d x=22\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow x^{2}-\\left.2 x\\right|_{0} ^{-a}+\\left.2 x\\right|_{0} ^{2}+x^{2}-\\left.2 x\\right|_{2} ^{a}=22\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow a^{2}+2 a+4+a^{2}-2 a-(4-4)=22\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 2 a^{2}=18 \\Rightarrow a=3\\)\n\n\\(\\int_{3}^{-3}(x+[x]) d x=-\\left(\\int_{-3}^{3}(x+[x]) d x\\right)=-\\left(\\int_{-3}^{3}[x] d x\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=-\\left(\\int_{-3}^{-2}[x] d x+\\int_{-2}^{-1}[x] d x+\\int_{-1}^{0}[x] d x\\right.\\)\n\n\\(\\left.+\\int_{0}^{1}[x] d x+\\int_{1}^{2}[x] d x+\\int_{2}^{3}[x] d x\\right)\\)\n\n\\(=-(-3-2-1+0+1+2)=3\\)",
        "question_type": "Numerical",
        "answer": "3",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 21
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "question": "The function \\(f(x)\\) that satisfies the condition \\(f(x)=x+\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin x \\cdot \\cos y f(y) d y\\), is:",
        "options": [
            "x+\\frac{2}{3}(\\pi-2) \\sin x",
            "x+(\\pi+2) \\sin x",
            "x+\\frac{\\pi}{2} \\sin x",
            "x+(\\pi-2) \\sin x"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\nf(x)=x+\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin x \\cos y f(y) d y\n\\]\n\n\\(f(x)=x+\\sin x \\underbrace{\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\cos y f(y) d y}_{K}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(x)=x+K \\sin x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f(y)=y+K \\sin y\\)\n\nNow, \\(K=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} y \\cos y d y+K \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\cos y \\sin y d y\\)\n\nApply IBP Put \\(\\sin y=t\\)\n\n\\(K=(y \\sin y)_{0}^{\\pi / 2}-\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\sin y d y+K \\int_{0}^{1} t d t\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow K=\\frac{\\pi}{2}-1+K\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow K=\\pi-2\\)\n\nSo, \\(f(x)=x+(\\pi-2) \\sin x\\)\n\nOption (d)\n\nAns 49\n\\(A=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}((\\sin x+\\cos x)-|\\cos x-\\sin x|) d x\\)\n\n\\(A=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}((\\sin x+\\cos x)-(\\cos x-\\sin x)) d x+\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}((\\sin x+\\cos x)-(\\sin x-\\cos x)) d x\\)\n\n\\(A=2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin x d x+2 \\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\cos x d x\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& A=-2\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}-1\\right)+\\left(1-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}\\right) \\\\\n& A=4-2 \\sqrt{2}=2 \\sqrt{2}(\\sqrt{2}-1)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nOption (a)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 22
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "question": "The area enclosed by the curves \\(y=\\sin x+\\cos x\\) and \\(y=|\\cos x-\\sin x|\\) and the lines \\(x=0, x=\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "2 \\sqrt{2}(\\sqrt{2}-1)",
            "2(\\sqrt{2}+1)",
            "4(\\sqrt{2}-1)",
            "2 \\sqrt{2}(\\sqrt{2}+1)"
        ],
        "solution": "No solution provided",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 22
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "question": "Let \\(f: R \\rightarrow R\\) be a continuous function. Then \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow \\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{\\frac{\\pi}{4} \\int_{2}^{\\sec ^{2} x} f(x) d x}{x^{2}-\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{16}}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "f(2)",
            "2 f(2)",
            "2 f(\\sqrt{2})",
            "4 f(2)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\lim _{x \\rightarrow \\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{\\frac{\\pi}{4} \\int_{2}^{\\sec ^{2} x} f(x) d x}{x^{2}-\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{16}} \\\\\n& =\\lim _{x \\rightarrow \\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{\\pi}{4} \\cdot \\frac{\\left[f\\left(\\sec ^{2} x\\right) \\cdot 2 \\sec x \\cdot \\sec x \\tan x\\right]}{2 x} \\\\\n& =\\lim _{x \\rightarrow \\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{\\pi}{4} f\\left(\\sec ^{2} x\\right) \\sec ^{3} x \\cdot \\frac{\\sin x}{x} \\\\\n& =\\frac{\\pi}{4} f(2) \\cdot(\\sqrt{2})^{3} \\cdot \\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\times \\frac{4}{\\pi} \\\\\n& =2 f(2)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 22
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "question": "If \\([x]\\) is the greatest integer \\(\\leq x\\), then \\(\\pi^{2} \\int_{0}^{2}\\left(\\sin \\frac{\\pi x}{2}\\right)(x-[x])^{[x]} d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "2(\\pi-1)",
            "4(\\pi-1)",
            "4(\\pi+1)",
            "2(\\pi+1)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=\\pi^{2} \\int_{0}^{2} \\sin \\left(\\frac{\\pi x}{2}\\right)(x-[x])^{[x]} d x \\\\\n& =\\pi^{2} \\int_{0}^{1} \\sin \\left(\\frac{\\pi x}{2}\\right) x^{0} d x+\\pi^{2} \\int_{1}^{2} \\sin \\left(\\frac{\\pi x}{2}\\right)(x-1) d x \\\\\n& =\\pi^{2}\\left[\\frac{-2}{\\pi} \\cos \\frac{\\pi x}{2}\\right]_{0}^{1}+\\pi^{2}\\left[(x-1) \\frac{2}{\\pi}\\left(-\\cos \\frac{\\pi x}{2}\\right)\\right]_{1}^{2}+\\pi^{2} \\int_{1}^{2} \\frac{2}{\\pi} \\cos \\frac{\\pi x}{2} d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\pi^{2}\\left(\\frac{2}{\\pi}\\right)+\\frac{2 \\pi^{2}}{\\pi}(1-0)+\\left.2 \\pi \\cdot \\frac{2}{\\pi}\\left(\\sin \\frac{\\pi x}{2}\\right)\\right|_{1} ^{2}\\)\n\n\\(=2 \\pi+2 \\pi+4(0-1)=4 \\pi-4=4(\\pi-1)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 22
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "question": "Let \\(f\\) be a non-negative function in \\([0,1]\\) and twice differentiable in \\((0,1)\\). If \\(\\int_{0}^{x} \\sqrt{1-\\left(f^{\\prime}(t)\\right)^{2}} d t=\\int_{0}^{x} f(t) d t, 0 \\leq x \\leq 1\\) and \\(f(0)=0\\), then \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0} \\frac{1}{x^{2}} \\int_{0}^{x} f(t) d t\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "equals 0",
            "equals 1",
            "does not exist",
            "equals \\frac{1}{2}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(\\int_{0}^{x} \\sqrt{1-\\left(f^{\\prime}(t)\\right)^{2}} d t=\\int_{0}^{x} f(t) d t, 0 \\leq x \\leq 1\\)\n\ndifferentiating both the sides\n\n\\(\\sqrt{1-\\left(f^{\\prime}(x)\\right)^{2}}=f(x)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow 1-\\left(f^{\\prime}(x)\\right)^{2}=f^{2}(x)\\)\n\n\\(\\frac{f^{\\prime}(x)}{\\sqrt{1-f^{2}(x)}}=1\\)\n\n\\(\\sin ^{-1} f(x)=x+C\\)\n\n\\(\\because f(0)=0 \\Rightarrow C=0 \\Rightarrow f(x)=\\sin x\\)\n\nNow, \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0} \\frac{\\int_{0}^{x} \\sin t d t}{x^{2}}\\left(\\frac{0}{0}\\right)=\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 22
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\sqrt{x} d x}{(1+x)(1+3 x)(3+x)}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{\\pi}{8}\\left(1-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\right)",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\left(1-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{6}\\right)",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{8}\\left(1-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{6}\\right)",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\left(1-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\right)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\nI=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\sqrt{x} d x}{(1+x)(1+3 x)(3+x)} d x\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { Let } \\mathrm{x}=\\mathrm{t}^{2} \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{dx}=2 \\mathrm{t} . \\mathrm{dt} \\\\\n& I=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{t(2 t)}{\\left(t^{2}+1\\right)\\left(1+3 t^{2}\\right)\\left(3+t^{2}\\right)} d t \\\\\n& I=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\left(3 t^{2}+1\\right)-\\left(t^{2}+1\\right)}{\\left(3 t^{2}+1\\right)\\left(t^{2}+1\\right)\\left(3+t^{2}\\right)} d t \\\\\n& I=\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d t}{\\left(t^{2}+1\\right)\\left(3+t^{2}\\right)}-\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d t}{\\left(1+3 t^{2}\\right)\\left(3+t^{2}\\right)} \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\left(3+t^{2}\\right)-\\left(t^{2}+1\\right)}{\\left(t^{2}+1\\right)\\left(3+t^{2}\\right)} d t+\\frac{1}{8} \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\left(1+3 t^{2}\\right)-3\\left(3+t^{2}\\right)}{\\left(1+3 t^{2}\\right)\\left(3+t^{2}\\right)} d t \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d t}{1+t^{2}}-\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d t}{t^{2}+3}+\\frac{1}{8} \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d t}{t^{2}+3}-\\frac{3}{8} \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d t}{\\left(1+3 t^{2}\\right)} \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d t}{t^{2}+1}-\\frac{3}{8} \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d t}{t^{2}+3}-\\frac{3}{8} \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{d t}{1+3 t^{2}} \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\tan ^{-1}(t)\\right)_{0}^{1}-\\frac{3}{8 \\sqrt{3}}\\left(\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{t}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)\\right)_{0}^{1}-\\frac{3}{8 \\sqrt{3}}\\left(\\tan ^{-1}(\\sqrt{3} t)\\right)_{0}^{1} \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}\\right)-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{8}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{6}\\right)-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{8}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right) \\\\\n& =\\frac{\\pi}{8}-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{16} \\pi \\\\\n& =\\frac{\\pi}{8}\\left(1-\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\\right)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 22
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "question": "The area of the region bounded by the parabola \\((y-2)^{2}=(x-1)\\), the tangent to it at the point whose ordinate is 3 and the \\(\\mathrm{x}\\)-axis is:",
        "options": [
            "9",
            "10",
            "4",
            "6"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\ny=3 \\Rightarrow x=2\n\\]\n\nPoint is \\((2,3)\\)\n\nDiff. w.r.t \\(x\\)\n\n\\(2(y-2) y^{\\prime}=1\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow y^{\\prime}=\\frac{1}{2(y-2)}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow y_{(2,3)}^{\\prime}=\\frac{1}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{y-3}{x-2}=\\frac{1}{2} \\Rightarrow x-2 y+4=0\\)\n\nArea \\(=\\int_{0}^{3}\\left((y-2)^{2}+1-(2 y-4)\\right) d y\\)\n\n\\(=9\\) sq. units\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-081}\n\\end{center}",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 22
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int_{6}^{16} \\frac{\\log _{e} x^{2}}{\\log _{e} x^{2}+\\log _{e}\\left(x^{2}-44 x+484\\right)} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "6",
            "8",
            "5",
            "10"
        ],
        "solution": "Let \\(I=\\int_{6}^{16} \\frac{\\log _{e} x^{2}}{\\log _{e} x^{2}+\\log _{e}\\left(x^{2}-44 x+484\\right)} d x\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int_{6}^{16} \\frac{\\log _{e} x^{2}}{\\log _{e} x^{2}+\\log _{e}\\left(x^{2}-22\\right)} d x \\ldots\\)\n\nWe know,\n\n\\(\\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\) (king)\n\nSo, \\(I=\\int_{6}^{16} \\frac{\\log _{e}(22-x)^{2}}{\\log _{e}(22-x)^{2}+\\log _{e}(21-(22-x))^{2}}\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int_{6}^{16} \\frac{\\log _{e}(22-x)^{2}}{\\log _{e} x^{2}+\\log _{e}(22-x)^{2}} d x \\ldots\\)\n\n(1) \\(+(2)\\)\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{6}^{16} 1 . d x=10\\)\n\n\\(I=5\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 22
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "question": "If \\(U_{n}=\\left(1+\\frac{1}{n^{2}}\\right)\\left(1+\\frac{2^{2}}{n^{2}}\\right)^{2} \\ldots \\left(1+\\frac{n^{2}}{n^{2}}\\right)^{n}\\), then \\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty}\\left(U_{n}\\right)^{\\frac{-4}{n^{2}}}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{e^{2}}{16}",
            "\\frac{4}{e}",
            "\\frac{16}{e^{2}}",
            "\\frac{4}{e^{2}}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(U_{n}=\\prod_{r=1}^{n}\\left(1+\\frac{r^{2}}{n^{2}}\\right)^{r}\\)\n\n\\(L=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty}\\left(U_{n}\\right)^{-4 / n^{2}}\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\log L=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{-4}{n^{2}} \\sum_{r=1}^{n} \\log \\left(1+\\frac{r^{2}}{n^{2}}\\right)^{r} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\log L=\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\sum_{r=1}^{n}-\\frac{4 r}{n} \\cdot \\frac{1}{n} \\log \\left(1+\\frac{r^{2}}{n^{2}}\\right) \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\log L=-4 \\int_{0}^{1} x \\log \\left(1+x^{2}\\right) d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nput \\(1+x^{2}=t\\)\n\nNow, \\(2 x d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(=-2 \\int_{1}^{2} \\log (t) d t=-2[t \\log t-t]_{1}^{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\log L=-2(2 \\log 2-1)\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore L=e^{-2(2 \\log 2-1)}\\)\n\n\\(=e^{-2\\left(\\log \\left(\\frac{4}{e}\\right)\\right)}\\)\n\n\\(=e^{\\log \\left(\\frac{4}{e}\\right)^{2}}\\)\n\n\\(=\\left(\\frac{e}{4}\\right)^{2}=\\frac{e^{2}}{16}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 22
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}\\left(\\frac{1+\\sin ^{2} x}{1+\\pi^{\\sin x}}\\right) d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{\\pi}{2}",
            "\\frac{5 \\pi}{4}",
            "\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}",
            "\\frac{3 \\pi}{2}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\frac{\\left(1+\\sin ^{2} x\\right)}{\\left(1+\\pi^{\\sin x}\\right)}+\\frac{\\pi^{\\sin x}\\left(1+\\sin ^{2} x\\right)}{\\left(1+\\pi^{\\sin x}\\right)} d x \\\\\n& I=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}\\left(1+\\sin ^{2} x\\right) d x \\\\\n& I=\\frac{\\pi}{2}+\\frac{\\pi}{2} \\cdot \\frac{1}{2}=\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 22
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "question": "If the value of the integral \\(\\int_{0}^{5} \\frac{x+[x]}{e^{x-[x]}} d x=\\alpha e^{-1}+\\beta\\), where \\(\\alpha, \\beta \\in \\mathrm{R}\\), \\(5 \\alpha+6 \\beta=0\\), and \\([x]\\) denotes the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(x\\), then the value of \\((\\alpha+\\beta)^{2}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "100",
            "25",
            "16",
            "36"
        ],
        "solution": "NULL",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 23
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{\\frac{-1}{\\sqrt{2}}}^{\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}}\\left(\\left(\\frac{x+1}{x-1}\\right)^{2}+\\left(\\frac{x-1}{x+1}\\right)^{2}-2\\right)^{\\frac{1}{2}} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\log _{e} 4",
            "\\log _{e} 16",
            "2 \\log _{e} 16",
            "4 \\log _{e}(3+2 \\sqrt{2})"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=\\int_{\\frac{-1}{\\sqrt{2}}}^{\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}}\\left(\\left(\\frac{x+1}{x-1}-\\frac{x-1}{x+1}\\right)^{2}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{2}} d x \\\\\n& I=\\int_{\\frac{-1}{\\sqrt{2}}}^{\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}}\\left|\\frac{4 x}{x^{2}-1}\\right| d x \\Rightarrow I=2.4 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}}\\left|\\frac{x}{x^{2}-1}\\right| d x \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow I=-4 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}} \\frac{2 x}{x^{2}-1} d x \\Rightarrow I=-4 \\ln \\left|x^{2}-1\\right|_{0}^{\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow I=4 \\ln 2 \\Rightarrow I=\\ln 16\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 23
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "question": "If the area of the bounded region \\(R=\\left\\{(x, y): \\max \\left\\{0, \\log _{e} x\\right\\} \\leq y \\leq 2^{x}, \\frac{1}{2} \\leq x \\leq 2\\right\\}\\) is, \\(\\alpha\\left(\\log _{e} 2\\right)^{-1}+\\beta\\left(\\log _{e} 2\\right)+\\gamma\\), then the value of \\((\\alpha+\\beta-2 \\gamma)^{2}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "8",
            "2",
            "4",
            "1"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\nR=\\left\\{(x, y): \\max \\left\\{0, \\log _{e} x\\right\\} \\leq y \\leq 2^{x}, \\frac{1}{2} \\leq x \\leq 2\\right\\}\n\\]\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-085}\n\\end{center}\n\n\\(\\int_{\\frac{1}{2}}^{2} 2^{x} d x-\\int_{1}^{2} \\ln x d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow\\left[\\frac{2^{x}}{\\ln 2}\\right]_{1 / 2}^{2}-[x \\ln x-x]_{1}^{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{\\left(2^{2}\\right)-2^{1 / 2}}{\\log _{e} 2}-(2 \\ln 2-1)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{\\left(2^{2}-\\sqrt{2}\\right)}{\\log _{e} 2}-2 \\ln 2+1\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\alpha=2^{2}-\\sqrt{2}, \\beta=-2, \\gamma=1\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore(\\alpha+\\beta+2 \\gamma)^{2}\\)\n\n\\(=\\left(2^{2}-\\sqrt{2}-2-2\\right)^{2}\\)\n\n\\(=(\\sqrt{2})^{2}=2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 23
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "question": "The value of the definite integral \\(\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{d x}{\\left(1+e^{x \\cos x}\\right)\\left(\\sin ^{4} x+\\cos ^{4} x\\right)}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "-\\frac{\\pi}{2}",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{2 \\sqrt{2}}",
            "-\\frac{\\pi}{4}",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{\\sqrt{2}}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(I=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{d x}{\\left(1+e^{x \\cos x}\\right)\\left(\\sin ^{4} x+\\cos ^{4} x\\right)} \\ldots\\).\n\nUsing \\(\\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{d x}{\\left(1+e^{-x \\cos x}\\right)\\left(\\sin ^{4} x+\\cos ^{4} x\\right)}\\)\n\nAdd (1) and (2)\n\n\\(2 I=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{d x}{\\sin ^{4} x+\\cos ^{4} x}\\)\n\n\\(2 I=2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{d x}{\\sin ^{4} x+\\cos ^{4} x}\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{4}} \\frac{\\left(1+\\frac{1}{\\tan ^{2} x}\\right) \\sec ^{2} x}{\\left(\\tan -\\frac{1}{\\tan x}\\right)^{2}+2} d x\\)\n\n\\(\\tan x-\\frac{1}{\\tan x}=t\\)\n\n\\(\\left(1+\\frac{1}{\\tan ^{2} x}\\right) \\sec ^{2} x d x=d t\\)\n\n\\(I=\\int_{-\\infty}^{0} \\frac{d t}{t^{2}+2}=\\left[\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{t}{\\sqrt{2}}\\right)\\right]_{-\\infty}^{0}\\)\n\n\\(I=0-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}\\left(-\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\right)=\\frac{\\pi}{2 \\sqrt{2}}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 23
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n} \\sum_{j=1}^{n} \\frac{(2 j-1)+8 n}{(2 j-1)+4 n}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "5+\\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{3}{2}\\right)",
            "2-\\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{2}{3}\\right)",
            "3+2 \\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{2}{3}\\right)",
            "1+2 \\log _{e}\\left(\\frac{3}{2}\\right)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\lim _{n \\rightarrow \\infty} \\frac{1}{n} \\sum_{j=1}^{n} \\frac{\\left(\\frac{2 j}{n}-\\frac{1}{n}+8\\right)}{\\left(\\frac{2 j}{n}-\\frac{1}{n}+4\\right)} \\\\\n& \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{2 x+8}{2 x+4} d x=\\int_{0}^{1} d x+\\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{4}{2 x+4} d x \\\\\n& =1+4 \\frac{1}{2}(\\ln |2 x+4|)_{0}^{1} \\\\\n& =1+2 \\ln \\left(\\frac{3}{2}\\right)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 23
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int_{-1}^{1} \\log \\left(x+\\sqrt{x^{2}+1}\\right) d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "2",
            "0",
            "-1",
            "1"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { Let } I=\\int_{-1}^{1} \\log \\left(x+\\sqrt{x^{2}+1}\\right) d x \\\\\n& \\because \\log \\left(x+\\sqrt{x^{2}+1}\\right) \\text { is an odd function } \\\\\n& \\therefore \\mathrm{I}=0\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 23
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "question": "If \\(f(x)\\) is not continuous at \\(x=2\\), then which of the following statements is incorrect?",
        "options": [
            "f(x) is not continuous at \\(x=2\\)",
            "f(x) is everywhere differentiable",
            "f(x) is continuous but not differentiable at \\(x=2\\)",
            "f(x) is not differentiable at \\(x=1\\)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& f(x)=\\int_{0}^{1}(5+(1-t)) d t+\\int_{1}^{x}(5+(t-1)) d t \\\\\n& =6-\\frac{1}{2}+\\left.\\left(4 t+\\frac{t^{2}}{2}\\right)\\right|_{1} ^{x} \\\\\n& =\\frac{11}{2}+4 x+\\frac{x^{2}}{2}-4-\\frac{1}{2}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\frac{x^{2}}{2}+4 x-1\\)\n\n\\(f\\left(2^{+}\\right)=2+8+1=11\\)\n\n\\(f(2)=f\\left(2^{-}\\right)=5 \\times 2+1=11\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow\\) continuous at \\(x=2\\)\n\nClearly differentiable at \\(x=1\\)\n\n\\(L f^{\\prime}(2)=5\\)\n\n\\(R f^{\\prime}(2)=6\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow\\) Not differentiable at \\(x=2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 23
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "question": "Let \\(f:(a, b) \\rightarrow R\\) be twice differentiable function such that \\(f(x)=\\int_{a}^{x} g(t) d t\\) for a differentiable function \\(g(x)\\). If \\(f(x)=0\\) has exactly five distinct roots in \\((a, b)\\), then \\(g(x) g^{\\prime}(x)=0\\) has at least:",
        "options": [
            "twelve roots in (a, b)",
            "five roots in (a, b)",
            "seven roots in (a, b)",
            "three roots in (a, b)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& f(x)=\\int_{a}^{x} g(t) d t \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{f}^{\\prime}(\\mathrm{x})=\\mathrm{g}(\\mathrm{x}) \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{f}^{\\prime \\prime}(\\mathrm{x})=\\mathrm{g}^{\\prime}(\\mathrm{x})\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nGiven, \\(g(x) \\cdot g^{\\prime}(x)=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f^{\\prime}(x) \\cdot f^{\\prime \\prime}(x)=0\\)\n\nAlso given \\(f(x)\\) has exactly 5 roots.\n\nSo from Rolle's theorem we can say,\n\n\\(f^{\\prime}(x)\\) has 4 roots and \\(f^{\\prime \\prime}(x)\\) has 3 roots.\n\n\\(\\therefore f^{\\prime}(x) \\cdot f^{\\prime \\prime}(x)=0\\) has \\(4+3=7\\) roots.",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 23
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "question": "The area of the region bounded by \\(y-x=2\\) and \\(x^{2}=y\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{16}{3}",
            "\\frac{2}{3}",
            "\\frac{9}{2}",
            "\\frac{4}{3}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-089}\n\\end{center}\n\n\\(y-x=2, x^{2}=y\\)\n\nNow, \\(x^{2}=2+x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow x^{2}-x-2=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow(x+1)(x-2)=0\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { Area }=\\int_{-1}^{2}\\left(2+x-x^{2}\\right) \\\\\n& =\\left|2 x+\\frac{x^{2}}{2}-\\frac{x^{3}}{3}\\right|_{-1}^{2} \\\\\n& =\\left(4+2-\\frac{8}{3}\\right)-\\left(-2+\\frac{1}{2}+\\frac{1}{3}\\right) \\\\\n& =6-3+2-\\frac{1}{2}=\\frac{9}{2}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 23
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "question": "Where \\([x]\\) is the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(x\\). Which of the following is true?",
        "options": [
            "f is continuous at every point in \\([0, \\infty)\\) and differentiable except at the integer points.",
            "f is both continuous and differentiable except at the integer points in \\([0, \\infty)\\).",
            "f is continuous everywhere except at the integer points in \\([0, \\infty)\\).",
            "f is differentiable at every point in \\([0, \\infty)\\)."
        ],
        "solution": "\\(f:[0, \\infty) \\rightarrow[0, \\infty), f(x)=\\int_{0}^{x}[y] d y\\)\n\nLet \\(x=n+f, f \\in(0,1)\\)\n\nSo, \\(f(x)=0+1+2+\\ldots+(n-1)+\\int_{n}^{n+f} n d y\\)\n\n\\(f(x)=\\frac{n(n-1)}{2}+n f\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{[x]([x]-1)}{2}+[x]\\{x\\}\\)\n\nNote \\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow n^{+}} f(x)=\\frac{n(n-1)}{2}, \\lim _{x \\rightarrow n^{-}} f(x)=\\frac{(n-1)(n-2)}{2}+(n-1)\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{n(n-1)}{2}\\)\n\n\\(f(x)=\\frac{n(n-1)}{2}\\left(n \\in N_{0}\\right)\\)\n\nso \\(f(x)\\) is cont. \\(\\forall x \\geq 0\\) nd diff. except at integer points",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 23
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "question": "The area (in sq units) of the region, given by the set \\(\\left\\{(x, y) \\in R \\times R \\mid x \\geq 0,2 x^{2} \\leq y \\leq 4-2 x\\right\\}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{8}{3}",
            "\\frac{17}{3}",
            "\\frac{13}{3}",
            "\\frac{7}{3}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-091}\n\\end{center}\n\nRequired area \\(=\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(4-2 x-2 x^{2}\\right) d x=4 x-x^{2}-\\left.\\frac{2 x^{3}}{3}\\right|_{0} ^{1}\\)\n\n\\(=4-1-\\frac{2}{3}=\\frac{7}{3}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 24
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "question": "The value of the definite integral \\(\\int_{\\pi / 24}^{5 \\pi / 24} \\frac{d x}{1+\\sqrt[3]{\\tan 2 x}}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{\\pi}{3}",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{6}",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{12}",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{18}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\text { Let } I=\\int_{\\pi / 24}^{5 \\pi / 24} \\frac{(\\cos 2 x)^{1 / 3}}{(\\cos 2 x)^{1 / 3}+(\\sin 2 x)^{1 / 3}} d x \\ldots \\ldots\n\\]\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\int_{\\pi / 2}^{5 \\pi / 24} \\frac{\\left(\\cos \\left\\{2\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-x\\right)\\right\\}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}}{\\left(\\cos \\left\\{2\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-x\\right)\\right\\}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}+\\left(\\sin \\left\\{2\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4}-x\\right)\\right\\}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}} d x\\left\\{\\int_{a}^{b} f(x) d x=\\int_{a}^{b} f(a+b-x) d x\\right\\}\\)\n\nSo, \\(I=\\int_{\\pi / 24}^{5 \\pi / 24} \\frac{(\\sin 2 x)^{1 / 3}}{(\\sin 2 x)^{1 / 3}+(\\sin 2 x)^{1 / 3}} d x \\ldots\\).\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { Hence, } 2 I=\\int_{\\pi / 24}^{5 \\pi / 24} d x[(\\mathrm{i})+(\\mathrm{ii})] \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 2 I=\\frac{4 \\pi}{24} \\Rightarrow I=\\frac{\\pi}{12}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 24
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "question": "If \\(\\int_{0}^{100 \\pi} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{e^{\\left(\\frac{x}{\\pi}-\\left[\\frac{x}{\\pi}\\right]\\right)}} d x=\\frac{\\alpha \\pi^{3}}{1+4 \\pi^{2}}, \\alpha \\in R\\) where \\([x]\\) is the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(x\\), then the value of \\(\\alpha\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "200\\left(1-e^{-1}\\right)",
            "100(1-e)",
            "50(e-1)",
            "150\\left(e^{-1}-1\\right)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\nI=\\int_{0}^{100 \\pi} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{e^{\\left(\\frac{x}{\\pi}-\\left[\\frac{x}{\\pi}\\right]\\right)}} d x\n\\]\n\n\\(\\because\\) Integrand is periodic with period 1\n\n\\[\n\\therefore I=100 \\int_{0}^{\\pi} \\frac{\\sin ^{2} x}{e^{\\left.\\frac{x}{\\pi}\\right\\}}} d x\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { Let } \\frac{x}{\\pi}=t \\Rightarrow d x=\\pi d t \\\\\n& =100 \\pi \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{\\sin ^{2}(\\pi t) d t}{e^{t}} \\\\\n& =50 \\pi \\int_{0}^{1} e^{-t}(1-\\cos 2 \\pi t) d t \\\\\n& =50 \\pi \\int_{0}^{1} e^{-t} d t-50 \\pi \\int_{0}^{1} e^{-t} \\cos (2 \\pi t) d t \\\\\n& =-50\\left[e^{-t}\\right]_{0}^{1}-50 \\pi\\left[\\frac{e^{-t}}{1+4 \\pi^{2}}(-\\cos 2 \\pi t+2 \\pi \\sin 2 \\pi t)\\right]_{0}^{1} \\\\\n& =-50 \\pi\\left(e^{-1}-1\\right)-\\frac{50 \\pi}{1+4 \\pi^{2}}\\left(e^{-1}(-1+0)-(-1+0)\\right) \\\\\n& =-50 \\pi\\left(e^{-1}-1\\right)-\\frac{50 \\pi\\left(1-e^{-1}\\right)}{1+4 \\pi^{2}}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n=\\frac{200 \\pi^{3}\\left(1-e^{-1}\\right)}{1+4 \\pi^{2}}=\\frac{\\alpha \\pi^{3}}{1+4 \\pi^{3}} \\text { (Given) }\n\\]\n\n\\(\\therefore \\alpha=200\\left(1-e^{-1}\\right)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 24
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "question": "Let \\(g(t)=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4} t+f(x)\\right) d x\\), where \\(f(x)=\\log _{e}\\left(x+\\sqrt{x^{2}+1}\\right), x \\in R\\). Then which one of the following is correct?",
        "options": [
            "g(1)=g(0)",
            "\\sqrt{2} g(1)=g(0)",
            "g(1)=\\sqrt{2} g(0)",
            "g(1)+g(0)=0"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(\\because f(x)=\\ln \\left(x+\\sqrt{x^{2}+1}\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore f(x)+f(-x)=\\ln \\left(\\sqrt{x^{2}+1}+x\\right)+\\ln \\left(\\sqrt{x^{2}+1}-x\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore f(x)+f(-x)=0\\)\n\n\\(\\because g(t)=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4} t+f(x)\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2}\\left\\{\\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4} t+f(x)\\right)+\\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi}{4} t+f(-x)\\right)\\right\\} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2}\\left\\{\\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi t}{4}+f(x)\\right)+\\cos \\left(\\frac{\\pi t}{4}-f(x)\\right)\\right\\} d x\\)\n\n\\(g(t)=2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\cos \\frac{\\pi t}{4} \\cdot \\cos (f(x)) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore g(1)=\\sqrt{2} \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\cos (f(x)) d x\\) and\n\n\\(g(0)=2 \\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2} \\cos (f(x)) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\sqrt{2} g(1)=g(0)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 24
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "question": "Let \\(y=y(x)\\) satisfies the equation \\(\\frac{d y}{d x}-|A|=0\\), for all \\(x>0\\), where \\(A=\\left[\\begin{array}{ccc}y & \\sin x & 1 \\\\ 0 & -1 & 1 \\\\ 2 & 0 & \\frac{1}{x}\\end{array}\\right]\\). If \\(y(\\pi)=\\pi+2\\), then the value of \\(y\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\right)\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{\\pi}{2}+\\frac{4}{\\pi}",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\frac{1}{\\pi}",
            "\\frac{3 \\pi}{2}-\\frac{1}{\\pi}",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\frac{4}{\\pi}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& |A|=-\\frac{y}{x}+2 \\sin x+2 \\\\\n& \\frac{d y}{d x}=|A| \\\\\n& \\frac{d y}{d x}=-\\frac{y}{x}+2 \\sin x+2 \\\\\n& \\frac{d y}{d x}+\\frac{y}{x}=2 \\sin x+2 \\\\\n& I . F .=e^{\\int \\frac{1}{x} d x}=x \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow y x=\\int x(2 \\sin x+2) d x \\\\\n& x y=x^{2}-2 x \\cos x+2 \\sin x+c \\ldots\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nNow, \\(\\mathrm{x}=\\pi, \\mathrm{y}=\\pi+2\\)\n\nUse in (i)\n\n\\(c=0\\)\n\nNow, (i) becomes\\\\\n\\(x y=x^{2}-2 x \\cos x+2 \\sin x\\)\n\nput \\(x=\\pi / 2\\)\n\n\\(\\frac{\\pi}{2} y=\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\right)^{2}-2 \\cdot \\frac{\\pi}{2} \\cos \\frac{\\pi}{2}+2 \\sin \\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)\n\n\\(y\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\right)=\\frac{\\pi^{2}}{4}+2\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 24
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "question": "If the real part of the complex number \\((1-\\cos \\theta+2 i \\sin \\theta)^{-1}\\) is \\(\\frac{1}{5}\\) for \\(\\theta \\in(0, \\pi)\\), then the value of the integral \\(\\int_{0}^{\\theta} \\sin x d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "2",
            "-1",
            "0"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& z=\\frac{1}{1-\\cos \\theta+2 i \\sin \\theta} \\\\\n& =\\frac{2 \\sin ^{2} \\frac{\\theta}{2}-2 i \\sin \\theta}{(1-\\cos \\theta)^{2}+4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta} \\\\\n& =\\frac{\\sin \\frac{\\theta}{2}-2 i \\cos \\frac{\\theta}{2}}{2 \\sin \\frac{\\theta}{2}\\left(\\sin ^{2} \\frac{\\theta}{2}+4 \\cos ^{2} \\frac{\\theta}{2}\\right)}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\(\\operatorname{Re}(z)=\\frac{1}{2\\left(\\sin ^{2} \\frac{\\theta}{2}+4 \\cos ^{2} \\frac{\\theta}{2}\\right)}=\\frac{1}{5}\\)\n\n\\(\\sin \\frac{2 \\theta}{2}+4 \\cos ^{2} \\frac{\\theta}{2}=\\frac{5}{2} 1-\\cos ^{2} \\frac{\\theta}{2}+4 \\cos \\frac{\\theta}{2}=\\frac{5}{2}\\)\n\n\\(3 \\cos ^{2} \\frac{\\theta}{2}=\\frac{1}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\frac{\\theta}{2}=n \\pi \\pm \\frac{\\pi}{4}\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\theta=2 n \\pi \\pm \\frac{\\pi}{2} \\\\\n& \\theta \\in(0, \\pi) \\\\\n& \\therefore \\theta=\\frac{\\pi}{2} \\\\\n& \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin \\theta d \\theta=[-\\cos \\theta]_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\\\\n& =-(0-1) \\\\\n& =1\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 24
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "question": "If \\([x]\\) denotes the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(x\\), then the value of the integral \\(\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2}[[x]-\\sin x] d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "-\\pi",
            "\\pi",
            "0",
            "1"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2}[[x]-\\sin x] d x \\\\\n& =\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2}([x]+[-\\sin x]) d x \\\\\n& =\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2}([x]+[-\\sin x]+[-x]+[\\sin x]) d x \\\\\n& =\\int_{0}^{\\pi / 2}(-2) d x \\\\\n& =-\\pi\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 24
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "question": "The value of the integral \\(\\int_{-1}^{1} \\log _{e}(\\sqrt{1-x}+\\sqrt{1+x}) d x\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{1}{2} \\log _{e} 2+\\frac{\\pi}{4}-\\frac{3}{2}",
            "2 \\log _{e} 2+\\frac{\\pi}{4}-1",
            "\\log _{e} 2+\\frac{\\pi}{2}-1",
            "2 \\log _{e} 2+\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\frac{1}{2}"
        ],
        "solution": "NULL",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 24
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "question": "Let a be a positive real number such that \\(\\int_{0}^{a} e^{x-[x]} d x=10 e-9\\) where \\([x]\\) is the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(x\\). Then a is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "10-\\log _{e}(1+e)",
            "10+\\log _{e} 2",
            "10+\\log _{e} 3",
            "10+\\log _{e}(1+e)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(a>0\\)\n\nLet \\(n \\leq a<n+1, n \\in W\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& {[a] \\quad+\\quad\\{a\\}} \\\\\n& a=\\Downarrow \\quad \\Downarrow \\\\\n& \\text { G.I.F. } \\quad \\text { Fractional part }\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nHere \\([\\mathrm{a}]=\\mathrm{n}\\)\n\nNow, \\(\\int_{0}^{a} e^{x-[x]} d x=10 e-9\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\int_{0}^{n} e^{\\{x\\}} d x+\\int_{n}^{a} e^{x-[x]} d x=10 e-9\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore n \\int_{0}^{1} e^{x} d x+\\int_{n}^{a} e^{x-n} d x=10 e-9\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow n(e-1)+\\left(e^{a-n}-1\\right)=10 e-9\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\mathrm{n}=0\\) and \\(\\{\\mathrm{a}\\}=\\log _{\\mathrm{e}} 2\\)\n\nSo, \\(a=[a]+\\{a\\}=\\left(10+\\log _{e} 2\\right)\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow\\) Option (2) is correct.",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 24
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "question": "Let \\(g(x)=\\int_{0}^{x} f(t) d t\\), where \\(f\\) is continuous function in \\([0,3]\\) such that \\(\\frac{1}{3} \\leq f(t) \\leq 1\\) for all \\(t\\) in \\([0,1]\\) and 0 \\(\\leq f(t) \\leq \\frac{1}{2}\\) for all \\(t\\) in \\((1,3]\\). The largest possible interval in which \\(g(3)\\) lies is:",
        "options": [
            "\\left[-1,-\\frac{1}{2}\\right]",
            "\\left[-\\frac{3}{2},-1\\right]",
            "[1,3]",
            "\\left[\\frac{1}{3}, 2\\right]"
        ],
        "solution": "NULL",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 24
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "question": "The area bounded by the curve \\(4 y^{2}=x^{2}(4-x)(x-2)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{\\pi}{16}",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{8}",
            "\\frac{3 \\pi}{2}",
            "\\frac{3 \\pi}{8}"
        ],
        "solution": "Given,\n\n\\(4 y^{2}=x^{2}(4-x)(x-2)\\)\n\nHere, Left hand side \\(4 y^{2}\\) is always positive. So Right hand side should also be positive.\n\nIn \\(x \\in[2,4]\\) Right hand side is positive.\n\nBy putting \\(y=-y\\) in equation (1), equation remains same. So, graph is symmetric about \\(\\mathrm{x}\\) axis.\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-098}\n\\end{center}\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { Required Area }=2 \\mathrm{~A}_{1} \\\\\n& =2 \\int_{2}^{4} y d x \\\\\n& =\\int_{2}^{4} x \\sqrt{(x-2)(4-x)} d x \\\\\n& \\text { put } x=4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta+2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow d x=[4(2 \\sin \\theta \\cos \\theta-4 \\sin \\theta \\cos \\theta)] d \\theta \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow d x=4 \\sin \\theta \\cos \\theta d \\theta\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nWhen lower limit \\(=2\\) then\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& 2=4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta+2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 4\\left(1-\\cos ^{2} \\theta\\right)+2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta=2 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 4-4 \\cos ^{2} \\theta+2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta=2 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow 2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta=2 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\theta=0, \\pi\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nWhen upper limit \\(=4\\) then\n\n\\(4=4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta+2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow-2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\theta=\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore\\) Range of \\(\\theta=0\\) to \\(\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore\\) Area \\(=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}\\left(4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta+2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta\\right) \\sqrt{\\left(2 \\sin ^{2} \\theta\\right)\\left(2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta\\right)}(4 \\sin \\theta \\cos \\theta) d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(=\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}\\left(4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta+2 \\cos ^{2} \\theta\\right) 8 \\sin ^{2} \\theta \\cos ^{2} \\theta d \\theta\\)\n\n\\(=32 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{4} \\theta \\cos ^{2} \\theta d \\theta+16 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\sin ^{2} \\theta \\cos ^{2} \\theta d \\theta\\)\n\nUsing Wallis formula,\\\\\n\\(=32 \\cdot \\frac{3 \\cdot 1 \\cdot 1}{6.4 \\cdot 2} \\cdot \\frac{\\pi}{2}+16 \\cdot \\frac{1 \\cdot 3 \\cdot 1}{6.4 \\cdot 2} \\cdot \\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)\n\n\\(=\\pi+\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{3 \\pi}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 25
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "question": "If the integral \\(\\int_{0}^{10} \\frac{[\\sin 2 \\pi x]}{e^{x-[x]}} d x=\\alpha e^{-1}+\\beta e^{-\\frac{1}{2}}+\\gamma\\), where \\(\\alpha, \\beta, \\gamma\\) are integers and \\([x]\\) denotes the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(x\\), then the value of \\(\\alpha+\\beta+\\gamma\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "0",
            "10",
            "20",
            "25"
        ],
        "solution": "Given integral\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\int_{0}^{10} \\frac{[\\sin 2 \\pi x]}{e^{x-[x]}} d x=10 \\int_{0}^{1} \\frac{[\\sin 2 \\pi x]}{e^{\\{x\\}}} d x \\text { (using property of definite in.) } \\\\\n& =10\\left[\\int_{0}^{1 / 2} 0 . d x+\\int_{1 / 2}^{1} \\frac{-1}{e^{x}} d x\\right] \\\\\n& =-10\\left[\\frac{e^{-x}}{-1}\\right]_{1 / 2}^{1}=10\\left[e^{-1}-e^{-1 / 2}\\right] \\\\\n& =10 e^{-1}-10 e^{-1 / 2}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\ncomparing with the given relation,\n\n\\[\n\\alpha=10, \\beta=-10, \\gamma=0\n\\]\n\n\\(\\alpha+\\beta+\\gamma=0\\)\n\nTherefore, the correct answer is (A).",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 25
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "question": "Let \\(f: R \\rightarrow R\\) be defined as \\(f(x)=e^{-x} \\sin x\\). If \\(F:[0,1] \\rightarrow R\\) is a differentiable function with that \\(F(x)= \\int_{0}^{x} f(t) d t\\), then the value of \\(\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(F^{\\prime}(x)+f(x)\\right) e^{x} d x\\) lies in the interval:",
        "options": [
            "\\left[\\frac{331}{360}, \\frac{334}{360}\\right]",
            "\\left[\\frac{330}{360}, \\frac{331}{360}\\right]",
            "\\left[\\frac{335}{360}, \\frac{336}{360}\\right]",
            "\\left[\\frac{327}{360}, \\frac{329}{360}\\right]"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\mathrm{F}(\\mathrm{x})=\\int_{0}^{x} f(t) d t \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\mathrm{F}^{\\prime}(\\mathrm{x})=\\mathrm{f}(\\mathrm{x}) \\text { by Leibnitz theorem } \\\\\n& \\mathrm{I}=\\int_{0}^{1}\\left(F^{\\prime}(x)+f(x)\\right) e^{x} d x=\\int_{0}^{1} 2 f(x) e^{x} d x \\\\\n& I=\\int_{0}^{1} 2 \\sin x d x \\\\\n& I=2(1-\\cos 1) \\\\\n& =2\\left\\{1-\\left(1-\\frac{1^{2}}{2!}+\\frac{1}{24}\\right)\\right\\} \\\\\n& =2\\left\\{1-\\left(1-\\frac{1}{2}+\\frac{1}{24}-\\frac{1}{720}\\right)\\right\\} \\\\\n& \\frac{330}{360}<2(1-\\cos 1)<\\frac{331}{360} \\\\\n& \\frac{330}{360}<1<\\frac{331}{360}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 25
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "question": "Which of the following statements is incorrect for the function \\(g(\\alpha)\\) for \\(\\alpha \\in R\\) such that \\(g(\\alpha)=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{6}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{3}} \\frac{\\sin ^{\\alpha} x}{\\cos ^{\\alpha} x+\\sin ^{\\alpha} x} d x\\)?",
        "options": [
            "g(\\alpha) is a strictly increasing function",
            "g(\\alpha) is an even function",
            "g(\\alpha) has an inflection point at \\(\\alpha=-\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
            "g(\\alpha) is a strictly decreasing function"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& g(\\alpha)=\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{\\sin ^{\\alpha}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-x\\right)}{\\cos ^{\\alpha}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-x\\right) x+\\sin ^{\\alpha}\\left(\\frac{\\pi}{2}-x\\right)} d x \\\\\n& =\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{\\cos ^{\\alpha} x}{\\sin ^{\\alpha} x+\\cos ^{\\alpha} x} d x \\\\\n& \\therefore 2 . g(\\alpha)=\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} \\frac{\\sin ^{\\alpha} x+\\cos ^{\\alpha} x}{\\sin ^{\\alpha} x+\\cos ^{\\alpha} x} d x=\\int_{\\pi / 6}^{\\pi / 3} d x=\\frac{\\pi}{3}-\\frac{\\pi}{6}=\\frac{\\pi}{6} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow g(\\alpha)=\\frac{\\pi}{12} \\text { i.e. a constant function hence an even function. }\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 25
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "question": "Let \\(P(x)=x^{2}+bx+c\\) be a quadratic polynomial with real coefficients such that \\(\\int_{0}^{1} P(x) d x=1\\) and \\(P(x)\\) leaves remainder 5 when it is divided by \\((x-2)\\). Then the value of \\(9(b+c)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "9",
            "11",
            "7",
            "15"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n(x-2) Q(x)+5=x^{2}+b x+c\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { Put } \\mathrm{x}=2 \\\\\n& 5=2 \\mathrm{~b}+\\mathrm{c}+4 \\ldots \\text { (1) } \\\\\n& \\int_{0}^{1}\\left(x^{2}+b x+c\\right) d x=1 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\frac{1}{3}+\\frac{b}{2}+c=1 \\\\\n& \\frac{b}{2}+c=\\frac{2}{3} \\ldots .(2)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nSolve (1) \\& (2)\n\n\\(b=\\frac{2}{9}\\)\\\\\n\\(c=\\frac{5}{9}\\)\n\n\\(9(b+c)=7\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 25
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "question": "Consider the integral \\(I=\\int_{0}^{10} \\frac{[x] e^{[x]}}{e^{x-1}} d x\\) where \\([x]\\) denotes the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(x\\). Then the value of \\(I\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "45(e-1)",
            "45(e+1)",
            "9(e+1)",
            "9(e-1)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I=\\int_{0}^{10}[x] \\cdot e^{[x]+1-x} d x \\\\\n& =\\int_{0}^{1} 0 d x+\\int_{1}^{2} e^{2-x} d x+\\int_{2}^{3} 2 \\cdot e^{3-x} d x+\\int_{3}^{4} 3 \\cdot e^{4-x} d x+\\ldots \\ldots \\ldots+\\int_{9}^{10} 9 e^{10-x} d x \\\\\n& =-\\{(1-e)+2(1-e)+3(1-e)+\\ldots \\ldots .+9(1-e)\\} \\\\\n& =45(e-1)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 25
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "question": "For \\(x>0\\), if \\(f(x)=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{\\log _{e} t}{(1+t)} d t\\), then \\(f(e)+f\\left(\\frac{1}{e}\\right)\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{1}{2}",
            "-1",
            "0",
            "1"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\nf(x)=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{\\ln t}{1+t} d t\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\text { then } f\\left(\\frac{1}{x}\\right)=\\int_{1}^{1 / x} \\frac{\\ln t}{1+t} d t\n\\]\n\nLet \\(t=\\frac{1}{u} \\Rightarrow d t=-\\frac{1}{u^{2}} d u\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow f\\left(\\frac{1}{x}\\right)=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{\\ln \\frac{1}{u}}{1+\\frac{1}{u}}\\left(-\\frac{1}{u^{2}}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(f\\left(\\frac{1}{x}\\right)=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{\\ln u}{u(1+u)} d u=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{\\ln t}{t(1+t)} d t\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore f(x)+f\\left(\\frac{1}{x}\\right)=\\int_{1}^{x} \\ln t\\left(\\frac{1}{1+t}+\\frac{1}{t}-\\frac{1}{t+1}\\right) d t\\)\\\\\n\\(=\\int_{1}^{x} \\frac{\\ln t}{t} d t=\\frac{1}{2}(\\ln x)^{2}\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore f(e)+f\\left(\\frac{1}{e}\\right)=\\frac{1}{2}(\\ln e)^{2}=\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 25
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\sum_{n=1}^{100} \\int_{n=1}^{n} e^{x-[x]} d x\\), where \\([x]\\) is the greatest integer \\(\\leq x\\), is:",
        "options": [
            "100 \\mathrm{e}",
            "100(e-1)",
            "100(1+e)",
            "100(1-e)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(\\sum_{n=1}^{100} \\int_{n-1}^{n} e^{x-[x]} d x\\)\n\nHere, \\(n-1 \\leq x<n\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore[x]=n-1\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore \\int_{n-1}^{n} e^{x-(n-1)} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\left[e^{x-(n-1)}\\right]_{n-1}^{n}\\)\n\n\\(=e^{1}-e^{0}\\)\n\n\\(=e-1\\)\n\nNow, \\(\\sum_{n=1}^{100}(e-1)=100(e-1)\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 25
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{-\\pi / 2}^{\\pi / 2} \\frac{\\cos ^{2} x}{1+3^{x}} d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "2 \\pi",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{2}",
            "4 \\pi",
            "\\frac{\\pi}{4}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\text { Let } I=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\frac{\\cos ^{2} x}{1+3^{x}} d x\n\\]\n\nReplace \\(x\\) with \\(-x\\),\n\n\\[\n\\therefore I=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\frac{\\cos ^{2} x}{1+\\frac{1}{3^{x}}} \\cdots\n\\]\n\nAdding (1) and (2), we get,\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& 2 I=\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\frac{\\cos ^{2} x\\left(1+3^{x}\\right)}{1+3^{x}} d x \\\\\n& =\\int_{-\\frac{\\pi}{2}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\cos ^{2} x d x\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n[ \\(\\cos ^{2} x\\) is a even function as \\(f(x)=f(-x)\\) for \\(\\cos ^{2} x\\) ]\n\n\\(=2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\cos ^{2} x d x\\)\n\n\\(=2 \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}\\left(\\frac{1+\\cos 2 x}{2}\\right) d x\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow I=\\frac{1}{2} \\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}}(1+\\cos 2 x) d x\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\frac{1}{2}[x+\\sin 2 x]_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{2}\\left[\\frac{\\pi}{2}-0\\right] \\\\\n& =\\frac{\\pi}{4}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 25
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "question": "If \\(I_{n}=\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\cot ^{n} x d x\\), then:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{1}{I_{2}+I_{4}}, \\frac{1}{I_{3}+I_{5}}, \\frac{1}{I_{4}+I_{6}} are in A.P.",
            "I_{2}+I_{4}, I_{3}+I_{5}, I_{4}+I_{6} are in A.P.",
            "\\frac{1}{I_{2}+I_{4}}, \\frac{1}{I_{3}+I_{5}}, \\frac{1}{I_{4}+I_{6}} are in G.P.",
            "I_{2}+I_{4},\\left(I_{3}+I_{5}\\right)^{2}, I_{4}+I_{6} are in G.P."
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& I_{n}=\\int_{\\pi / 4}^{\\pi / 2} \\cot ^{n} x d x=\\int_{\\pi / 4}^{\\pi / 2} \\cot ^{n-2} x\\left(\\operatorname{cosec}^{2} x-1\\right) d x \\\\\n& =\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\cot ^{n-2} x \\cdot \\operatorname{cosec}^{2} x d x-\\int_{\\frac{\\pi}{4}}^{\\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\cot ^{n-2} x d x \\\\\n& \\left.=\\frac{\\cot ^{n-1} x}{n-1}\\right]_{\\pi / 4}^{\\pi / 2}-I_{n-2} \\\\\n& =\\frac{1}{n-1}-I_{n-2} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow I_{n}+I_{n-2}=\\frac{1}{n-1} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow I_{2}+I_{4}=\\frac{1}{3} \\\\\n& I_{3}+I_{5}=\\frac{1}{4} \\\\\n& I_{4}+I_{6}=\\frac{1}{5} \\\\\n& \\therefore \\frac{1}{I_{2}+I_{4}}, \\frac{1}{I_{3}+I_{5}}, \\frac{1}{I_{4}+I_{6}} \\text { are in A.P. }\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 25
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "question": "The value of \\(\\int_{-1}^{1} x^{2} e^{\\left[x^{3}\\right]} d x\\), where \\([t]\\) denotes the greatest integer \\(\\leq t\\), is:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{e+1}{3}",
            "\\frac{e-1}{3 e}",
            "\\frac{1}{3 e}",
            "\\frac{e+1}{3 e}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(I=\\int_{-1}^{1} x^{2} e^{\\left[x^{3}\\right]} d x\\)\n\nHere \\(-1 \\leq x \\leq 1\\) then \\(-1 \\leq x^{3} \\leq 1\\)\n\nInteger between -1 and 1 is 0 . So integration will be divided into two parts, -1 to 0 and 0 to 1 .\n\n\\(=\\int_{-1}^{0} x^{2} e^{-1} d x+\\int_{0}^{1} x^{2} e^{0} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\\\int_{-1}^{0} x^{2} e^{-1} d x+\\int_{0}^{1} x^{2} e^{0} d x\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{e} \\times\\left[\\frac{x^{3}}{3}\\right]_{-1}^{0}+\\left[\\frac{x^{3}}{3}\\right]_{0}^{1}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{e} \\times\\left(0-\\left(\\frac{-1}{3}\\right)\\right)+\\frac{1}{3}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{1}{3 e}+\\frac{1}{3}=\\frac{1+e}{3 e}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 26
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "question": "The area of the region: \\(R=\\left\\{(x, y): 5 x^{2} \\leq y \\leq 2 x^{2}+9\\right\\}\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "6 \\sqrt{3} square units",
            "12 \\sqrt{3} square units",
            "11 \\sqrt{3} square units",
            "9 \\sqrt{3} square units"
        ],
        "solution": "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-108}\n\\end{center}\n\nRequired area\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =2 \\int_{0}^{\\sqrt{3}}\\left(2 x^{2}+9-5 x^{2}\\right) d x \\\\\n& =2 \\int_{0}^{\\sqrt{3}}\\left(9-3 x^{2}\\right) d x \\\\\n& =2\\left|9 x-x^{3}\\right|_{0}^{\\sqrt{3}}=12 \\sqrt{3}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 26
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "question": "Let \\(f(x)\\) be a differentiable function defined on \\([0,2]\\) such that \\(f^{\\prime}(x)=f^{\\prime}(2-x)\\) for all \\(x\\) in \\((0,2)\\), \\(f(0)=1\\) and \\(f(2)=\\mathrm{e}^{2}\\). Then the value of \\(\\int_{0}^{2} f(x) d x\\) is:",
        "options": [
            "1+\\mathrm{e}^{2}",
            "2\\left(1+e^{2}\\right)",
            "1-\\mathrm{e}^{2}",
            "2\\left(1-\\mathrm{e}^{2}\\right)"
        ],
        "solution": "\\(f^{\\prime}(x)=f^{\\prime}(2-x)\\)\n\nOn integrating both side \\(f(x)=-f(2-x)+c\\)\n\nput \\(x=0\\)\n\n\\(f(0)+f(2)=c \\Rightarrow c=1+e^{2}\\)\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\Rightarrow f(x)+\\mathrm{f}(2-\\mathrm{x})=1+\\mathrm{e}^{2} \\ldots . . \\text { (i) } \\\\\n& I=\\int_{0}^{2} f(x) d x=\\int_{0}^{1}\\{f(x)+f(2-x)\\} d x=\\left(1+e^{2}\\right)\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "A",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 26
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "question": "The value of the integral, \\(\\int_{1}^{3}\\left[x^{2}-2 x-2\\right] d x\\), where \\([x]\\) denotes the greatest integer less than or equal to \\(x\\), is:",
        "options": [
            "-5",
            "-\\sqrt{2}-\\sqrt{3}+1",
            "-4",
            "-\\sqrt{2}-\\sqrt{3}-1"
        ],
        "solution": "NULL",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "D",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 26
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "question": "If a curve \\(y=f(x)\\) passes through the point \\((1,2)\\) and satisfies \\(x \\frac{d y}{d x}+y=b x^{4}\\), then for what value of \\(b\\), \\(\\int_{1}^{2} f(x) d x=\\frac{62}{5}\\)?",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{31}{5}",
            "10",
            "5",
            "\\frac{62}{5}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\frac{d y}{d x}+\\frac{y}{x}=b x^{3}, I . F .=e^{\\int \\frac{d x}{x}}=x \\\\\n& \\therefore y x=\\int b x^{4} d x=\\frac{b x^{5}}{5}+C\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\nPasses through \\((1,2)\\), we get\n\n\\(2=\\frac{b}{5}+C\\)\n\nAlso, \\(\\int_{1}^{2}\\left(\\frac{b x^{4}}{5}+\\frac{c}{x}\\right) d x=\\frac{62}{5}\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow \\frac{b}{25} \\times 32+C \\ln 2-\\frac{b}{25}=\\frac{62}{5} \\Rightarrow C=0 \\& b=10\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "B",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 26
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "question": "The area (in units) of the part of the circle \\(x^{2}+y^{2}=36\\), which is outside the parabola \\(y^{2}=9 x\\), is:",
        "options": [
            "12 \\pi-3 \\sqrt{3}",
            "24 \\pi+3 \\sqrt{3}",
            "24 \\pi-3 \\sqrt{3}",
            "12 \\pi+3 \\sqrt{3}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_06_11_5bae6af2ed6dc69baf79g-110}\n\\end{center}\n\n\\(x^{2}+y^{2}=36\\) and \\(y^{2}=9 x\\)\n\n\\(\\therefore x^{2}+9 x-36=0\\)\n\n\\(\\Rightarrow x=3,-12\\)\n\nRequired Area,\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& A=\\pi(6)^{2}-2\\left[A_{1}+A_{2}\\right] \\\\\n& A=\\pi(6)^{2}-2\\left[\\int_{0}^{3} \\sqrt{9 x} d x+\\int_{3}^{6} \\sqrt{36-x^{2}} d x\\right] \\\\\n& =36 \\pi-2\\left[\\left[3 \\times \\frac{2}{3} x^{\\frac{3}{2}}\\right]_{0}^{3}+\\left[\\frac{x}{2} \\sqrt{36-x^{2}}+\\frac{36}{2} \\sin ^{-1} \\frac{x}{6}\\right]_{3}^{6}\\right]\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\[\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =36 \\pi-2\\left[\\left[2 x^{\\frac{3}{2}}\\right]_{0}^{3}+\\left[\\frac{x}{2} \\sqrt{36-x^{2}}+18 \\sin ^{-1} \\frac{x}{6}\\right]_{3}^{6}\\right] \\\\\n& =36 \\pi-2\\left[[6 \\sqrt{3}-0]+\\left[\\left(0+18 \\sin ^{-1} \\frac{6}{6}\\right)-\\left(\\frac{3}{2} \\times 3 \\sqrt{3}+18 \\sin ^{-1} \\frac{3}{6}\\right)\\right]\\right] \\\\\n& =36 \\pi-2\\left[[6 \\sqrt{3}]+\\left[\\left(\\frac{18 \\pi}{2}\\right)-\\left(\\frac{3}{2} \\times 3 \\sqrt{3}+\\frac{18 \\pi}{6}\\right)\\right]\\right] \\\\\n& =24 \\pi-3 \\sqrt{3}\n\\end{aligned}\n\\]\n\n\\section*{Note :}\n(i) \\(\\int \\sqrt{x^{2}+a^{2}} d x=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[x \\sqrt{x^{2}+a^{2}}+a^{2} \\log \\left|x+\\sqrt{x^{2}+a^{2}}\\right|\\right]+C\\)\n\n(ii) \\(\\int \\sqrt{a^{2}-x^{2}} d x=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[x \\sqrt{a^{2}-x^{2}}+a^{2} \\sin ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{x}{a}\\right)\\right]+C\\)\n\n(iii) \\(\\int \\sqrt{x^{2}-a^{2}} d x=\\frac{1}{2}\\left[x \\sqrt{x^{2}-a^{2}}-a^{2} \\log \\left|x+\\sqrt{x^{2}-a^{2}}\\right|\\right]+C\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 26
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "question": "\\(\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0} \\frac{\\int_{0}^{x^{2}}(\\sin \\sqrt{t}) d t}{x^{3}}\\) is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "\\frac{1}{15}",
            "0",
            "\\frac{2}{3}",
            "\\frac{3}{2}"
        ],
        "solution": "\\[\n\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0^{+}} \\frac{\\int_{0}^{x^{2}} \\sin (\\sqrt{t}) d t}{x^{3}}\n\\]\n\nThis is in \\(\\frac{0}{0}\\) form, so use L' Hospital rule\n\n\\[\n=\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0^{+}} \\frac{\\frac{d}{d x}\\left(\\int_{0}^{x^{2}} \\sin (\\sqrt{t}) d t\\right)}{\\frac{d}{d x}\\left(x^{3}\\right)}\n\\]\n\n\\(=\\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0^{+}} \\frac{\\sin x \\cdot 2 x-0}{3 x^{2}}\\)\n\n(applying Leibnitz rule)\n\n\\(=\\frac{2}{3} \\lim _{x \\rightarrow 0^{+}} \\frac{\\sin x}{x}\\)\n\n\\(=\\frac{2}{3}\\)",
        "question_type": "MCQ",
        "answer": "C",
        "CourseSubjectName": "Integration",
        "LessonId": 26
    }
]